So Gabi sent to the
end.
So welcome to
Symposium 15.
We will look at operationalizing digital twins for
biodiversity, and we'll have a few talks to
introduce this process. So first, we'll
hear from Matthias Dillen about BMD and their work
with
the Cubing Engine. I will do all
of the presentations. And then Lena will
look a bit about the European data space
in Klaus' team.
Then Laura Slater will
help us a bit with the buzzwords and getting through all the
words that we need to know.
Then Peter Desmet will
look a little bit about monitoring and twins in
that. There's Peter Desmet.
And then Shirin will
close off with digital
twins on ecosystems, and you were sitting there.
So welcome up.
And
Sharif, yeah.
I flipped through. I also forgot Tanja.
Is Tanja here?
I didn't see her yet. So maybe she's coming.
So Tanja will also show us
the infrastructure, our keynote from the first day.
So
welcome up, Matthias. Can you
remind people that-
Yes. And then Sharif also reminds me to remind you that we
have an unconference, so you should submit topics.
So we have work
to cover up topics that you want to have discussed and which we
haven't covered yet in
this conference. So thank you, and I leave the word to
Matthias.
All right. Hi. Good morning, everyone.
I'm Matthias Dillen from Meise Botanic Garden, and I'm going to
talk to you about the Cubing Engine, a tool we've been working on in the
Biodiversity Meets Data project, and which is intended to harmonize
biodiversity observation data with Earth observation and other abiotic
predictor data.
So see if my
slides
can make it on this big screen.
You have to do it on the device.
Okay, so I have to go in presentation mode then?
You could just slide it
to the right.
That looks good?
Yes.
Okay. On zoom.
Like this way.
Yeah?
Yeah, and then
slide it to the... Yeah. And then click the
bigger again.
One button.
Yeah.
Okay.
I think that's fine in the context of not losing too much time.
All right. So as I said, Biodiversity Meets Data, the Cubing Engine,
which I've been working on, and in particular, my colleague, Niels Bilit, who's not
here today, but who did a lot of the development.
So now I do need to
move ahead. Is this going to work?
Okay, so maybe just try to
do-
And probably go full screen.
Up and next, yeah.
But I think we're already full screen.
No, we have already full screen? Okay.
So if you just click on it.
It might not have been highlighted. Let's just try it again.
Ah.
Okay, now it's working.
Yeah, the window was not selected, I guess.
Okay.
Now that we got that out of the way.
So first a bit about the Biodiversity meets Data project, which is quite an
ambitious project, with the idea to build a whole pipeline going from a data
catalog of different resources to a set of analytical tools that are
easy to use for downstream users, in particular managers of Natura 2000 sites.
For all of that to work, there needs to be a whole ecosystem making these analyses
work. One of the key components is a central harmonization layer,
which takes data from the catalog, harmonizes it to, for instance, same
squared reference system, but also other transformations, and feeds
those to, that's the idea in the end, an API to the analytical
tools. So
to make that work, we need quite a bit of technical
setup to optimize this and to make it scalable.
For that, we also wanted to build on the tools developed in the D3
project, which recently finished, and in which an extra
API was developed for GBIF, which facilitates exporting
data into a resampled manner called cubes, which also makes them
safer to use,
considering that they often have very heterogeneous data in the background.
So this is what it looks like, the more or
less architectural structure
of the cubing engine. So there's a considerable back end, which is as
modular as possible, and a very slim and
as tiny as possible front end to make it as easy to use as possible.
I'm going to go into a bit more depth into both in the
next few slides, but not into too much detail because there's not that much
time in this presentation. So first, the back end, as modular as
possible. Central to it is this base grid class, which lists the
currently supported grids and coordinate reference systems.
It could be extended in the future for more.
Currently, it supports the
EEA grid and the Global Eco Area one and
WGS84.
Then very close to that are the raster and vector engines, which are really
geospatial classes intended to just optimize and
just focus on the geospatial transformations like snapping to grids and
reprojecting needed for the harmonization, completely abstracted from the
different data sources.
Then we have the data cube orchestrator, which orchestrates the different
harmonization processes with different data sources that are needed and has as
abstract child classes, this raster and vector cube
class, which
are abstract classes. And
as child classes of those, we have classes for each different data
source that the cubing engine currently supports, making it very easy to
extend because in principle, all you have to do is create another child
class, which indicates the logic needed to access the data and to convert it
to the central data model that the cubing engine expects.
In the front end, we have
one main class called BMDCube, and in principle, what it mainly is
intended to do is read a markup language file, a YAML
file,
which includes the recipe of what the cubing engine is supposed to do in terms of
harmonization, which data sources it's supposed to access, and according to which
dimensions. And in principle, if you feed that YAML
file into this function, and you wait long enough,
depending on how heavy the operation is, you get the output
without minimal
skills in terms of coding notebooks and having to process the code
on your end.
So the output that is created out of this is a data
tree of the harmonized files that you want to have,
split up for raster and vector files, but harmonized to the same
master grid.
There's a stack file, which describes the cube, its internal structure, so it could
be indexed and makes it more easy to find the cube if you develop a large
storage space for them, which is the intention in the Biodiversity meets Data
project, and a provenance record which details, for instance, the
runtime, the version of the cubing engine used, the version of the dependencies
used, and the hardware underneath it.
So all to optimize and to make sure that the whole process is as reusable
and reproducible as possible.
So in principle, this is the minimal line of code that you could use
to launch a cubing engine process and get the cubing engine output in the
end.
And this is an example of how the output looks.
So you have different folders for the different data sources with different files,
depending on how many variables there are, and we have a more complex setup for
vector output. So you have the original vector items, but also harmonized to the
grid. And
you can easily stream those files from a central storage layer, so you don't have
to download the whole cube. If you want it, you can actually be more flexible and
only access the files that you need from this cube.
This is a bit about the software stack.
So the whole tool is built in Python.
It obviously uses some of the common geospatial libraries,
such as GDAL for the geospatial processing, GeoPandas to
store the objects internally in memory, xarray as the internal central
data model, and Dask and/or DuckDB for
optimized processing, in particular for very large files, which tends to
happen with some Earth observation data.
You can see a link to the repository there as well.
And currently for output, we support GeoPark for the vector files
and NetCDF or Zarr for the raster files.
And not importantly, in the current version of the Cubing Engine, we
mainly support data coming from GBIF, from Celsa climate data,
and earth observation data coming through by GEO.
Though we're currently adjusting that pipeline to work directly with the S3 bucket
storage from through Copernicus to make it more
streamlined, and we don't have to bother with
accessing it through the API. We can just access the files directly.
So
finally, I want to go then into a bit more detail on this YAML
recipe file and what it looks like.
So it includes configuration
for
the global configuration, which is mainly just where you
want the output to go, what format you want it to go.
The spatial configuration, so what is the target width, at which
resolution, if you have a bounding box, if you have a temporal resolution
restriction that you want to apply.
And you have some more flexibility, as you can see in the different parameters
here.
Then there are some more data source specific
terms that you can add. These, in principle, need to be
coded into these child classes, which I talked about before.
But oftentimes it's just which variables you want to include, maybe some
specific parameters for these variables.
In this case, as an example of Celsa, it is mainly which models,
which variables, which time ranges for these models that you want to include, which
you need to specify in the recipe. And this may look a bit
complicated, but this is something that you could easily
add a front-end wrapper on top of it with an interface with some form elements.
And so the user would just fill in the form, gets transformed into the YAML file,
fed into the function, and the Cubing Engine would run.
For GBIF, it can get a bit more complicated.
There's also a bit more flexibility.
There's a lot of different additional parameters you could use.
So you can look at different taxon keys that you want to focus on, at which taxon
ranks you want to aggregate them. You can have different parameters for the
uncertainty. You can have a default uncertainty, minimum or maximum.
You can exclude some issues that GBIF flags to the data.
And there's also some options
for vector processing. So as I said very quickly before,
GBIF now supports resampling some of its occurrence data through the SQL
API using some cubing functions.
We also incorporated that logic into the Cubing Engine, but extended it a bit, so
you can now also, through the Cubing Engine, do a more Monte Carlo resampling, so
you have much more resampling of the same point.
And you can also snap that to grid cells at a fractional
output, or also turn that into a point cloud, all to account for the
heterogeneous underlying data.
In terms of future plans, we plan to add more data sources to the Cubing
Engine. That's one of the key prints that we want to do.
That will still go under the banner of the BMD project because plenty of more
data sources are needed.
We plan to publish that as a package as well.
That will probably happen after the refactor from GEO has been done.
And
yes, and not least, we also plan to deploy it as an
internal service in the Biodiversity Data Project so the different analytical
tools can access it through an API.
The API also governs the waiting time and leads them to the outputs where it is
stored, so it can be easily streamed from there.
I think that was
it in a nutshell. There's some links here at the bottom,
link to the repository again. There's some tutorials, notebooks, how to use that in
practice. We have a deliverable report, which is published on Zenodo.
You can access to that for some more information.
And other than that,
thank you on behalf also of my colleague, Nils.
And if you have any questions, feel free to ask them.
So we have time for one or two questions.
I don't see any in the chat. Do you see any?
No. A question or two?
Yep. Tania.
Did you turn it on?
It's okay. Can you hear?
Yes.
Okay, great.
Great talk. And so
as you
alluded that there are other data sources, and
are you looking also extending it to other ways of
slicing and dicing the data, not just repeated sampling,
so that the spatial, temporal-- Sorry, that the temporal
repetition of the spatial--
No, but there are many ways to organize data and
many ways to
get a repeat
and organize surveys. There's
clearly, and different data sources, including
bioacoustics,
visual,
constantly extending array of camera traps and all of the
citizen science efforts and so on.
By design, since you're designing it, how much flexibility
can you envision building into it in the current structure, and how can
you modify it to add that flexibility?
So the question is about how modifiable and extensible
the Cubing Engine is for more complicated surveying and
sampling efforts, in particular of biodiversity data.
Have I got that correct? Yeah. So we have some support
for that currently.
And that could be extended, like the whole resampling procedure that I talked
about, turning it into point data with some uncertainty into point
clouds. So more complicated vector objects than these simple points
with uncertainty around them could be accommodated.
We'd have to see how that looks like in the data sources that we're talking about,
because for biodiversity observation data, we've currently been focusing on GBIF,
and the massive bulk of data in there is typically points with uncertainty
around them. But given the methods that we have implemented
It shouldn't be that hard unless there are
obstacles that we haven't foreseen that complicate the internal data model for
accommodating these kind of objects.
Then we'd have to design additional methods to account for those, and
that may be a bit trickier because then you're looking at changing the code
internally, and that may lead to unforeseen consequences or possible
refactors.
Does that answer your question?
Thank you. Then I think we'll move on. We're on time.
So Lena,
her talk will be a video. Or
do we need to start it here?
This is also connecting to the Biodiversity Meets Data
Project, and
do you have it?
Do you need to start it from here?
I don't have access to-
Okay, we're getting help.
We should have practiced, I think, starting the presentations
and video.
And she will look a bit at the European data
spaces and
how to operationalize these twins using that.
Hello, I'm Lena Pertzelmaier and-
I will shut up.
Hello, I'm Lena Pertzelmaier, and I'm working
at Senckenberg in Frankfurt, Germany, and I'm part of the
Biodiversity Meets Data Project,
for which I will present today their workflows and how they
fit into the European biodiversity data space.
So I want to start with an example that we use a lot in BMD, which
is where we have two stakeholders.
On the one side, we have a scientist, and the scientist, in this
case, an ecologist, for example, develops a really good species
distribution model for predicting where a species might occur
today and also in the future with changing climate.
And on the other side, we have a Natura 2000 site manager,
which are the main stakeholders in BMD.
And those site managers, they want to understand how a
certain invasive species may expand within their conservation
area. So there's a clear link between the scientist and the
Natura 2000 site manager, and the Natura 2000 site manager
would really benefit from having a way
to reuse and access the model
outputs that the scientists produce.
So the question is, how can this be achieved?
And this is where the workflow engine that we've developed comes in.
So the first step that the scientist needs to take
is an obvious one. They would need to share their code.
So that actually enables others to inspect the code, and if they are
skilled enough, they can also try to reuse it.
But obviously, this often leads to troubles because we also need to
have the right environment and the right dependencies installed.
That's why we don't only want the scientists to publish their code, but also, you
guessed it, containerize it.
So that way, the model becomes portable and executable.
But that's not enough to actually understand how the model is working.
If the model has different steps that need to follow each other, we need to know
that.
We also need to know which inputs are required for the model to run, and we
also would like to know beforehand which outputs are produced.
This is why we also require the scientist to define a
workflow. Workflows basically consist of
defining inputs, steps, and outputs.
There are many different workflow specifications that can be used for
this task. In BMD, we mainly work with Argo, but
have also considered the common workflow language.
But the important part is no matter which workflow specification you use, it
usually also comes with a workflow runner that can actually execute
your workflow. And those workflow runners, they can also
run on remote infrastructure. So actually, if you have
access to a remote
execution infrastructure that supports the workflow language,
the site managers don't need to run the
workflows and the model on their local machines anymore, which might have
very limited hardware specs,
but they can actually easily run the model on a
remote machine.
So now we have something like this, where the Natura 2000 site
manager can submit a workflow to a workflow engine, and then
once the workflow engine finished, he receives the
workflows back and has the results.
But this process is still missing very important information.
So the workflow itself does not have any license information, so we don't even know
if we are allowed to reuse the workflow.
We also don't have an author attribution
or things like descriptions and keywords to understand what the workflow is
about. We also don't know in which workflow language this
workflow specification is written, and thus, if our
workflow engine is actually able to execute the model.
And this is where
metadata comes in, and in our case, we went for the Workflow
RO-Crate profile to describe the workflows that have been developed.
The main entity that has been introduced for that is the
computational workflow,
which basically describes the script
that describes the workflow, which is also part of the Workflow RO-Crate.
And this computational workflow is then again described by many other
entities, such as the creator, or which programming
language, and also it defines the inputs that are required
and the outputs that are expected.
So this way of looking at a workflow is also called the
prospective provenance. It is a way of looking at the workflow
before it is initiated or before it is executed.
It's a kind of a general workflow description,
like a recipe that has not yet been executed.
But we also want to have a way how to describe workflows that have actually been
run and that have produced results.
And for that, we use the workflow run RO-Crate profile, which is
basically an extension of the workflow RO-Crate profile, as you can
see, and it adds as a main entity this create action,
which references the computational workflow.
It also specifies an agent which
triggered this execution, and it specifies
the objects, which are the values that
are used as an input parameter. So for example, if the
formal parameter, the input, says species name,
this object, this property value, then defines exactly
for which species this workflow has run.
And last but not least, obviously it also contains information
about the results that have been produced, which you can also see here because
this workflow RO-Crate
now also contains an
outputs folder with all the generated files.
So in total, our workflow engine architecture looks
like this. So in the middle of it sits the RO-Crate service, which
connects user interfaces, workflow engines, and workflow registries.
And the flow is basically that the user interface
submits a workflow RO-Crate to the RO-Crate service, which then
unpacks the workflow manifest and submits that to a workflow engine.
Once the workflow has been executed, the RO-Crate receives the workflow run
information and uses that to package it again into a
workflow run RO-Crate. This run RO-Crate is
then fed back to the user interfaces and can also be published
on different workflow registries.
As you can see, we have multiple user interfaces and multiple workflow
engines deployed. One implementation is Workflow.earth,
which is deployed in Destination Earth, where also the workflow engine
sits. And it was our first implementation of a workflow
engine
focusing on agricultural digital twins.
And on the other side, we have the BMD BAT platform.
And
the workflow engine for this BAT platform is deployed
at our BMD partner, LifeWatch ERIC.
And as you can see, there are different workflow registries to which the
workflows can be published, such as, for example, the BMD
DataSpace, Workflow Hub, or Workflow.earth.
So now I want to show you our implementation of Workflow.earth,
where you can see here now a detailed view of a
workflow that has been run. You can see that it contains
standard information,
the title, description, and so on.
And it also contains provenance information, so when was the workflow triggered,
with which parameters, and so on. All of this information comes from
the workflow run RO-Crate, which is rendered in a human-readable way
here on this web page of Workflow.earth.
So for a human, this is quite clear what this web page is about, but the thing
is, a machine arriving at this page has no idea what it is about
without having to go into the page itself and try to
analyze that.
This is why FAIR Signposting has been developed.
FAIR Signposting basically provides information to machines
already in the HTTPS header,
and it contains information like
what is this page even about? Is there some information that
describes this in a closer way? What is the license of this page,
who authored it, and so on.
Usually, this signposting information is not visible to the user
browsing on the web page, but you can actually
visualize the signposting by using a signposting sniffer, at least in the
Chrome browser.
So what we have developed actually on Workflow.earth is that we
combine a unique identifier that gives each workflow a clear
identity
with RO-Crates that package the workflow, the metadata, the provenance,
and so on,
and FAIR Signposting, which makes information
easy to find on the web also for machines.
And
with all of that, we actually are able to expose those workflow
runs as W3C FAIR Digital Objects, which means we can
provide the workflow information and all the details that
belong to this workflow in a both human-readable and also in a
machine-actionable way.
So lastly, I want to show you the user interface that is being
developed in BMD.
It has the same
back end as the Workflow.earth platform,
but it is being developed with the special needs and requirements that the
Natura 2000 stakeholders have.
So basically, you can go to the page and browse the different workflows that are
available,
and then once you select a workflow, you can define the different
parameters in an
interactive way. So you can select the species that you're interested in from a
drop-down list, you can select the area you're interested in on the map
directly, and then you can submit the workflow.
The workflow then goes to the LifeWatch ERIC workflow engine.
And once it is finished, it produces also this kind of dashboard that you can see
here on the right side, which enables The Natura 2000
site manages to directly browse the results in the browser
without having to even download them.
But of course, we also offer them the
possibility to download the results in form of a workflow run
RO-Crate, which then contains all the files, and they can
do with those files whatever they want.
So that being said,
what have we developed to summarize?
So we
focus very much on workflows that are really fair, and we
enforce this also with the workflow engine by
using a standard workflow language and enforcing
that the data also comes with the right metadata, which then
makes the workflows portable, reproducible, and reusable.
We focus also a lot on federated data infrastructures because we
really want to be able to connect to multiple workflow registries and to multiple
workflow execution engines
so the workflows can be shared and reused across institutions.
And we focus on web-fair digital objects by combining
the unique identifier, the RO-Crate, and fair signposting to make
workflows and workflow runs discoverable, citable, machine
actionable on the web.
That's all from my side. I want to thank all the BMD project partners and thank you
for your attention.
So then it's online.
So now we head about some terrestrial twins.
By the way, do you want to have a question or not?
I think we have one.
So I think we'll go on. So now,
many of you were on excursions yesterday, and some of you explored
the Oslo fjord with boats, and Laura and Arne has
made a digital twin of the Oslo fjord.
And she will talk a bit more about coastal twins and integration across
terrestrial and marine
twins.
How do we make them full screen?
So we are ready to go on with the next talk.
So
welcome up Laura from
SINTEF Digital and Designs.
Okay.
Can I get rid of this
thing in front of this so I can see? Am I able to see my slides without
looking up?
Okay. I don't-
I don't think so, maybe. Or-
It's a PDF. So these are PDFs.
So you don't have slide notes.
Yeah, but I don't need the notes-
No
... but I just want to see the slide on the
screen.
No. First of all, I get rid of this.
I can just look up here, too. It's fine. Just...
Mirroring the slide.
Sorry?
To mirror the slide. The slide is not mirrored.
Yeah, I don't- I also provided slides, so I actually have both.
There's PDF and there's a
PowerPoint presentation.
I can fire it up again.
Were the other ones the same?
Yeah, they're exactly the same.
Yes, but the other talks?
I don't know what you mean, sorry.
You can use the PowerPoint and not the PDF.
Ah, okay.
Because I
uploaded both.
No, that's a PowerPoint.
Yeah, but it's okay.
So we present PowerPoint on?
Yeah.
They're the same slides.
Yes.
Okay.
Make full screen.
Yeah.
No, but if you keep it there and make full screen, do you think it will-
Good. Thank you.
Maybe on this side.
It works.
Yeah, but this is the different one, so it's not the
slides, it's the
PDF. This one. Where the...
No reaction.
It's exactly the same presentation. Yeah.
All right.
Hi.
So,
I'm Laura Slaughter, and I work at SINTEF
Digital.
And today I'm going to talk to you about
coastal digital twins,
and some of the work that we've been doing.
So, as you know, coastlines in Norway just go
on forever. We're a country with a lot of coastlines.
And so we have a lot of projects
which are coastal twins.
And just some examples here.
The whole project started with us
looking at how to build different kinds of coastal twins, like
for looking at coastal change,
and looking at coastal storm simulators.
And so as soon as you start to work with coastal data, the marine and the
terrestrial worlds just clash. Right?
And so
you start to run into different problems.
So land and marine data sets describe the same coastal
phenomena but using different concepts and classifications, different feature
types and vocabularies.
In order to do this, you have to combine all different kinds of sensors, both on
land and sea,
different geospatial data sets, different kinds of models.
The coastal twin may need to connect different terrestrial,
marine, hydrological, different environmental and-
Infrastructural data.
We also look at ecosystem of twins, not just
building one twin, but making the twins
also
interact with each other, or just to be able to look at how you
can build up an entire ecosystem.
So that's why we run into this multiple twins problem.
Land and sea data have radically different spatial and temporal
resolutions,
and
we also run into problems with the models and the simulators.
So a digital twin has lots of different
components, so there are a lot of different problem areas, and I just
wanted to give an overview of what those are.
Everything from
provenance tracking to being able to represent spatial and
temporal
information, different units and measurements you're dealing with,
in addition to the semantic interoperability,
and all of those standards.
In addition, you have cross-domain integration,
just two different bodies trying to
talk to each
other. Okay, so what this work was, is basically a landscape analysis,
in which I looked at this question: to what extent do existing
standards, data models, and interoperability approaches support the
integration of heterogeneous land-sea data that's
required by digital twin architectures, and where do the critical
gaps remain?
Okay, so the first thing that I did was that I
looked at the digital twin literature.
Because there's been a lot of work done with land-sea integration,
but not in the context of building digital twins.
So what I looked at was, okay, what are the actual requirements of the
twins that we're building?
And then
I went off into the land-sea integration literature,
and I pulled out what the problem areas were, who's working
on it, and then what are the existing problems, and where are the
gaps and what needs to be solved. And then basically I created this
landscape
map of the existing support and the gaps.
But before I go any further, I'm just going to just step back a
little bit and talk about twins.
I took this slide from another presentation in which I talk about the
history of the concept of digital twins. What are they?
And so
I'm just jumping ahead for you because this is a much shorter
talk, and I just need to explain something
about different concepts of what a digital twin
is. So
in 2002,
there was the start of it. The digital twin was basically
a mirror representation. 2010, NASA brought in
the simulations. But in 2018, there
was a paper in which they described
three different concepts.
So there's the digital model,
which is basically
you're sharing the model. You just model the world.
And
it's just a manual push. There's no automated
connection between the two.
Then you have something called a digital shadow,
and digital shadows are
a lot of what we make. We don't make true twins, we make
digital shadows.
And this is where you have
a digital representation is automatically updated by the physical system, but
it does not automatically act back on it.
So quite a lot of the
demonstrators which we've made are actually digital shadows.
But what we're really working towards is the full-on
digital twin,
in which you have bi-direction. So the digital and the physical system are
connected in both directions, and each can automatically affect the
state of the other.
And
what we're working towards
is
having the twin be able to recommend, for example,
some sort of
intervention,
or to have some kind of automation in
the system. And,
okay, I'll just go back really quick because I have this little note at the top.
So it was in 2018 that you see
this terminology of digital twin
spreading into adjacent domains.
It started in manufacturing, but in 2018, it started to spread, and you start
to see it in agriculture and smart farming.
But in 2021,
it really pushed itself into ecology, into
marine sciences,
and out in the world.
And so
in this publication, Gordon Bellier's publication,
he really talks about his vision of what
twins can do. And
so-
... is talking about
basically a kind of a learning twin.
So
you want to be able to
amend
not just the state, but potentially also the structure of the models.
And so
this is
one of my key goals and one of our key goals is to work on learning
twins.
And so the requirements when you have a digital shadow and when
you have for a full-on digital twin,
they're heavier. You need to be able to
dynamically integrate data.
And so it's much more challenging.
You need to deal with missing data, and yeah,
there's a lot more in terms of
requirements
for the full twin. But in my landscape analysis, I
basically mapped out all of these requirements for
the digital twin.
And then I went out and started to map out what are some of the
issues with the land-sea interface.
And so I put these into different categories.
So there's spatial reference and boundaries
issues there.
So,
one of them is the horizontal coordinate reference system
mismatch.
And many of these have been
addressed. There are different initiatives.
OGC has also addressed this.
But there's still needed work there, so we need consistent implementation
across heterogeneous coastal datasets.
Another problem is this vertical datum mismatch.
So, where's your
floor?
So land elevations and marine depths often use different vertical
datums.
And so this still remains a problem for our twins.
There's the shoreline coastline mismatch.
So you need dynamic representation of a changing shoreline.
This is another problem to solve for our twins.
We've got the land-sea boundary mismatch.
So we need a semantic alignment between different boundary
concepts.
And you have this geometry mismatch, so we have different
geometry representations,
which make direct integration difficult.
Another category of issues is the scale and
spatiotemporal resolution
category. And since I only have two more minutes left, I'm just going
to buzz through all of these. But what I want to say
is that I'm making all this available, so I'll
put it up,
the landscape analysis. So if anyone's interested,
just let me know and
I'll point you to the right place.
So we have scale and spatiotemporal
resolution issues.
Those are spatial resolution mismatches, temporal
mismatches.
Temporal harmonization is
difficult,
as many people know.
So
we have uneven spatial coverage
and
scale-dependent meaning. So
we need better scale-aware semantic models.
In terms of semantic interoperability, it's the classics,
the classic issues. So cross-domain feature mappings remain
incomplete.
We need more explicit land-sea cross-domain mappings.
You'll see in here that I recommend, for example, like
with the terminology differences needing shared land-sea vocabularies.
There are existing land-sea vocabularies.
It's just that
when we start to look at actually solving some of the
issues and building the twins,
we do find that,
or have seen that there are specific issues in
terms of
one concept can have different names or definitions,
different conceptual models. So we need
cross-domain ontologies.
Units and measures is definitely an issue
as usual.
We have data structure and technical interoperability issues, including
schema mismatch, different format mismatches,
incompatibilities in terms of API service.
Static integration becomes outdated, so we need
dynamic integration with minimal information loss.
And again, data silos between the different organizations.
And of course, there's lots of problems around missing data because we have what's
called the white ribbon.
The white ribbon is basically that area which is
too deep for the terrestrial surveys, but too shallow for ships.
So it's that area of the coastline where we actually
have a lot of missing data.
I have to go. So we have also
provenance and
discovery access and fairness issues with the data.
And then there are also institutional and governance interoperability
issues,
and
that's it.
Yeah. So sorry, I went a bit over.
So thank you, Laura.
Yeah.
Maybe one quick question, otherwise, we need to move on to the
next.
Then, yes,
Gabby?
Thank
you. Thank you.
Hello. Well.
It's not working, so.
Actually, it works, but it
only
goes to the online.
Okay. So you quickly went through many of the
challenges.
Yes.
How do you see the solutions coming?
Excellent question. This is very preliminary
work in which we need to make decisions about where to
focus our efforts.
So
yeah.
They will go across different upcoming projects.
As for myself, I'm most interested in the semantic
interoperability issues, but
in order to make the twins function,
there are a lot of other
issues that also need to be resolved, especially
around the geospatial
problems. So
we can talk about it afterwards, but yeah.
That's it. All right. Thank you.
So thank you very much, Laura.
Yeah, thanks.
Now we heard a bit about terrestrial and marine twins,
coastal NEAR, and now Sherif will help us with the buzzwords and
how to tie it all together. In the beginning, when we
worked on the digital twins, we were starting with what is a
twin, and I hope Sherif will help us to understand
better there.
Yeah. Thank you.
So Laura gave a nice background about where these terms came
from, so I will also go to 2018. So this is the
famous Gartner hype cycle curve that
you've probably seen. So as you see, 2018 on the top is
digital twin. And what it does is that it predicts what
happens in the next five years, and it's supposed to come to what they call
the plateau of productivity because it's not a hype anymore.
Of course,
they also have different other hype cycle where it appears in manufacturing and
other things.
So if we jump back to 2025,
I couldn't find 2026, but anyway, but it gives you an idea.
Of course, digital twin is not there anymore.
We have other buzzwords. There's agents, augmented
AI, physical AI, and things like that.
And digital twin does appear in other hype cycles.
But this kind of tells you how
this
happens. So as Laura showed the history, our
BioDT project started in 2022, and the DTO BioFlow,
I think, started 2023. So this helps you to understand that the buzzwords
help us to get these proposals. But in a
way, I do have this love-hate relationship with these
buzzwords because it helps us, but when the project starts,
we have to figure out what exactly is a digital twin, what exactly is
a data space.
So when the real work starts, the buzzwords don't really help
us.
So what we need is, well, this is another buzzword, the data space.
So luckily, it's not in the hype cycle, but you will see in a lot
of in the European funding cycle, this term is used.
If you read the description, secure, trust, reusable, we
all need these things. But if I show you this architectural diagram today
and ask you to do something on Monday, it's probably not going to happen.
So we need a little bit more concrete stuff that goes with these
buzzwords, so that's where I'm coming up with the idea from the buzzword to the
blueprint.
So this is like my punchline. I will give it away.
So where I think things happen
is basically in the middle. Of course, yeah, in the other talks you also
saw there's all these fragmented data sources,
comparing coastal and marine and terrestrial is problematic.
Even within single domain is often problematic.
But in the middle, we need some context and discovery.
So some of these things could be centralized, some of this could be federated.
And where the buzzwords comes from, it's on the consumer side, on the right-hand
side. So that's where probably the media and the funders and the
policymakers are looking at. They're understanding digital twins, they're
understanding
agents.
But if we don't take care of the things on the other side with the data sources and
the governance and the contracts in between, this consumer is probably not
going to be able to do anything.
So I'll give an example of
one of our projects,
which ended, but we also produced something.
So in this publication, we don't go into detail of what exactly
a digital twin. There's other papers we wrote that talks about it, what it means
for ecology and biodiversity. But here, what we try to argue,
specifically when it comes to FAIR with findability,
accessibility, interoperability, and reusability, is that it all boils
down to metadata. And you also saw the examples in the other two talks.
So when you open the lid, open the hood of a digital twin, this is what you see.
We also ran into a lot of human communication issue.
For example, if you talk with somebody with the ecology background, they will say
model calibration. But if you talk with somebody from data science and AI, they
will say model learning or active learning or training and things like that.
So oftentimes, we have to figure those things out.
So one solution is that, of course, the human communication is needed, but
for the machine readability, we came out with these
profiles where we said these very basic things has to
be mandatory, or you have to use profile and extend the profiles.
For example, the version of the model, the datasets, the input and output.
And we also worked a lot on the mappings, to figure
out the
common-
... cross-domain things. So basically, what we are good is that
FAIR is not just for the data. If we bring all of this together, then the digital
twin makes it FAIR, which means that we can
talk with other things.
And then there comes the data space. Again, the same pattern you can see.
So this is coming in the Biodiversity Meets Data, BMD project.
You heard from Matthias what we were doing, and also from Lena.
So for example, we will have these boundary files,
shapefiles, and GeoJSONs file from Natura 2000.
There are species checklist that's coming from European environmental agents.
We will also have survey data with a camera trap eDNA.
So these are all fragmented, even though
there are connecting points coming in.
So what we're focusing on right now is cubing engine is one of the thing that we'll
bring together, but we also have an approach of the discovery of the metadata
as a sort of centralized catalog approach.
And there's also, of course, policy and access control for
restricted species that we have to think about.
And again, on the other side, on the right-hand side, is where, again, the
consumers will come in. It could be a different organization, it could be Natura
2000 sites or other organization that also will need to consume
these things. But again, the idea is that if we don't take care of the things on
the other side,
and especially the middle control plane, the consumers and services
probably won't be able to do anything.
I'll give a brief example, this catalog that we're working on.
So STAC is called Spatio-Temporal Access Catalog.
It's quite recent.
GeoNetwork is within geospatial domain, been there for a while,
but STAC became very popular with our observation data.
The idea is actually very simple. You have a static JSON file.
The JSON file describes a lot of metadata, and basically you serve it with a common
specification and API, and you have some sort of search things.
But within the last few years, this became very popular with lot of different
projects, and we're trying to understand how we can use it with BMD with
all sorts of different types of data.
And of course, provide API and search layer.
So one simple example, let's say you have a large
S3 files that's sitting in a bucket,
and basically what this JSON file does is that tells you what this S3 file is and
points to the bucket. So you could have 20,000 buckets in
20,000 different S3 location.
The JSON could combine them and point to that.
And GeoParquet is also another format that helps you, in a way,
efficiently catalog these things.
And you can query
very nice geospatial query or other metadata query
that can get you this JSON. And there's also extension,
that's
different communities coming in.
So we have some examples in our GitHub repository, but this, again,
shows you this middle layer, the control layer, where the context and the
discovery is needed
for the data space.
So these are concrete example that can help you to get there, and also FAIR and
other things. And similarly, I think the digital twin ecosystem can use some of
these things.
I'll give one more example
to show how the data cube that we talked about earlier.
So Matthias showed that the data cube will also generate a STAC.
And actually, the payload, the file itself is there, but we
need some way to query it. So we need to query to understand
what's the spatial resolution,
what is this cube describing.
So the catalog and the STAC could help us to do that.
And the idea is that both in this case,
we only take what we need. So oftentimes, we see in a lot of
our projects, a lot of people have to download the full data, download the large
CSV files, millions of millions of rows.
So in this new cloud-native format, you don't have to download the whole
thing. You can just say, "Give me this slice based on the query.
I only want to work with this. I want to visualize this part.
I don't have to download the whole thing." Same with the cube.
We can slice it and dice it in a different way and get the information
we need and present to the users as needed.
Because some of our users are policymakers, some are scientists, so it will also
depend how they see it. So in conclusion, how it
comes into, and again, remember the buzzwords will be
coming from the market. It will tell us what is important.
The funders like it. So we do need the buzzwords that help us to
get the proposal
funded, but we need the blueprint to get the work done.
And you already heard a lot about the standards and the metadata.
I think that's very important. That's a very
important foundation layer that we need.
And TADWIG is foundational for supporting some of these things.
But we also working with Open Geospatial Community and
other standards as well to bring them together.
And governance oftentimes is behind the scene, but we need that.
We need support for stewardships, both for the data and the model.
So the concept of the data space brings them together.
And it's also nice way to show our funders
without the governance and stewardship, some of these things won't happen.
And of course, yeah, we have to remember that there are people consuming it.
There are the users, services, they're coming in different flavors.
Oftentimes, they probably don't care about what's in the
bottom, this contract and governance. They just want to get the visualization.
They just want to get the data and move on.
But
we have to have these in the blueprint for them to understand what's going on with
their use case. So in conclusion, basically, buzzwords are
there. We have to use them to get the funding.
But after the funding
is received, use the buzzword and break it down to a blueprint
to get something useful. Yeah. Thank you.
I didn't see any questions in the chat.
Any questions-
We have time for one or two more
... in the room?
One question.
Or should we move on?
Can you help us to load Tanya's slides? You're so good at loading yours.
Oh, sure.
So now we looked a bit about how we
were building a few twins.
Yeah.
Yeah. And now,
when we were building these twins, we grappled with
representing the physical-
To move the mouse
... domain in the digital twin.
Yeah.
And now,
an important part of these twins is that they are making actions, that they are
actually modifying
the-
Yeah
... physical environment. And now Tanya will show us a bit about
these autonomies, how they interact back and give feedback into the
system they model. Thank you.
Thank you. Yes. So I am Tanya Berger-Wolf, but I'm
impersonating Jenna Klein,
who was my PhD student, now postdoc at
Massachusetts Institute of Technology, MIT, still
working on drones, and a whole team of students
who did this work. So what we're adding in this
conversation is, or in this proposal, is the
systems part of all the sensor integration to the
digital twin concept.
Because over the last
20 years or so, there's been an explosion of technology that can provide
biodiversity and ecological data
from remote sensing satellites, autonomous vehicles,
underwater, as we heard also earlier today, underwater, on the ground, in the air,
on-body sensors that you can put like GPS tags, and
increasingly pretty much everything measuring about an individual animal,
and walk with it, camera traps, acoustic recorder, eDNA,
citizen science. So there's ton, and increasingly this
technology is being developed
more and more. And so what we're getting today...
Sorry, I'm going to stand here.
If we truly do want to monitor at scale, and today there was
announced the launch, for example, of at-scale monitoring
of the entire Amazon. So Amazon.ai project was
announced today at the Climate Week by the UN.
And so this kind of at-scale monitoring requires
cross-modal coordination because different modalities capture different parts
of the ecological signals, and they're complementary.
There are unique signals that are captured by unique modalities
at unique scales of spatiotemporal resolutions.
And so the
leveraging that sensor's complementary strength
also across this
granularity of space and times requires
knowing where to deploy the sensors
so that they capture the best information
at the best time, at the best
location.
Right. And it requires a systems-level approach.
So how do we provision
for these multimodal systems? How do we provision the compute, the
energy, the infrastructure, and the actual sensor deployment that's
required with the goal of sensing everything, everywhere, all at
once?
For example, how do we know where to fly drones in the
vast landscape of such an Amazon?
How do we
decide where to put the infrastructural support?
What kind of infrastructural support?
Should it be compute? Should it be
network relays? Should it be
power supplies? And so on.
And so digital twins, we argue that digital twins must capture not just
the virtual realism of the nature,
but also the system infrastructure built in together.
Right?
Because what we're suggesting is that we need to close this
simulated to real, as was just provisioned.
Digital twins increasingly have this bidirectionality
already in the term, but they miss the
system aspect of it, the hardware system data
connection. So starting with the real
world,
now the model is that you deploy some hardware
with AI models at the edge, you do system refinement, you do field
tests, you get data.
We get this data, and we analyze this data, and that's where
most of the
integration stops.
What we need to do is to go not from data analysis
back to the system refinement, system of sensors,
system of data collection,
with the digital experiments still in the twin so that we can
plan better the future deployment.
So we did this at the largest safari in North America, The
Wilds,
which is in Ohio, and close to about an hour from the university where I am.
And
this is also one of the largest conservation areas.
They're part of the zoo systems,
and
they're a conservation science site.
So they have
many of the
functionally extinct or severely endangered populations.
You can see zebras in Ohio, or zebras,
and giraffes, and also Pierre David's deer, and many
others, and rhinos.
We instrumented it with many different sensors you
can see. And so there was a talk earlier on Tuesday
about the Full Smart Wilds. You can see this talk.
And over the course of a summer deployment, collected over
400- ... thousand data points across five modalities
of GPS tags, camera traps,
acoustic sensors, drone flights, and citizen
science.
Did we get the right data? Did we deploy the system in the
right way?
How can we do it? And so we argue that needs to be part of the digital twin.
So this
particular, it's a mockup, very quick mockup of what it might look like.
So the same scene
captures not on the...
No? Still no?
Let's try again.
The same scene
captures not just the nature realism. Can somebody run that?
For some reason it's not... Okay, there we go.
Not just the nature realism, which is not realistic, but you can
move, you can play with the positioning of your
camera trap at the top, or the sensor flight plan, the
drone flight at the bottom, to figure out what
the system actually needs to provision with all the full
details of your sensors as part of the twin.
So what we see now is that
all of the spheres of the nature,
the
computer, the models, and the sensors, they
intersect on the data. So in this
trisection, we're
starting to have the
standards on all the biodiversity and ecological
data.
We are starting to talk, and we talked a lot in this
conference about AI readiness so that this data can talk to these
models.
We need to add the part of the robotics,
of the sensor aspect of it, back into the same
conversation
so that
we can build smart sensor systems, not just deploy one
modality at a time,
and then integrate it into data cubes, which is great,
but it doesn't allow you to plan system as
a whole, just use one modality at a time.
And so start having both within the
digital twins, within the replay,
because we already have a lot of the simulation environments, for example, for
drones,
that's starting to exist, not just for biodiversity, but for many other
applications,
where you can simulate and plan flight paths, where you can simulate your
data collection systems, when you can simulate drone systems.
For biodiversity, for example, we have the
Wildwing software and simulation that allows you to do drone
system planning.
And so thus expanding it to all the other modalities and integrating it,
situating in the context of ecological and biodiversity deployments,
you can start planning your mission before you take it to an
environment where you have one chance to deploy it and collect the data.
We've developed a lot of the
edge AI planning tools and starting to integrate
this, and if you want to hear about what a
FAIR4AI drone data standard might look
like, today Jenna is going to give a virtual talk at
2:00 PM, I think. So
talk to us, talk to me.
I'll try to impersonate Jenna as much as I can.
Thank you.
So we have time for questions. Sharif, it's already starting.
Right. Thank you for your-
Oh, they don't work
... talk. A lot of these
drones and instruments are coming from commercial partners-
Mm-hmm
... companies and things like that.
How do you see that fit into our
open research-
Mm-hmm
... ecosystem?
Yeah.
So a lot of the technology is built
with a commercial specification, but open software
on top of the drone. So all the computer vision models that we put
on the drones are open. All the coordination models are open.
System planning and deployment and
provisioning models are open, and the entire
environment
that are being built like Wildwing for simulation,
and provisioning the system for deployment, everything is open.
And
in fact, Jenna
Klein, the
postdoc,
has a whole
line of work that showed how you can take
both off-the-shelf and open source components to actually build
drone systems for biodiversity deployments.
Okay.
And do we have other questions?
Did I get the right... Yeah, there they are.
Okay.
Well, thank you so much, Tania.
Is it possible to make this full screen?
So how do we...
I think this is a PDF. Do you know how to get it full screen?
I can't see my mouse.
No, it's a PDF.
No, there's no PowerPoint.
But it's up there.
Yeah.
So.
You have to go somewhere.
There, now we see it.
So.
Close.
From the control down.
There's a button somewhere. You see it?
Throw out.
Perfect.
Excellent.
So Peter Desmet will show us a bit how to
reuse weather data radar to detect biomass, and how we
can use that to learn more about the birds
in connection with other data.
Hi.
We've heard about the marine realm, the freshwater realm, and the terrestrial
realm, but there's also another important one, which is the aerial realm, and that
is what I'm going to talk about. So while we all had, I hope, a good
night's sleep, there were millions of songbirds migrating over
us south. And they do this
mainly at night, and they often do this at very high altitudes
in massive numbers and in a very broad scale.
You have some choke points, but they typically do this in a very broad front
all over the continent. And that makes it difficult to monitor.
You can use citizen science observations, but those are mainly coming from
the birds coming back to the ground to roost, or
you can use GPS trackers, but then you can only track a number of individuals,
and it's also harder with songbirds, which are smaller.
But luckily, we have weather radars, and there is a network of weather
radars that is across the whole continent.
It is monitoring the sky 24/7. And we mainly do this,
meteorological institutes do this, to know
what the weather is going to be like, so to monitor precipitation.
And the way a radar works is it emits a microwave into the sky at
different angles, and they do this up to 35 kilometers from the
radar. And then if an object in the sky, whether it's
rain, snow, dust, or animals,
some of those microwaves are bounced back in all different directions, and some of
those are received back by the radar, which then knows, "Oh, there are
these objects in the sky." So,
this is a very useful tool. What you see here are not all the weather radars in
Europe. There's more. But these are the ones that we have access to.
And why would we want to have access to weather radars?
And that is because, and I think this is so cool, weather radars can actually
detect animals in the sky as well. So this is mainly useful or
applicable for birds. Insects are a lot harder.
Bats, too, unless there's really big roosts coming out
of a cave, for example. Then you can detect those on weather radar.
But what you can see in the image up there,
basically, you have to think of this radar as looking in different angles.
So you see these donut shapes of things that were at different altitude
layers in the sky. And you can differentiate those
from precipitation because the birds
typically have a more variant speed and direction than the rain, which
is typically going into a more uniform direction, and also the
reflectivity of animals in the sky is typically lower than rain
and precipitation. And through that,
through algorithms that were developed by a community, the Volto Bird
algorithm can extract that animal information
from weather radar data. And
we then can know the altitude at which animals were
flying, the speed, the direction, and also
the density or the amount of animals.
You basically translate the reflectivity that you get back into an
average size of a songbird, and then you can apply numbers to
those. These are the amount of birds that were in the sky at this altitude.
What we do not know is species information.
It is basically we know there's meat in the sky.
And through this technology, there's a whole community that has started,
the radar aviary ecology community.
And this group of people is basically using radar to study animals
aloft. And not only through weather radar, but also through more
specialized radars as vertical-looking radars, which are
very local but can detect
very
precise also insects, and sometimes they can also detect through
Doppler effect, the wind beat frequency, which then can be translated into
species groups. Or tracking radars, which are more like the
military radars, but you track animals rather than aircraft, for example.
This community has
been going on for about 10 years and matured and
has developed a number of things, and one of them is just like that is a data
standard. So we have the VPTS CSV file,
or format, which is
a format to express the time series of what we call vertical
profiles. So you have altitude layers of animal
migration, and we use the frictionless table
schemas to define the fields that you can find, which is direction,
speeds, the radar location, and also the types and
constraints of those fields. We also have a similar format to express the
raw polar volume data that is coming from the radar, as well as
we have a list of
the weather radars in Europe and the metadata for those, the status,
which is co-maintained by the meteorological community.
But it's especially important for us that we know if a radar has
changed codes, that it is actually the same radar at the same location, but, for
example, with a new upgrade, so we can build longer time series with codes
that have changed so we can tie those together.
And the other thing we have started in 2017 is a-
Bucket, the Aloft data portal, where we can
store this vertical profile data.
The meteorological institutes have been doing slowly a good job to actually
open up radar data and not only keep it under a license.
But they typically keep this data only for two days, so you only have
access to the data of now and not historical data.
But to be able to do actually real science over a long time period, we
have started to archive the
derived biological data from this weather radar data.
And so this is a
data repository over 24 European countries,
173 radar locations, and we've also filled up the
historical data until 2012.
And this is a time series of almost close to 5,000 days.
So it's a very long time series that we have.
We've also archived this on Zenodo under CC0 license, and the
really cool thing is that this is updated daily.
So as data are coming in, it's also added to this repository,
with a time delay of about one to two days.
And
the last component is there's a number of open source packages that have
developed to, one, explore different sources of
radar data and biological data derived from radar that are out there,
and to
visualize those and analyze those, as well as the default
to bird algorithm. You can run it yourself too if you so want to.
And there is a tool called CRO, which allows us to
visualize in real-time or semi-real time, the
migration that is happening now. And this is what I can show you here.
So this is from a couple of days ago.
This is a radar about 20 kilometers south from Oslo.
And what you see on the top chart is the amount of birds that are flying
over
a line of
one kilometer.
And you can see at the bottom of the chart, the darker colors, so this
is
dusk and then night and then dawn, that the birds are really,
the numbers are really increasing.
So they stay inactive during the day, but at night, it's really
ramping up, and you see this very high peak in the morning.
And on the bottom chart, you see not the amount of birds but
the height at which this bird flies, and the brighter colors,
there's a higher density. And as you can see here, they're flying up to
2,000 meters high, and then they're settling down here.
And then the next night, we don't have a lot of information because it was
raining that night, and that's actually good for us that the birds don't really
move a lot during the rain,
because it's also much harder for us to differentiate birds from rain
and radar data that has a lot of rain contamination, we call it.
This is a clearer picture from Karlskrona in the
coast of Sweden, and here you can really see these nice blooms of
density and these high peaks. And if you follow this, you can actually also see the
live data the night of the 21st of September over
the Oslo radar, had a very nice peak of
passerines flying over.
So how do we evolve from here? There's a lot of potential here,
there's data there, to something like a digital twin of the aerial
habitat.
And I think the main thing why such a twin would be useful is
migration forecasting, so that you can have models running on the
historical data to be able to predict what kind of migration are we going to
have in the future, which is really useful for bird collision
prevention. So birds often collide with wind
turbines, but also with aircraft, and the first is dangerous for the birds, but the
second can be very dangerous for the passengers of the aircraft as well.
So it is very useful that we can predict when there's going to be massive migration
of birds. And radar is already used for that
for larger birds, but also for passerines, it would be very useful.
The other one would be disease threat modeling. Avian flu, for example.
If you know where
waterfowl is going to move, and we can differentiate that from the radar data,
that would be really useful.
And it's also very cool for public outreach, and it's, I think,
an important essential biodiversity variable, the biomass that is flowing over a
continent.
But the challenges we have is,
for meteorologists, these birds are clutter in the data.
They used to call them angels in World War II.
It's like things that they see on the radar data that cannot really explain.
And it's still the case. Some are interested, but they typically
don't want the biological data and the radar data.
They want the precipitation, and they also have limited funds, so they
tend to filter the data and then only publish the filtered data, while we
want the unfiltered data.
The other thing is the taxonomic information. Well, you don't have much.
It's meat in the sky. But if you combine it with, for example,
citizen science data on the grounds, you are able to know, oh, we had a
huge flux of migration, then you can actually know, oh, and these were suspicious
composition that is very likely to be in there.
And then the typical thing is, this is done by a small community,
so building and maintaining that infrastructure and scaling is a huge
challenge.
In the US, they have a more unified weather radar network.
It's only done by one organization, NOAA.
They've been able to build on the historical data that's also been open longer,
models that can actually predict bird migration.
It's called BirdCast, and users can go there.
This is a picture from the night of September 21, but you can also now
go to 25, 26 of September, so they predict three days ahead.
And you see this flow, this bloom of migration.
So they say, "Yeah, there's going to be about 340 million birds flying over
continental US tonight," which is insane.
But that's also when birders know, okay, it's really useful to go
out now, or the next night it's going to be rain, and we predict there's going to
be less migration.
So we hope to get there at some point with the European weather radar as well.
And yeah, I think the take home message for me is
weather radars can detect birds. It is really cool.
We already have a network that is out where we don't need to deploy anything.
The sensors are already out there, and I think it's a
very unique type of data that they capture.
And really, the strength comes from combining this with other digital
twins and other information. It doesn't really make sense for me to publish
1.5 billion animals
on GBIF as a data set. It's
just meat in the sky that doesn't belong on GBIF.
But when combining with other sources, we can do really, really cool things.
Thank you.
Thank you. Do we have a-- Yeah. Dimitri has a question.
Yes. Thank you very much. Very nice talk.
I was thinking about this a lot in the context of insect movement, and there is a
whole field of movement ecology where
particular pattern of an individual of a group of animals can
be recognized. And I'm not a birder, but I can tell a flock of geese from a
murmuration of starlings. So if a human can do it, then
computers, too. Is there any movement recognition patterns
potential in moving from meat
in the sky to species names?
Not to a species name, but to differentiate insects from
waterfowl to passerines.
People are working on this and using AI models to actually differentiate this
better.
It is the access to the unfiltered weather data that is one of the bigger
bottlenecks now to really train those models well. Yeah.
But watch this space, I would say.
One more
question.
Yes, we have a question in the back.
Thanks. Really interesting talk.
I guess maybe a counter question in a way to Dimitri's.
I feel like when I read about outcomes of radar
studies, I should say it's amazing the kind of bio flows, the meat in the
sky.
But my issue is that if we want to talk about publishing these data as
biological observations, then
it's actually not 1.5 billion animalia, it's
1.5 billion putative animalia.
Yeah.
So
the issue is verifiability, and I think this applies also for,
for example, looking at how the birds move in the sky.
It's going to be very difficult to ever get to the point where we can say 100% this
is this species. It's always going to be probabilistic.
Yeah.
So do you have any thoughts about that?
Yeah, I've recently thought about that, and it's, I would say,
a little bit similar, for example, with eDNA data, where you also have
something like, "Well,
we have a very good guess that these species are out there." Or even
geolocator data, where the range on where the species was is very high
spatially, for example. And yeah,
I think I want to think about how can we express
the uncertainty we have about that.
I don't think this type of data belongs on GBIF, but eDNA data we are publishing to
GBIF. But how do we express the uncertainty we have?
Also with, for example,
computer vision models that are doing species identification.
I would really like to have a Darwin Core term where we can express, just
like we can express coordinate uncertainty, how can we express taxonomic--
the probability that it is the right one. Yeah. Thank you.
Cool.
So thank you, Pieter. Then we welcome up Sirine.
When we worked on this, we were creating a lot of new components, and
Sirine will show us how we can reuse these components and how this will help us to
make the twins more interoperable with each other.
Yes. Thank you.
Okay. So my name is Sirine. I am from TNO, the Netherlands.
And today, I'll be talking about operationalizing biodiversity
digital twins through assessment-driven service mapping and reusable workflow
integration. It is a lot of words, so this is what I would like to call or
also the team we would call the assessment tech.
So before moving to the next slide, today we talked a lot about technology.
We talked about great solutions that we are using in different projects.
They're all very useful. But if we look globally at what is
happening in the biodiversity digital twin landscape and initiatives
and all of these great projects, it is often that we do
produce a lot of tools, a lot of solutions, but then once the funding is
over or the project is over, we forget about these tools, or we move on to
other new solutions. And then it's only the team who worked on these
solutions that would still remember that, advocate for it, or use
it. But other people will just develop probably the same
solutions or similar things, and we keep on moving.
So a lot of useful tools exist, a lot of great
solutions, but they're often difficult to find, first of all,
they are difficult to reuse, and they are difficult to adopt in
many new projects. And this is due to the fact that they
are built in what we call a bubble. So they are designed specifically
for certain contexts or certain use cases, and then it's either
very difficult to adapt them to a newer context, or you don't even see the
vision. For example, if it's used, I don't know, for biodiversity
specific kind of case, is it pollinators or bees?
And then you don't necessarily see it for mountains or for forests
and so on. And the other reason also is access to expertise.
So these tools, while they might or often have documentation, it is
not necessarily understood by everyone.
So if I am a very dedicated scientist to my biodiversity or
biology, and then I run into some ...
hard, let's say, technology stuff, a lot of
buzzwords, a lot of technical terms, then it becomes very difficult for me to
understand, is this really what I need?
So I start asking around, and if in my team I don't have the IT
person that we all run into, it becomes difficult to use this tool and I just
let go and work on something else. And the last part, it is
also hard to adopt. So say you found the suitable tool, what could
seem that it's going to solve all of your problems.
It's the silver bullet in other terms.
But this tool, you look at the description, and you see it's requiring a lot of
resources, a lot of maintainers, and then it becomes
difficult to have it within your system.
So you don't really have the efforts or the, say, resources required
to maintain it over the long term.
And therefore, again, the statement is that we would rebuild similar solutions,
duplicate what is out there, what is existing, just because we cannot
reuse, we cannot understand,
and we get stuck with the prototypes, and we cannot take it to, let's say, the
next level. Every time there is a prototype, great, we did it, then we move on to
something else. We start again.
So the question here, how can we help ourselves, help also other teams
navigate this complexity? It's very complex. It's true.
Maybe there is a way to understand it, to navigate it without having to
look at all of this information and ask for a lot of people
to intervene and do something about it.
So what we came up with is an approach.
Well, this is kind of the structure of the approach to
understand the information that is laying around.
All of the information needed for you to make the technical decision.
We start by looking or saying two questions mainly: what is needed and
what is available? From one side, the what is needed looks
at the purpose and the stakeholders.
We tend to understand them. So what is your digital
twin here trying to achieve? Who will use it?
What is your team
hoping for or wanting as a purpose out of this digital twin?
And the other side is the capability and maturity.
So once you know what is the purpose of your digital twin, you gather your team,
your different roles, and you look together with them.
Okay, what do we have in place? Can we automate, for example, stuff?
Do we have fair data mechanisms, and so on.
And how ready it is to be, for example, integrated in a dynamic
digital twin solution. And then we move on to also
looking at what is available or what is also there
for solutions and resources. What can we use? What can we not use?
And once we map these two sides together, we see that we can actually identify the
areas for improvement. We can see the gaps, we can see what is missing
to make the digital twin function towards the purpose we have in
mind. And from here, we can point out towards the solution and resources
or the expertise needed, and it makes it easier for the different roles within the
team to agree, let's say, on the how to move forward and what
is the next step for us.
And if we want to look at the steps for this approach, so as we said,
we are navigating complexity. We don't need extra complexity on top of
what is happening already. So we try to simplify it into five clear
steps. First, define the current context.
As we said, the most important is the purpose of your digital twin, and we
all agree within the team, what do we want to achieve and who
will use it, what kind of users? Are they biology
specialists or scientists? Is it tech people?
And then from that, we move into comparing the capabilities we have and
what is needed to make this digital twin or this technical solution
operational. Once we have this in hand, we can identify then gaps
and constraints. What do we need to address, whether it's expertise
or service or something that is crucial and missing and
needs to be in place in order for you to operate your digital twin.
And then we can match the goals to option, as in we know
now what is missing. We have an idea of the resources, for example,
from other projects, or we did some kind of inventory of different
tools and different services, and we can match it to what was
needed at the first on the basis of the gaps we identified.
And eventually, we would check the feasibility of implementation.
So we have the proposed solutions in place. Great.
Now we look at your resources, your infrastructure, your available team.
Are we really able to implement this? Are we able to maintain it?
Are we able to support it over the long term?
And of course, this is not a one-way process.
We have feedback from each step that would help us refine our
understanding, our assessment of your, say, use case, of
the context of what is happening, and also would allow us to
make a better match, a better search for the tool that would help you
solve your problems or your expertise.
And then if you want to speak about the application, we started testing
this approach, or at least trying out the approach in BioDT.
So there we developed this use case guide that
allows teams to understand what is happening, what's their
digital twin state. For example, are they very mature?
Are they still starting? Are they just dealing with scientific models?
And from there to see what is their ambition. Where do they want to go?
Where do they want to grow? Do they want to, for example, have dynamic digital
twins? Is it necessary for their use case or for
their goals, or can they already be in a less level of a
digital twin? They just want to monitor things.
They just want to get an understanding of what is happening.
And then with respect to their capabilities.
So they have identified what each, for example, aspect
necessary to run the digital twin is there.
And then they can make decisions on what is needed to go to the next
level. So if you cannot also, for example, improve your resources, that is
okay, but you keep that in mind for the next step, or you adjust your
purpose accordingly.
And the lesson from BioDT was that once you identify or
you understand your development needs and how you meet your purpose,
would help you greatly to make the technical decisions later on.
Instead of, for example, right away diving into technicalities and developing,
for example, the greatest digital twin in the world, but then your team cannot use
it or you cannot necessarily meet the purpose you had in mind.
And in BioFlow, we actually had the challenge on the basis of two
aspects or two sides. So from one side, we
had the goal of the project, which is making use of what was
available from other projects that the consortium did before, or members
of the consortium did. So there was a lot of great tools around biodiversity
and ocean biodiversity. And the other side, we have many use
cases who were working into getting their workflows into the digital twin of the
ocean. So the challenge was how can we make them use, or at
least help them use these tools, and how do these tools meet their needs?
So we started first by looking at the tools and identifying what is out there,
making it more understandable. Instead of long
descriptions, you go on those documentations, and it's awfully long
descriptions. Which is great, but it's not necessarily useful when you
really are working with a schedule and you have a lot of things to do.
So we identified keywords that would make them more accessible, key
tags for technicalities, for infrastructure needs, for also
limitations. And that helped us also navigate these tools and know
exactly what we have, so we would know what we can promise or what we could
help out with. And from the other side, we had the demonstrator use
cases that were running and trying to get their data into digital twin of the
ocean. We asked them questions, structured questionnaire, approached them,
so we could map their needs into what we called here thematic areas.
These are the most common challenges.
And from here, we were able to actually bridge from one way to the
other. So from the inventory towards the use cases, and then from the use
cases towards the inventory, and allowed to help out with the
problems they were having, and they found the solutions and
were able to get the support from the different other technical teams.
So yeah. This shows you that once you understand what is in place, it is pretty
much possible to reuse what is existing, and you would gain a lot of time in
your development, and also doing your work would become easier.
Now, what is next for us? This assessment tech approach would be more
solidified in Oceanity as part, again, of the digital twin
of the ocean and the Mission Ocean, where we would make it more
automated and validate also what we are having now in place and
make it more runnable, so we don't have to every time run in between
different roles and different technicalities and what is happening.
And on the longer term, we also envision the standardization of things that
could be repeated. We start to see pattern between the different domains.
And the question remains also what to keep non-standardized and so on, because
you need still to tailor some things to your audience and the
use cases you have in place.
And thank you to BioDT and BioFlow and, of course,
everyone within the TNO team who helped make this happen.
And I think I'm on time, so I will make it to the question round.
Of course, you can connect if you want to.
I see a hand.
I see Sharif has a question.
Thank you. It's, I think, very useful the method you described.
I was wondering if you have any suggestions, because a lot of our projects are
cross-institutional.
Mm-hmm.
So for example, in BMD, you saw what Matthias is
doing with DataCube. We have to run it at Naturalis and connect with what
Klaus' team is doing. What ends up happening is that, let's say,
our internal institutional process and cycle does not match with them, and then
sometime... So how do you see that happening?
Because most of these projects are very,
even though somebody's in charge of the final product, but
we have to figure out how two or three organizations will work together.
How do you see that happening?
Well, for this question, I think it goes beyond the assessment
tech approach. This is more about having either
coalitions or agreements from start, because we also at the same time, we want to
open up and to share what is happening between organization tools
solutions. But there is also a level of protection
needed for your intellectual, I don't know, property or things like that.
So what helps is that when we are in the same project, that we
have from the start or make room in our proposal, that would be room for
sharing what is already existing, either an inventory maybe of
tools and what could help with and see the potential, see the
outcome. And I think once you see the outcome, that helps break the,
how do you say, the obstacles, the bureaucracy obstacles,
because we see that very often.
Exactly.
Does this help?
Yeah.
Yeah. Anna has a question. Thank you.
Yeah. Thank you for your presentation.
Yeah.
I just have a question because in this process, it's still very manual,
and the history of this user
requirement elicitation, do you try to capture
them as machine-readable information that
could be kept for future,
even for machines, for understanding why this digital twin has been
developed and how?
And maybe also for the reusing
for new digital twin. Because at the moment, you have
questionnaire, and it's
really nice, but do you keep it somewhere and machine actionable or
readable?
Yes. What we try to do is eventually, once we are, for example, we
succeeded or we already experimented with enough, say, in
BioDT or BioFlow use cases of what is
happening, and we had some kind of learning, some kind of pattern, then we try to
code it into a proof of concept or something that could be run and
it's understandable even by other colleagues.
And yeah.
The information collected
from the user
Yes, it is also kept in projects.
In the project, for example, reports, there is one part about-
But it's not machine readable?
No.
For that, no.
Any other questions?
Do we have more questions, or do we want to transition into
discussion?
I think, yeah. I'm coming to you. That was exactly what we wanted
to discuss now with you, so to say, the post-BioDT lesson, which
Sharif, Ana, and Sirine already started, to see what
lessons we have learned and what next-gen biodiversity digital twins would look
like. So
I think we can just go on for the next 15 minutes.
So my question may help in that transition.
So what I see here is very interesting, and I'm assuming that you're
thinking about this as reuse within a research
landscape. Have you also
thought about or tried using this approach for tech transfer
so that these digital twins could then be used actually on the
ground by industry, by conservation organizations?
I'm just curious, does it translate well?
Yes. Actually, this idea of, or at least the approach of
assessment is inspired by one of our first project--
Well, at least what I witnessed in first projects in this assessment,
let's say, perspective, that it was within industry.
So there were
SMEs in place, and they needed to understand their level of
digitalization to grow into the next level and to have more mature
digital twins for factories and industry, so on.
So for us, we took the inspiration.
Of course, it was very complex because there is so much being done in industry
digital twins, and a lot of standards and a lot of
details. But for the
sake of simplicity with the biodiversity, you cannot add to the complexity.
We did adopt much of the approach without having all
of those buzzwords and all of the industry terms.
Yes. Can I go?
Okay, continue.
All right.
Are
we?
So I think we have transitioned to the discussion phase, so I think we can release
Sirine from the stage, unless you want to help us answering.
No, I can stay and orchestrate if you need. Okay. Doing.
So...
Yeah. The idea was now indeed, to look a little
bit of the lessons learned from the talk approaches.
As we have seen, there is, of course, these large-scale infrastructures like
DESTINY, which really excel in the production of continuous data, in
particular in the climate metrological domain.
There is a climate DT deployed as well as extreme
weather event DT. But post-BioDT lesson is that
the complexity of biology, in particular the
ecological modeling, couldn't really be captured by these large-scale
infrastructures and monolithic digital twins.
So what we did in BioDT, it was mentioned in the talk of Sirine, by Sharif to some
extent,
and in other talks from Matthias,
we still have these multitude of
prototype digital twins we called them, which were very specialized and
indispensably relied on the data provided by GBIF, the
RIs like LifeWatch, GBIF, Disco, and so on, to really
target their
problem domains. And what we wanted to discuss now in the
remaining minutes was
what ideas are there or can we develop to go on with that?
How can we persist this?
I understood Chary's question also a little bit in this direction.
How would a next gen or next generation biodiversity digital twin
project or digital twins, plural, of course, look like? Yeah.
Dimitri.
Thank you. It was good to walk from the reception yesterday together so I could
rehearse my
comment now. A bit of the reflection of the BioDT project. I fully agree.
Nature complexity is so insane that attempting
twinning it is naive and unrealistic.
And in biomedical domain, they have a human blood
model, and human blood system is very complex, and it takes them
years to perfect it. In engineering, they make twins of airplanes, which are also
complex structure, but nature is several levels
more. So what we ended up in BioDT project, having a bunch of
examples, a gradient of complexity from most simple to more
complex, but it's still like, "Hey, let's see what we can do." We
had pilots. We never promised anything than pilots, and we delivered them.
And for me, in the hindsight, the reflection on running a
work package in this project is that the best outcome of
BioDT was educational. That the modeling community twinning around
stopped thinking that data magically falls from the sky in a perfect shape, but
actually started to express some respect to the data efforts represented at
TadWig.
And the data managing community and data originator community
started to understand the modelers better.
It's never full eternal
friendship, but there is so much more understanding now
within project but also outside, that I think this is something that
really transformed the field. This is not what Brussels paid for,
I believe, but this is a good byproduct outcome and a very important
one, lasting beyond the project.
Thank you.
Okay.
Thanks.
More comments.
Well, I don't want this to become a BioDT meeting,
but I would like to add that I think the communication
between data scientists, biologists, social scientists was also
something that
gave a major step into this direction, and it was
really nice see today also this continuation.
Well, it's not a continuation, but somehow spin-offs of the lessons
learned. So I think BMD is doing such a great work
with this kubing that is moving forward.
And I also see a bit of a change in the mindset when these
different communities are communicating, because when you go to the Climate DT
that was just mentioned here, it's clear that the workflows are much
more clear.
Of course, the physical aspects are easier to model in a way,
but it's also that we
can improve in the communication among the
biologists and the data scientist tech
experts, and et cetera. So I think I see a very
important progress here, and
we are going there. We are getting there. Thanks.
Yeah, I think I also echo that, and I really like the way Serene had these two
question. I think what you said is,
what is needed and what is available framing it.
And I would also be interested to, maybe in
the US and other parts of the world, how they do it.
Maybe in the European projects, sometimes it's so already structured in the
proposal.
So for example, none of our scientists and users said that, "Hey, I need a
digital twin." They didn't say that.
We saw it because of the hype cycle and the
same with the data space and all of this thing.
Nobody's asking for any of these,
but I think somehow maybe we have to ask them like, okay, what is it
that you're-- For example, this example of the coastal and
the terrestrial and the ocean things.
So these are the problem, and if we can fix it with very simple
tools,
why
can't we do that within the project framework?
Of course, yeah, we will get the money for the digital twin and other things, but
maybe a simpler approach is also
okay to
do it and advertise that it's not the
cutting edge tool that we're using, but it's actually solving the problem.
So that's something to keep in mind.
But maybe, if
other parts of the world also have examples, it would be nice to hear.
Yeah.
Tanya had...
Speaking for other parts of the world here.
One of the, I
think, challenges is
to translating centralized, well-funded efforts like
BioDT to other parts of the world, is that there is no funding or
centralization or even the recognition that it is actually
necessary. And so what we're trying
to do in many of the conversations and efforts
is very much focus on decentralized approach.
How do you take the tools that were developed, for example,
in projects like BioDT or
other
very centralized and organized
efforts and translate them into a very decentralized
landscape of data collection, of
data holders, of decision makers,
of conservation organizations.
And I think one of the
intermediate points where we're finding that it may work well or at
least tested out is with
semi-centralized efforts, or at least semi-organized efforts.
So for example, in US, there is the
networks of monitoring like the National Ecological Observatory Network, long-term
ecological research initiatives that are
coordinated also. And we actually got the
coordination supported, shockingly,
with
broader efforts like GBIF, NatureServe,
iNaturalist bringing this more together.
And so we can test out some of the approaches, some of the
transferability of methods.
Right?
Some also, in a different way, you can focus on very regional
efforts like the coastal monitoring,
or the
Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute, which is very focused in one particular
area in Panama.
Or the just announced project that I mentioned,
Amazon.ia,
which is Inteligencia Artificial switched, right?
And that one is reasonably supported.
They still don't have all of the funding that they need, but
for example, that project takes all existing monitoring sites
that are highly distributed across three countries in that case, and they're
trying to create sort of a unified view
modeling and decision support system for the
entire Amazon.
So the question here is what can we take from these
centralized projects and what can be transferred, right?
Things like
establishing-- I really, really appreciate the push for,
because we've done in the conversations over the last 20
years, data standards. Yay. Okay, data has to be fair.
Then we're moving to code has to be
open and usable and kind of fair-like.
Then models, AI models. So now we're moving
to workflows. So I really appreciate that
movement and continuation of standards, so of reuse,
of the fairness
of this
set of tools.
How far can we extend the generalizability of this
outside of one particular project in a highly distributed system?
I don't know if my comment will be very relevant, but because the
question was
where should digital twins go from here on?
I don't know if anyone is aware, but last year, the Global
Nature Watch was released.
And one of the first things, because I beta tested, one of the first things I asked
them is:
Why is there no occurrence data in here?
Why am I only able to ask questions about land use and things
like this? And I think in that space where
big institutes are really exploring the capabilities of
AI,
I think really just occurrence data in and by itself
only could really fill in a better space and really help us also to use
those tools and integrate them into these bigger
platforms and structures. But obviously you need connections, and you need people
interested in using that type of data, which they seem not to be at
the moment when I contact them about this.
Yeah, anyways, just a comment.
Thanks. I would like to extend what Sharif said about the imaginary
audiences. All this high-level modeling and twin building has,
unfortunately, the element of theatrics, and the demand for this
often comes from policy and science,
is sort of serving the demand from the funders, in
this case, Euro Commission. And I think there'll be comparable forces
like, "Hey, give us a tool that give me an illusion of control of what's going on."
And I was very much inspired by Will's reply
about the sensitive species handling in another session that,
yes, it's all very important. We can do it.
We can do a beautiful model with a map dancing under your
fingertips, and at the same time, we deploy bulldozers and chainsaws
and cut half of Borneo to plant oil palms.
So I think the danger of playing with these toys is just to
stay in the playroom. You make your twins that gives you an illusion of
understanding of biodiversity processes, whereas half of the planet
is just being destroyed. And I think
in the BioDT project, this was a
very big challenge.
Okay, we didn't have users in the beginning.
We cultivate some community of interested people, but then what?
I think the
applicability of these modeling tools in land use planning, in conservation
action,
is something like
the real marketing, real application of this thing is
a frontier I don't actually know how to
approach. And I'm sure in the community, we have people with
experiences who build fantastic digital data intensive tools, and
then work with IUCN or provincial authorities to actually make
a difference on the ground.
I don't yet see the way how biodiversity digital twins are making this
difference, and I'm saying it from inside the project we just finished.
So it was important to break the ice.
Nobody did it before us. We deployed a bunch of pilots.
Yes, now we know what works, what doesn't, but the then what part is
something that needs to be addressed.
Okay. Yeah.
I think we're going a bit over time. Oh, but we have time to go on.
So I know we're over time, so I won't go on and on.
But what I'm seeing and reflecting on here is that by
focusing on
doing pilots,
thinking about use cases and how we can spin up very quickly, what's coming to
mind
is that we have a world with lots of emerging threats where we
don't have a lot of time to respond.
Somebody mentioned avian flu early on, and these are
cases where we're not sure what the threat is going to be, but
once we
identify an area, and I come from the area of agriculture
where we're constantly concerned about invasive pathogens that
might be damaging our crops, or I'm sure public health would tell you the
same for zoonoses and emerging diseases.
If we can use these tools to spin up digital twins extremely
quickly, if there's any connection to
the probability of spread or epidemiology that is
related to biodiversity, I think you've got a really great set of tools here,
and now a language to talk to the people where
they need these tools, but they don't necessarily know that we have them in this
community.
Okay.
Thanks. I take the opportunity of wrapping up, and I
do agree between you and Dimitri that this would be the way to
go, make these available. And openness is
not supposedly a threat if
the right people have the access to these tools.
So
in Finland, we have this forever ongoing forest
things where it's seen
as a threat of having the open data because the landowners
may think that it's a threat that their
property will be protected against their will if there's
endangered species. But I think it should be the logging companies
who should be aware that they can't log there.
So it's very much a data policy and
interoperability of the policy concern, and also that we have the
big picture around. Second thing
I will take the opportunity of saying that we could continue this
dialogue. In two weeks in London, there will be Research Data
Alliance, RDA session for advancing
scientific use of digital twins through open science and fair data.
And we have
both there trying to reestablish or establish
digital twins interest group there.
And Klaus will have a short talk, and we hope we
can get good dialogue and then enthusiastic
people
stepping up as co-chairs. So hopefully see you there.
Thanks.
Okay. And then we would
close the session now. I would like to thank all organizers
involving Hannah, Dag, Gabi, Sharif, Niels,
were pivotal to organizers and of course, thanks to all fantastic
speakers, was very imagining and thanks for all people joined here,
discussed and so on. And we hope we can go on. Thank you very much.
Okay, cool.
Hello, everyone. Thank you for coming.
This session
today is about AI readiness.
We will work on the definition and the
metrics and
... such things that are what makes the
data sets specifically or workflows AI-ready.
So this session is about that. And I'm going to be the first
speaker, and our third speaker will be
late, so instead of that, we will have an
online
speaker.
Otherwise, everything should be in order.
So
I am the first speaker, and
my name is Yasin Bakis from Tulane University Biodiversity Research
Institute. I am the senior manager
of biodiversity informatics, and I'm going to talk
about AI readiness metrics.
So the
question that I am
going to try to answer in this
presentation is how do we evaluate whether
biodiversity data are actually usable for AI
systems, AI pipelines, processes?
So also I use the Gemini.
I hope conference organizers
will not be mad at me.
So in my opinion, it is different for everyone.
There is no common, widely accepted definition for
AI readiness. And my definition is AI readiness
is the degree to which a data set and its
associated workflows can support a defined
AI task reliably, reproducibly, and
interoperably.
Well, rather than the definition, I will work on the
parameters that defines
what is AI-ready.
But let's keep that in mind. Those are important
factors. So
also the
other important factors are AI readiness is
task-specific, in my opinion,
multi-dimensional and testable and profile-based, which
I am going to explain in the following slides.
So it should look like this, like a profile
instead of a global AI readiness score.
It should be a profile,
like readiness profile, like here.
And then what are important in this profile
is metadata completeness,
semantic alignment, provenance, image
suitability. I work with image, so
it depends on what you are working with.
You can call it data suitability for your analysis of course.
And we know reproducibility, interoperability are important things.
And also task performance
according to the relevant task.
And then
if I have different tasks, AI readiness needs to be
task-specific.
So if I have different tasks such as classification, trait
extraction, scale-aware measurement, those are the things that I use
again in my studies.
What
is important
is different in each case, as you can see.
So
we were working with
collection images and we have done some
data cleaning and tried to
provide the data set that we have downloaded from GBIF,
iDigBio or museums harvested from them
try to clean them, data process them, and then provide it
to the machine learning people. And then that
workflow on the right
we end up with. And the first item that we
have done was capturing the metadata
manually for the data quality. We were trying to
understand what is this about. So that was one of
the steps in providing the
concept,
the
AI readiness concept. Metadata completeness.
Also,
metadata completeness is not just
what percentage of the columns are full.
It is also
what is available for that specific AI readiness
task, like what machine learning people are using
for filtering or cleaning the data sets.
And then we came up with the manual labor
was too expensive and too slow. So
within our larger group, we started capturing automated metadata
such as those.
And then
we filled in the profile.
However,
it doesn't necessarily mean the
AI-ready data set
is
going to give you good results, like in here,
but it just means
AI-ready data set will perform better.
So
sometimes it works, sometimes it doesn't.
So what I show here is those two images are
almost
same image quality,
but those are coming from a data set
that has lower AI readiness
So we also update the task
performance part. This is our trait
extraction landmarking
pipeline. So we receive scores
from that, how well the dataset performed within
this pipeline,
and then we use it to update the
task performance.
And
so how are we doing by means of TADWIC community
by covering all those
information,
metadata, terminology, vocabulary?
So it is not great because we end up
developing our own vocabulary with around
200 words, 200 terms,
and about 90%, 95%
were new. So we weren't able to find anything in Darwin
Core, Odonton Core, Audio-Visual Core,
or
even EXIF.
Whatever
is out there, MAKS, PROV, in any of those standards,
we couldn't find relevant terms. So this is why we
created AIQAER task group
within
TADWIC under Audio-Visual Core. So we
have a platform which we call Fish-AEAR.
Let me advertise a little bit.
So
we have a platform, Fish-AEAR, that we build a platform for our
machine learning people. What we do is basically capture all the data,
build the
relevant metadata for the
machine learning purposes, and provide everything to machine learning
people. And then if they complain, listen to those complaints,
update the metadata, build new terms
to provide them the best or perfect
dataset. Not means of data quality, but means of
AI readiness. So on top,
we are
performing our
tasks by this concept,
which we call Fish-AEAR. Fish-AEAR comes from AI
readiness is the
AEAR and fish is fish. So this is
specifically AI readiness fish image datasets.
And our products are data and metadata, of course,
we are providing them to our machine learning people.
And then we
also generate vocabulary. So if you go to that website, you will
find it. And then
we provide those vocabulary to AIQAER task group,
and then we discuss them here, and then we provide them to
Audio-Visual Core if it is relevant, then data
quality
work group. And then
if they
publish the terminology, then we give it to data
repositories such as GBIF, Disco or Phenoscape or
whoever wants to use it. And machine learning people are using
data and metadata from those
data repositories.
And then
so
we
have
defined
mostly what it needs to be done is
it needs to be task specific because for each task, AI
readiness is different. And also it needs to be
measurable
everything.
But it cannot be one data
readiness or AI readiness score
which can be used
globally. So it cannot be an AI readiness score, but it needs to
be a profile. And then the AI
readiness performance, AI performances needs to
be embedded afterwards to that every
profile. And then
there should be
experiences shared among the different
communities. So there are so many different taxonomic groups.
That was our experience with the fish and
mostly imageomics-related
datasets.
And then we
try to create an AI-ready platform.
And based on that platform, we expanded the
AI readiness
definition a little bit
comparing to
previous AI readiness workshops.
And then we have AIQAER task group.
This is the link you can join if you are working with images of any
kind,
biological images. It doesn't have to be collection images.
It doesn't have to be fish or
anything. You can join our task group
and you can share your experiences.
Even if you do not want to
join the task group because it is too much work, you can just share your
experiences at a meeting with us.
And then contact me if you have
anything to share or if you want further information.
And this is Fish-AEAR. You can go visit the Fish-AEAR.
You can use the datasets. It is available for everyone.
And then you can see our vocabulary. Thank you so much.
I guess I have some time that I can take a couple of questions.
Okay. Thank you. That was-
Do we have microphone? Oh, it is coming.
Put it against your chin.
Against my chin? Oh, okay.
Now it's quite loud.
Thank you. That was very interesting. My question is about the Fish-air.
Is it very specific, or
is it a software that we can use in other domains,
or it's very specific for fish?
So currently it is specific for fish, but we
designed it in an
expandable way. Which means
you can use it for different taxonomic units,
taxonomic groups,
and you can add extra columns that is
relevant to your specific AI task.
So you might be using a totally different AI
pipeline, for example. You should be able to add extra
columns, but those columns needs to be defined
in your own vocabulary if they are not existing TABIC or
other standards.
Thank you.
Mm-hmm. And it is available for everyone.
We
call it X-air, actually,
instead of Fish-air, the generalized term, so that you can
have your Butterfly-air, for example.
I will invite the next speaker.
Jessica Titocchi, right?
Yes.
Thank you.
Oh, you have a microphone? How does it work? You have a microphone?
Yeah, I have.
Sorry.
It doesn't-
Presentation?
Yeah, the presentation.
It
doesn't move.
Doesn't move?
No, it doesn't move.
It doesn't go to the left in a way that I can put
presentation.
Yeah, here. You can just-- This is yours, right? Yes.
There you go. Okay.
Hi, everyone.
I'm Jessica Titocchi from the National
Research Council of Italy.
I'm an aquatic ecologist working mainly with functional traits and
planktonic community, but I also collaborate with a digital
research infrastructure, LifeWatch ERIC, and at the national node
with LifeWatch Italy.
Try to bring together
closer these two worlds, the data science and the
trait-based research
community. And for that reason, today, I would like to introduce you
to the Trait Thesaurus. That is a semantic resource that we have developed
to support data harmonization and verification of
functional trait based for aquatic
organism.
So the present of ecological, and
specifically trait-based data, is a scattered landscape of open data.
We are assisting to an increasing and growing
publication of open datasets and databases of functional
traits
of species organism, and that is
a very good thing. But
making data open doesn't necessarily mean making this data
fair and reusable for other users.
So
this is the case when we often
have access to the data, but for different users can be
difficult to understand, comprehend, and
reuse this data.
This is mainly due to the nature of this data.
They are highly diverse, first of all, because they come
from different sources. They can derive from published
literature or specimen collection, in situ monitoring, or also
remote sensing and other type of
methods. But also because they can be collected as
quantitative data at the individual or also as aggregated data as
species or community level or as qualitative data.
Moreover, they can be stored in different
repositories that can be general purpose, but also more
thematic and domain specific repository.
And
Even more, they can be very heterogeneous
in also data structure.
People can collect data, for example, in spreadsheets, but even if
they use the same format, they can arrange and organize data in a different
way. Maybe they can use a species per trait matrix or
including trait information in columns or in rows.
And even more, they can store this as a different data file.
But one of the
most difficult issues that we are facing now
is semantic
heterogeneity. Indeed, when we talk about traits,
we often use different terminologies for meaning the same
thing, or we use same terminologies, but actually,
these same terminologies applied in different contexts can have
different meaning. This is the simple case of size.
Can be called body size, body length.
For
people that work with zooplankton, body size, especially for
copepods, means a specific region of the body that is the prosome length.
So it's dependent. This can be the case for many other
examples. And so
when we work with traits, we really face a lot
of difficulties to understand each other, even though we sometimes
use the same terminologies. That's why there is a urgent need to
clarify and find an agreement on how
ecologists define traits and trait terminologies.
And for this reason,
we have decided to
focus on this topic with the help of the research
infrastructure LifeWatch, to try to promote a common strategy
to globalize and mobilize trait-based data
by following the FAIR principles.
To do so, we started developing trait data
standards
within a thesaurus that is a controlled and structured vocabulary where
concepts are organized in relationship that can make them
explicit
relationship. And the development of this
thesaurus
had different steps. So we first
identify, determine the scope of the thesaurus that was mainly focused on
functional traits. Then we identify sources, gather the terms.
We
had then a formalization phase where we identify the structure and the
data model that we want to adopt. In our case, was a SKOS
thesaurus, so a SKOS data model. And we choose an editing tool to
build the thesaurus that, in our case, was a Bokbench editing tool.
And then there was the most important phase, that is the editing and
validation phase. So once the thesaurus
reach
a stable structure,
we let them open to the community in order that they could validate
the resource before going to the
repository.
The story started years ago. At the beginning, we
developed four different independent domain thesaurus, one for fish, one for
macroalgae, one for phytoplankton, one for zooplankton.
Then we realized that there was a bit of overlap in these independent
resources. So what we did was that we tried to
combine them by using a manual and automated ontology
alignment. And at the end, we ended up with a unified framework, the
trait thesaurus version that at the moment contains more than
1,500 concepts.
This is how it look like.
This is the page of Ecoportal. You can find the thesaurus
in this
repository. And here you have the QR code for a recent
publication if you want to know more.
Just to
show you how it look like when you navigate the thesaurus.
You can have all the concept here. Here you can see the different schemes.
At the moment, there are five. We have included also the macro and benthos scheme.
Each term has a preferred label with a stable reference
resource, a URI. Then we have included also synonyms,
definition, and we have say if this term is related to all the
schemes or only just one or few.
Then
if you go on this part in the raw data, you can have also the information of
the mapping that we have done among our terms that are included in
the trait thesaurus with already other
existing resources by using
SKOS relationship, so close relation and exact
match.
And then we have also other metadata information.
This is how it look like. There are so many terminologies
related to traits, but also to trait units.
So in a way that users can have the trait names and also the
units in the same framework.
For the applicability, this resource is already included in the data
portal and metadata catalog of LifeWatch Italy, where it is
used for semantic annotation of datasets, metadata, and all the
attributes. And it can support also
natural language processing,
artificial intelligence, and machine learning application.
And of course, from the ecological perspective, can permit
cross-taxa
integration of
information, and also as ecological synthesis.
This is just a few example of the use of these resources
for standardize and harmonize two datasets within the
PoMP project, the Polar Ocean Mitigation Potential project, for
example, from the planktonic communities.
But this has been also used
in a working that we are still
developing for the benthic communities, for the Coral Reef Genoscape
database. It's still in progress, but we hope to finalize this soon
as well.
And that's it. So as a future perspective, what we
aim is, actually,
we would like with this tool, with this service, is to
continue to reinforce the adoption of fair practices in
trait-based research, and this specifically important
by strengthen collaboration and networking, because
this semantic resource is always evolving.
It's not a static resource. It's very dynamic, and from the input that we
obtain from the community, we can include more terms,
refine the terms that are already
included, and so on. And this will permit then to mobilize
even more trait data in a more fair,
interoperable way. And for that reason, I would like just to
say that we are launching now within LifeWatch a working group that is
dedicated on this. So if you're working with traits, you have trait-based
data, you want to
make some work together, there will be soon this working group
dedicated to this. And then there is a more tailored group that is specifically
for zooplankton community, that is
a new launched group for SCORE working group.
And so if you are interested, we will be very happy to
collaborate with you. And with this, I would like to thank
all of you for your attention and all the people that have been
validating and creating and building together with us these
resources.
Thank you.
Thank you very much, Jessica.
I think it is very important to have such tools,
especially when we started
producing a massive amount of
traits.
So we have time for a couple of questions.
Can you show your hand again?
Yes. Hello. Great talk. I was wondering, it's only
applicable for English terms, because in our museums, we have some
Dutch terms as well, and we would like to use this, but
yeah, I was wondering if it's suitable for other languages.
Yes. So this is one of the implementation that we are actually thinking
about. So to
make this a resource,
to include multi languages for this resource.
It could be a bit difficult at the beginning because the terms are
really
so many, but we are starting to think about to do this at least to
translate the preferred label and the synonyms.
That is already something. And then we can continue also with the definition and so
on. So yes, we have this in plan. Thank you.
Thanks, Jessica. Great presentation.
Thank you.
We spoke yesterday.
Yeah.
I think your work is fantastic.
Two questions.
Are you working with TADWIG on a task group with this one? And if not, why?
So this is my first time here, so that's why.
I don't know that there was the opportunity to do that, but I would be very
welcome to do this, and work,
let's say, developing and increasing this resourcing.
Absolutely. Thank you.
Thank you too.
Yeah. Let's talk more.
Thank you, Jessica.
Okay.
Thanks.
There was, I think, another person, but...
We
will have the questions. Okay. One more person.
Thank you.
Okay.
One quick question.
I guess that many, if not most of the terms,
have corresponding
semantic concepts in existing ontologies already.
Are you preserving those, or are you documenting those relations, or are you
planning to do this?
Yes. So,
the thing is that at the moment what we did was mainly a
manual approach to find alignments.
Mm-hmm.
And so what we catch, the match that we catch-
Yes
... we reported with the semantic relationship, either
close or exact matches if the definition on the label were
exactly the same.
In some cases, when we wanted to import some
terms because they were already present-
Still there
... so we needed to create and invent a new one, we did this.
So we just imported the terms, but using the same
URI from the ontology of the provenance.
Okay.
So,
we are trying to not
redo things, but try to align and merge with what it's already
existing. But we have faced that for some, especially
aquatic organism, morphological traits or so on, there
were some terminology still missing. And so that's why we created.
Okay. Thank you.
Thank you, too.
Thank you, Jessica.
Thank you.
Our next speaker.
So, the third speaker cannot make it, and someone
from my team, Xiaojing Wang, is going to present
the next
presentation.
Hi, everyone. I'm Xiaojing Wang from-
Can we all learn from me?
It's online
... Turin University Biodiversity Research Institute.
FishR is our repository for museum fish specimen
images, and the images produced from them through AI
processing. Most of that processing happens outside the
repository. When we bring the results into FishR, we need
to know which image was used as input and which
processing run created each result.
Today, I will show how we record and validate those two links in
our system.
Fishare is the image repository developed for the
biology guided neural networks and image omics
projects. Excluding test records, the current
database snapshot contains just over 400,000
source image records from 67 institutions
and seven source collections. It also contains about
306,000 derived images and roughly
290,000 bounding box images,
42,000 segmentations and 27,000 landmarks.
The source images are distributed across many collections,
but a number of project teams carried out the AI processing
pipelines, mostly outside Fishare.
The repository, therefore has to receive the output files together
with enough information to reconnect them to their
sources and processing history.
This figure follows one specimen through three AI processing tasks.
At the top is the digitized source image.
The first task produces a bounding box image.
That image is then used for segmentation, and the segmentation
result is used for landmark detection.
Each task produces a separate image record and
belongs to a separate processing batch.
Files can later be renamed or copied, so file names alone
cannot reliably preserve these relationships.
So in Fishare provenance for derived image records,
both its direct input image and its
processing run.
This diagram shows what moves between Fishare and the external
processing pipelines. The blue outline includes the image
sets stored in Fishare. At the top, images from
digitized collections enter the repository after cleaning and filtering.
The blue arrows show selected images moving from
Fishare to a processing pipeline.
The pink arrows show the resulting files returning to the
repository. When a team submits its results,
Fishare stores the output images together with one batch
record describing that run. Our current database contains
21 batch records for AI pipelines carried out from our
team and the Virginia Tech team.
Once the results are in Fishare, we use ArchIDs to preserve those
connections. An ArchID is an archival resource key, a
persistent identifier assigned to a record in Fishare.
ArchIDs connect each output to its
direct input image and to the batch record for that processing run.
For derived image records, we focus on its own ArchID and
two ArchID references stored with it.
They are parent ArchID and the
batch ArchID. The parent ArchID identifies the
image used directly in the current processing step.
Following this field from one record to the next reconstructs
the lineage back to the source image.
A source image has no parent ArchID, so that's where the chain
ends. The batch ArchID records how the image entered
Fishare. Derived images refer to the
processing batches, while harvested source images
refer to the harvest batches.
The parent chain reconstructs the sequence of the images, while
the batch records preserve the context of the event that added each
image to the repository.
This is one batch record from our system.
It describes a bounding box run completed at Virginia Tech on
February 3rd, 2022. Dr. Murrough is
listed as the creator, and BGN is
listed as the project. These fields shown here are
terms in the Fishare vocabulary: pipeline, institution,
creator, project, and the date. They describe the batch as a whole,
so the vocabulary defines batch as
its own class with 14 terms. Additional terms
include supplement paths for an extra metadata file
and code repository for the source code.
Software configuration and processing parameters can be included
in the supplementary file when it's available.
Also, this structure matters at scale.
The largest Fishare batch contains just under a quarter of a million
outputs. Fishare stores the shared metadata once
on the batch record, and each output
only needs the batch ArchID to refer back to it.
Again, this figure shows how ArchIDs connect images to their metadata.
On the left is the one parent and child chain from the source image
to landmarks. Each stage has its own ArchID.
The segmentation in the middle is shown again on the right.
Resolving its ArchID brings up the corresponding images,
records, and its metadata.
At the same time, those same connections remain in the downloadable
archive when a user download it,
such as in multimedia CSV. Every image
record includes its ArchID and
batch ArchID.
AI-derived images also include parent ArchID.
Batch CSV supplies the shared context for each batch.
The download also contains citation information, term
definition, and RDF model.
Fish Share Vocabulary Version 3 defines the provenance terms and
declares batch as a class. A user should not need
access to our internal database or a separate workflow
system to reconstruct these relationships.
The exported files carry the parent chain and the batch
references into another computing environment.
Those exported identifiers also make the relationships
easy to check automatically.
In our current database, we checked about
359,000 parent links and about
763,000 batch links. All of them
point to existing records, and no image has
itself as its parent. An early audit found 29
unresolved batch links, but all of them came from test
records, not the production dataset.
So we run the same checks after each batch is ingested
and before every export.
Also, once we know these links are complete, we can use them during
model analysis. If a result looks wrong, a
researcher can start with its ArchID and follow its lineage
back through the intermediate
images to the original specimen image.
The batch records show which pipeline run
produces each step. At the dataset level,
the same metadata lets researchers compare model performance
across source collections or across batches
within the same pipeline stage. They can
see whether a performance difference is
associated with the source material or with a particular
AI pipeline.
To summarize, Fish Share uses ArchID to keep two parts of
a provenance together, the image lineage and the pipeline
context. The parent chain records the lineage,
while the batch records provide the context.
Both remain in the exported data and Fish Share checks them
automatically. Researchers can therefore trace a result back to
its source specimen and understand the processing history
behind it.
Finally, I would like to thank my team members and everyone who
contributed data or pipeline works to Fish Share. Thank you.
I think we can have a
couple of questions again.
I will answer the questions.
Henk Bart is here as well.
He can answer the biology side, I can answer the technical side, if
there are any questions.
There seems to be no question.
Our next speaker is Wouter Edding.
Yeah.
Is this PDF?
Yeah, fine.
I got that.
Yeah.
Okay.
Thank you.
Okay, I will start with a question.
How many of you already know about
ISCC codes, International Standard Content Codes?
Raise your hands, please.
Interesting. I see no hands. So I'm not here for nothing,
because I would like to introduce the ISCC codes
to you. It is a relatively new
ISO standard introduced in 2024.
A little disclaimer, I was not involved in any way in the
standard,
so I also do not know the nitty-gritty details.
But I think this is a very important
standard if you work with media files,
and I'm sure you do. And I think this is going to
revolutionize
how we manage the assets.
You see here a nice image, which is obviously
AI-generated.
So
this is one of the challenges that we have now,
because
if it's not so obvious like this, then you create a lot of
issues with trust if you start to have these kind of images,
and you cannot see whether these are actual specimens or
artificial ones.
But we have other challenges as well.
We have unlimited copies of
media files
because we do not have these identifiers.
And
they are uncoordinated because the metadata and the
connection
with other data easily gets lost. If you change the
name of the file, you already cannot relate that
back to
the rest of the data.
If you have some metadata attached that tells you some provenance of who made
the image
and when it was made, it easily becomes disconnected if you change that image from
a JPEG to a PDF,
a PNG image, or whatever.
So uncoordinated copy is an issue and broken link data
also.
So why do traditional identifiers fall short
for images?
We have traditional persistent identifiers like DOIs,
and they focus on the location of your content.
And it's a good practice for persistent identifiers to have
some metadata included
that makes one persistent identifier
identifiable as different from another one.
And that's easy to do for some things like people,
institutions, specimens, and you have examples
like
RORs and ORCIDs,
and digital specimen DOIs. But for images, it's hard
because how do you
describe an image in such a way that you know that it's different from another
image? You really need the content of that image, what the image
represents.
And that's just not there.
You could try to solve that with adding a hash.
You could create a hash. A standard hash solution is
SHA-2056.
But the problem with these hashes is that if you change
the image even a tiny little bit, even if you change one pixel, but
also if you change the metadata or you change the format of the image,
you already generate a completely different hash, and you cannot relate
these things to each other.
And this is what the International Standard Content Code
solves.
So this is really great, I think.
It can work on images, on
video, on audio, and even on text.
And it is a code that has four
different parts.
You can also have codes for only one of these four, but you can also have codes
that have all these four different parts.
One is a code for the metadata
of the media.
One is for the content, for what it represents.
One is a code for the data, and one is a code for the instance.
Now, the instance is similar to the hash, so if there's a little change, the image
code changes. The data code only changes
if there is a change in the data, but not a
change in the content. So if you change a metadata, if you
add a watermark,
if you change the format from a JPEG to a PNG, these
kind of things, your data code will change, but your content
code will still be the same because what the image represents is still
there.
And they use some intelligent
algorithms for that, SimHash and things like that.
And what's unique also in these codes is that you can use
Hamming distance.
So
usually you say if you have a persistent identifier, you don't want any semantics
in it. This carries semantics. And I think it's
fine because it's identifying the content itself.
And that means that if you compare two identifiers,
you can look at how many bytes they are different.
And
I see that.
And so you can calculate how much these two
images are different.
And you can do that for the content, but you can also do that for the
data itself.
So this allows smart matching of images.
You can match images only on the content, and you can compare them, and you can
find similar images.
A short breakdown.
So we have these
four
parts of the code.
The code is
a concatenation of these four parts, plus some
self-describing metadata about the code.
The main type describes whether it contains all the four parts or
only one of them.
The subtype describes whether it's an image or
a sound because you need different algorithms for the content
detection.
And it's usually
using 64 bits for each part, but you can also have a
shortened code.
So
if we have this, which is great, what are we then still missing?
What is still missing,
and that's something that's still being worked on, so this is in
beta. It's not a part yet of the standard.
You want to bind
this ICC code, the content code, with
who created that content and when was it created.
And this is what they do with the declaration event, which
is a FAIR digital object
that binds the ICC code together with
a signature of who created the content
and the timestamp.
They started to do this with a blockchain-like ledger, but now I think they just
use
a log that's append only. So
you don't need to have a blockchain anymore.
And they use DIDs,
decentralized identifiers,
and a peer-to-peer-like solution.
So everybody can
run a server, run a hub. The
source code is available. You can just run it locally, and you can
run an index with these declaration events.
For the codes themselves, you can also run the algorithms just on your local
laptop. You can generate the algorithm of the content so anybody
can create or recreate the ICC code
from the content.
So this enables the content-based discovery and also the
provenance, so who created the image, and this also isolates
AI-generated fakes because the AI
fakes will never have these signatures of who created it.
It is also creating resilience for annotations,
because
if you have annotations, you can link them not to
the image file, but you can link them
to the ICC ID.
And that means that
even if
you have an image that's a little bit different, it is a derivative from
the original image,
you can
still keep the annotations linked to the content
because the content is still the same.
So this is my last slide. If you want to get started with
that,
I think you should start here. You should start on the Hackingface playgrounds.
You can just try it out yourself there.
You can upload some images or sounds or whatever,
and you can create these codes and just to play with that around.
If you want to take it a bit more seriously, you can
install the software, which is Python,
and
start
creating these codes and maybe run a server also for
these
IDP
identifiers.
So you can run a decentralized node for
the local registry indexing as well.
And this is what I had to tell.
Thank you.
Thank you very much, Wouter.
This is very interesting talk. I especially like the
content-based discovery section.
Are there any questions?
I see one there.
Hello. Yes, there's sound. First of all, thank you for a very exciting
presentation.
One bit that was a bit unclear to me,
this
code that you end up with, is that something that you have in a separate
catalog file, or are you able to
also include it in the image file itself, for instance, in the EXIF
metadata or something like that? Of course, not all parts of it could go into the
EXIF metadata because-
Oh
... somehow circular, or is it-- Yeah.
It's up to you. You could include it in your EXIF if you want.
But anybody can recreate that code at any time.
So if you just have the-
Mm
... image as input itself,
using the algorithm, you can recreate that code.
Mm-hmm.
So basically, you don't need to store it
in your EXIF because you can just recreate that.
Yeah. So mainly, you will keep it in a separate catalog file of sorts.
Yeah.
Yeah. Hmm. Thank you.
Another question on that.
Hello. Very interesting. I was wondering
specifically for the content-based embedding part.
Yeah.
Is it then a fixed algorithm, let's say, for
images, something like a clip or something?
Or how should we see that? Or is it something where you can choose which
algorithm to embed the content with?
I think it's a fixed algorithm, but they have different algorithms for different
types of content, so they have a different algorithm for sounds than for
images and different from video.
I know that for sounds,
I think they first convert it into a sonogram, and they
use that.
I don't know all the details on that, but you can look it up in the
documentation. It's online.
Thank you.
I have one question.
About the
provenance,
how does it work? It is very straightforward, and it is easy,
but if there are multiple
data sources or multiple mothers that creates the
same object or
same item, how does the
provenance method react to this?
You can have only one creator, basically.
So
the
institution or the person who declares that,
"I'm generating that with my
private
public key
cryptographic hash," then that's the
originator, that's the source.
And the rest is copies.
Mm-hmm. Okay.
Yeah.
Thank you so much, Wouter.
Hi. My name's Andrew Topnakov, and I'm the technical lead for Turing Ecosystem
Surveillance, presenting for the team
Walid Alnam built the exporter at the center of this
presentation.
In the keynote, there was a discussion about the tricky part about
meaning, context, and trust being
the biggest problems that we're facing at the moment.
So we're going to
talk about that a little bit and see how far shared specification can take us from
the field collection all the way through to the repo at the end.
So TERN is Australia's national terrestrial ecosystem research infrastructure
funded through NCRIS, which is a federal
scheme.
TERN Ecosystem Surveillance is based here in Adelaide, and we've been here since
2011.
We have a bunch of ecologists who define protocols and then hop
in their cars and drive out and collect field data.
So we've got a long-term standardized field survey network that crosses
the
continent's terrestrial ecosystems in the rangelands most specifically.
So we collect, curate, and publish the data.
And the point of this talk today is about how we are using
specifications to govern
the collection and also the publishing.
So here's a slide that shows you the network.
There's many, many plots across the country.
We collect soil and veg data, and also samples, and
all according to a single protocol,
which has now moved from our own protocol to
EMSA, which I'll get to in a moment.
And the thing about this is that we can use this long-term data collection
to understand
change over time. So you can see that certain plots here are located in certain
strategic positions to provide an understanding of how things
change over time,
giving a comparability essentially.
So our software infrastructure...
This is just giving some context so you understand where we come from.
We had a
Android app called AusScribe and a Postgres relational
database, which we used for over a decade.
So we were collecting with the app and then curating
and storing and publishing all in Postgres,
using Couch also as a staging JSON database. And that worked fine.
And now we've now moved to a next-generation system that we built
for the federal government,
called EMSA, which has the protocols and also monitors the software that supports
it. So this is quite new, only a couple of years old, and
these are new standards. And the field app is running as
a
PWA rather than a native Android app,
which means that it's essentially a web app that's
able to work offline.
The back end is Strapi, which is a headless CMS.
We call that Core, and there's a Postgres that backs that as well.
Core is where all the data ends up and also what creates the specifications.
So the thing that we're interested in here is that the new system
has the data modeling in the back end, and that data modeling is a specification
that informs the front end on what to collect, and it also informs the back end on
how to export and transform it into
ABIS.
So here's a very high-level system picture, just so that you get a
feeling for things. So that
in the middle, we've got Core and Org. Org is about people and projects.
Core is where the data is actually stored.
We have a PWA on the left, which is
taking a specification, which is actually
a machine interpretation of a PDF that people have written, which is what we've got
here. So that informs the client, and then it also
informs the export function, which is the ABIS push, which goes to the BDR, which
is a national biodiversity data repository.
So that single data model informs the client, and it also informs
the exporter, which exports the data out of our system.
So there's two possible ways you can get to standards-compliant data.
Maybe there's more, but at least there's two obvious ones.
Go out and collect the data, stick it in your CSV, put it in your database, and
just keep doing that. And then at some point,
when standards emerge, you have to
map the semantics across and get your data across into this other
repository.
That's okay, but it can be a bit tricky.
And of course, it's always been done like that in the past before we had decent
tooling and standards. But with EMSA, we've gone the other way and we
start with the protocol definition, which drives the field app
collection, and it also drives the
RDF creation. Which we then validate, and then we make sure that that's all good
before it goes into the repository.
So
we're starting with standards rather than trying to work them out a bit
later.
One thing that's important to note here is that our system is more than just
occurrences, so they're actually structured surveys.
So when the field data is collected, it's collected against a defined protocol,
which is a sequence of steps and actions and workflows.
And these things are defined and semantically mapped to IRIs
so that the procedure and the steps that are taken are understood at the
time of the data being collected and also when it's being exported.
Which means that the data
is self-describing in some sense, and we know if data is collected according
to a certain procedure and a certain protocol, then it can be interpreted correctly
later on by analysis
activities a bit later on.
So yeah, it's not just occurrences, it's also how it's collected.
So
this is one of the key points of this presentation is to talk about how we
have machine-readable contracts.
So
on the left, we see
OpenAPI specification. It's a 3.0, which is not
JSON schema, but it's pretty close.
The app uses that to inform the user interface that it
presents, and then it generates JSON,
which we then also do validation on.
And then once it's stored in the database, we do an export, we transform that into
RDF, and then we run SHACL over that to make sure that it's conformant as well.
So there's a whole bunch of checking that goes on to make sure that
data is correct and complete, but it's also coming from the same
singular specification in different forms.
You can see also
about things that machines can do right now, and then there's some sort
of proposals about with the machine readability, things that could be
possible in the future such as
build your own new front-end based upon that OpenAPI spec,
or
answer questions across an entire graph
rather than just on small parts of it. It's all a bit open at the moment.
But that's also why machine interpretability is important.
So here's an example with a concrete example of a point intercept.
The specification declares once that growth form is a lookup table reference.
You see that there X lutRef
veg growth form.
And so
this
informs the app and the app can then see which lookup table to use and
automatically generate the UI element that's correct for that protocol.
And the exporter reads the same key and it maps it to the
chosen code into the graph. So,
there's a uniform space there where the markup and the key is
used in both cases.
The front end uses it to generate the UI and the back end uses it to
generate the exported data.
So what we have here really is for the exporter, which is what Waleed has built,
is a
mapper between two modeling paradigms.
We've got flat JSON with semantics connected to it to a certain degree
because the fields have IRIs connected to them.
And then we've got the graph, which is actually a graph-based
modeling approach, which is
the ABIS and term ontologies.
So the job of the exporter is to map between those two, and we use the
simple same spec in the middle
to keep that all aligned.
Obviously, when we create an RDF output, we're not putting that into
some file system. We're actually going to be adding that into a larger graph
database, which is the BDR, which takes state agencies and territory
agencies and other providers potentially,
and it
is able to add them to a larger graph.
So,
the BDR holds our observations next to the other provider's
observations. And with the shared IRIs, you can have
queries that walk from our plot observations all the way through to someone
else's record
without any complex mapping needed.
So,
yeah, our data joins a larger graph,
so we need to obviously make sure that it
complies.
Getting close to the end here.
So this is essentially saying that the exporter is a dynamic
entity.
It's not all baked in, so it actually makes SPARQL queries against the GraphDB to
make sure that the EMSA vocabularies,
and the properties and the protocol attributes and all those things are
queried. And then we do some caching, obviously, to avoid
performance issues. But
this means that as the protocols evolve,
the exporter should be
relatively flexible
to accommodate those changes.
As I mentioned before, we do
quality gating at both boundaries.
So on the way in, the JSON schema is checked in the app, but it's also checked
when it's
submitted to core. So we want completeness and correctness
on those two endpoints. And then also on the way out, the EMSA
shapes are used to validate the RDF that we create.
So there's a lot of QA on there to make sure that
the data is intact and complete and correct.
Just on those ontologies and the
SHACL shapes that we use.
ABIS is at the highest of levels. That's the national profile.
Then the term ontology sit below that, which sort of talk more about what an
observation and a procedure are. And then the EMSA shapes are the
very specific protocol shapes that
talk about the specific records that need to be collected inside those
protocols.
All of them are used on the way out. We validate against all of them.
So what this enables us to do is to validate, obviously, and to also
compose the outputs into a larger graph.
And in the future, maybe there'll be some machine new
robot aspects such as
looking into and classifying certain habitat or condition or maybe even
combinations of LLMs that propose things and then
SHACL and verifiers that can actually
verify the postulate that the model is putting forward.
So just the takeaway here,
we attach meaning wherever it's known.
So we have the IRIs that define
meaning. We check on the way in
from the app, and we also check it on the way out.
So we have some very
strict schemas or a singular
rule which is used by both, and that is also very robot-ready.
We do have provenance, so we understand which versions of the documentation are
used in which situation, so that we can track things down in the future if things
change and we need to fix things.
And yeah, we think that this is very AI-ready because of the
fact that it's essentially specification-driven.
So
I hope that was useful. If you'd like more information, you can
contact my lead or myself.
Thanks a lot.
Thank you, Andrew. If you have questions for the online
presentations, you can ask them through the application, and they can
answer through the application again.
I do not see the next speaker
in here.
I know that they uploaded their presentation.
Is Brooke Longfox here?
Is Sefika Efeoglu here?
Do we have the
drive folder here?
Yeah, but I don't know how to access it.
Scene 46.
Brooke Longfox.
That was the last one of this.
There
should be one more presentation.
Can you refresh that?
Yeah.
So it's a video?
Yeah, it is here.
Okay.
Put it
full
screen.
Hi, everyone. I'm Brooke Longfox.
I'm a data curation scientist at MorphoBank, and this work
on, Is Artificial Intelligence Amplifying
Paleontology's Reproducibility Problem?
has been done with Mark Young, who's the editor-in-chief at Historical
Biology.
I wanted to start off by saying that this is not an argument against
AI in paleontology. I use AI-assisted approaches in
my own data curation work, and I think that they offer enormous
opportunities for making biodiversity data more accessible and
reusable.
However, AI is entering a field, paleontology,
that already has a significant reproducibility challenge.
So my argument and discussion here today is that AI can
amplify those challenges because it can transform
incomplete or maybe ambiguous information into structured
outputs that look ready for reuse.
So the question I want to ask is: what does our data
need to contain before we consider it truly AI-ready?
So paleontology is increasingly a digital and
data-intensive science.
A physical specimen can now be connected to images, occurrence,
and stratigraphic information, publications,
measurements, morphological matrices, and
analytical outputs. This is part of the broader idea of
the digital extended specimen. So the specimen becomes an anchor
within a network of linked digital information.
For example, I show here
an image of a skull from MorphoBank.
And what we have here is information
about where this skull is stored,
information about the photo itself, and then information about the
character. So this is the character state
information listed here.
This is giving an example of the connectivity,
and that's what we want. It makes information discoverable
and allows data generated for one study to support completely new
research.
But greater connectivity also means that problems in one
digital object can propagate much further downstream.
Before I discuss AI, I first want
to go over what is already happening with the data
being reused.
I see this quite directly through my work as a data editor for
Historical Biology.
As we've implemented a stronger journal data policy, the
same types of problems come up repeatedly.
I'm grouping them here into three broad categories.
This is availability. So can we get the data?
Then documentation. So if we get the file, can we
understand and reuse it? And finally, traceability.
Can we reconstruct where those data come from and how they produce the
published result?
So these are not AI problems, these are existing reproducibility
problems.
But AI matters because it changes what happens to those problems
next.
The first problem is simply availability.
Sometimes underlying data are never deposited.
Sometimes the manuscript says that no data exist, even though the
study is clearly reusing measurements,
images. It talks about models. It could talk about
specimens.
It could talk about photos that they took.
So we routinely encounter files on
personal websites. This could be cloud storage links rather
than persistent repositories, and repository records that are
private, incomplete, or inaccessible to reviewers.
So the first reproducibility barrier
is pretty basic, and it's, is there actually
data available after publication?
But availability alone is not enough.
We can have the file and still not have enough information to reuse it.
A dataset may have no README or data dictionary.
Abbreviations or exclusions may not be explained.
We may have a 3D model without enough information
about how it relates to the original specimen or imagery.
In a morphological matrix, character or state
definitions may be incomplete.
So a persistent identifier can tell me where the file
is, but it does not necessarily tell us what the
file means.
Then the third problem is traceability, and this is the one that
becomes particularly important for AI.
And this is, can we follow the chain from evidence to
result?
So sometimes a data availability statement does not correspond to the
files actually deposited.
A measurement or character score may not link clearly to its source.
A matrix may have been modified through multiple studies
without clearly documenting where individual characters or scores
originated.
And the version in the repository may not clearly be identifiable
as the version that produced the published analysis.
These individual pieces may all exist, but the linkage between them
has been lost. And now, if we introduce AI
into that environment,
basically we get uncertainty.
And AI can make that uncertainty look structured.
So this is the specific failure mode
I'm concerned about. One of AI's greatest strengths is that it can
take messy information and turn it into structure.
We can take an old PDF, a scanned table
with inconsistent terminology, a matrix,
and extract it, or normalize that information into a clean
dataset. But imagine that something in the source is
ambiguous.
Perhaps OCR shifted a column. Perhaps an
anatomical term was translated inconsistently.
Perhaps the original paper never documented why a
particular state was scored.
AI can still produce a perfectly formatted table.
That table may contain all the expected fields.
It might even pass schema validation.
It might be deposited in a repository, receive a DOI,
and then become ingested into another AI
program for more analysis.
So the structure has been improved, but the underlying scientific
uncertainty has not necessarily improved with it.
So that is the distinction I want to make between technical validity
and scientific validity.
A machine can tell us that a value has the correct format,
but that does not necessarily establish that the value accurately
represents the underlying biological evidence.
For example, morphological phylogenetics
gives an especially clear example.
So if we look at a character matrix that looks machine
friendly, we have taxa, characters, discrete values, zeros,
ones, twos, question marks.
If we take this example, for character 37, zero
is absent, one is present.
The values look objectively binary,
but producing it may have required considerable scientific reasoning.
What anatomical structures are we actually comparing?
Are those structures homologous?
Is something truly absent and not merely preserved?
Are we looking at different ontogenic stages?
Is the taxon polymorphic?
Are there any characters missing?
Is it biologically inapplicable?
So the cell in the matrix is structured, but the structure does
not contain all the reasoning that generated the cell.
AI may be able to extract an existing score or potentially infer
one, but responsible reuse will also need to
be able to be evaluated through evidence and
interpretation behind that score.
So in other words, character states can encode expert judgment,
not simply observations waiting to be extracted.
So this brings me to AI-ready data.
We already have several important pieces to the answer.
AI-ready data should be machine readable so computational systems can
actually work with them.
They should be FAIR, findable, accessible, interoperable, and reusable.
They need sufficient documentation so methods and context are
explicit.
And they need validation, some defined process for checking that
output against technical and, where appropriately,
scientific criteria
But for interpretive data, I think we need to make one additional idea
explicit, and that's verifying it.
So can I take an individual assertion and trace it back to the
evidence that supports it?
Can I determine whether it was transcribed,
transformed, or inferred?
And can I tell whether a human expert or an automated process or
both validated it?
This is a different question from simply asking whether the file is structured.
And I think this gives us a practical path forward
toward robot-ready biodiversity data.
So first, I think we should define a use case.
So what exactly is the system doing?
Extracting information, transforming it, or making new inference?
Second, identify the information we need to preserve.
So the source method, the responsible agent, validation
status, and uncertainty.
Third is crosswalk existing standards.
This could be Darwin Core or other standards.
And then we need to identify the gaps.
So for example, can we currently record not just
that an assertion exists, but that it was
generated through an AI-assisted inference and then
confirmed by a domain expert?
So the goal is not to prevent machines from reusing our data.
It's to give the machines and the people enough context to reuse them
responsibly.
I'll end by thanking the TADWIG and symposium organizers
as well as researchers, editors, curators, and repository staff
whose day-to-day challenges helped shape this talk.
Thank you, Brooke.
If you have questions for Brooke,
I'm sure some of you have, and my team has, you can ask those
questions through the app or our application.
Our next speaker is
Sefika Efeoglu.
If you go up to five maybe it's--
Oops.
Hi, I am Sefika presenting this work together
with Jana Hofmann from Senckenberg.
In this presentation, we look at how
biodiversity collection data, specifically type specimen
catalogs, can be made more suitable for AI and
ML workflows.
Our focus is on combining established biodiversity standards
with ML Commons Croissant and metadata format
designed for
ML ready datasets. Broader questions behind this
work is
how can we make valuable historical
biodiversity data not only FAIR but also easier for modern
AI systems to discover, understand, and reuse?
I will introduce why biodiversity data matter for AI
connect with
FAIR principles and Croissant, and present our
workflows from historical catalogs to AI-ready dataset.
I will then show the
Croissant and Darwin Core mapping, FAIR
evaluation impact, and key takeaways.
Biodiversity data are increasingly being used
in AI applications. Examples include
species identification, named entity recognition, taxonomic knowledge
extraction, and building
biodiversity knowledge graphs. However, historical collection
catalogs create several challenges.
Much of their information is stored as unstructured or
semi-structured text. Human specialists may be able to read
records, but they often lack the explicit
machine-readable metadata that computational
workflows need.
As a result, valuable collection information can be difficult
to reuse directly for AI and ML. This
motivates a workflow that transforms historical
catalog content into structured, standardized, and
machine-readable data while preserving the biodiversity semantics.
The FAIR principles, findable,
accessible,
interoperable, and reusable, provide an important
foundation for AI-ready data. For ML, FAIRness
is not only about making a dataset available,
it makes experiments more reproducible, improves data
clarity and quality, makes the dataset easier to share,
and
can support more reliable model development.
In this work, we treat FAIR principles and AI readiness as
closely connected. A dataset that has a
well-described structure, semantics prevalence, and access
information is
much easier for both people and
computational systems to reuse. The goal is therefore
not to replace the FAIR principles, but to extend their
practical
values into
AI and ML workflows.
This brings us to ML Commons
Croissant, introduced as the metadata format for
ML-ready datasets.
Croissant provides a standardized, machine-readable
way to describe the dataset. It represents the data
structure and resources in a form ML tools can
interpret, rather than relying only on human-readable
documentation.
An important advantage is platform workflow
integration. Croissant supports the dataset use in
AI ecosystem, including platforms such as Hugging Face machine
learning pipelines. For our use case, the key benefits
are standardization across systems, easier
workflow integration, and clearer path from
biodiverse data to dataset usable for
model training.
This slide emphasizes Croissant as a common metadata
layer connecting three groups. First, data creators can
describe the dataset structure, resources, and semantics using
standardized ML-readable metadata.
Second, data repositories can publish
that metadata alongside the dataset, improving
consistent discovery across ML-oriented
platforms such as Hugging Face, Kaggle, OpenML.
Third, data users can search, understand, and load the dataset
more directly into the ML
workflows and frameworks. The key message is create
once, publish anywhere, and use everywhere.
For biodiverse collections, this common metadata layer can
help connect domain-specific data standard with the wider
ML ecosystem.
Here is the proposed workflow. We start with type specimen
catalog. A catalog record may contain specifically
rich information, but much of it appears as unstructured
historical text. In the next step, LLMs, for
example, GPT and Qwen, can be used to extract
structured information from that text.
The extracted information is then represented using
the Darwin Core metadata so that biodiversity concepts
follow an established community standard.
After that, Croissant metadata describes the resulting
dataset in a machine-readable form suitable for
ML workflows. So the transformation is type specimen
catalog, unstructured text, LLM assistant extraction,
Darwin Core metadata, and then Croissant
metadata.
Intended output is an AI-ready dataset.
A central
part of the approach is mapping Darwin Core elements into a
Croissant representation. For example, scientific name
can become a field that provides a special label for
ML classification. Genus can be
represented as a taxonomic feature, and
individual count as an integer-valued quantity feature.
The catalog number is particularly important because it serves
as a unique specimen or record
identifier. Locality provides a geographic feature.
Event date provides temporal metadata.
Collector captures the collection prevalence and type status
to present the type specimen classification.
The point is not to discard the Darwin Core.
Instead, it preserves its biodiverse semantics and
expresses those elements with a metadata structure that
ML systems can understand.
The overall goal shown at the bottom of the slide is
to bridge the biodiverse standards with AI metadata
standards.
This slide shows how Darwin Core records are represented
in Croissant using
ML-readable JSON-LD. Each
specimen attribute becomes an explicit field with a
defined data type, making biodiverse data easier to
discover, integrate, and use directly in ML
workflows.
We also evaluate the dataset's FAIRness.
The pipeline measures the FAIR
metrics,
checks the metadata quality and standards
compliance, helps
identify areas for improvement.
The proposed approach has five main areas of impact.
First, it supports creating AI-ready biodiverse dataset from
collection information. Second, it introduces
automated metadata extraction, reducing the
manual effort needed to structure historical catalog text.
Third, it connects
Darwin Core and Croissant, linking
biodiversity domain semantics with ML-oriented metadata.
Fourth, it includes FAIR metrics evaluation as a
part of workflow rather than treating FAIRness.
And fifth, the workflow can serve as a reference approach for
biodiversity collection that want to make
historical data more reusable in computational and
AI contexts.
To conclude, FAIR data provides a foundation for
trustworthy AI. AI LLMs can
structure historical catalog data while Darwin Core and
Croissant connect biodiversity standards with ML
workflows. FAIR metrics help evaluate AI readiness, and
this approach can be extended to other biodiversity collections.
Thanks
for your attention. You can also connect with me
via
this email.
So we are out of our time,
but
I will be here if
you want to have some discussions.
As you can see, everyone's understanding
about AI readiness is a little bit different from each
other. So I hope this session
helped a little bit with the understanding of what
we should expect from AI readiness and what
should be the
definition or the dimensions to describe it.
Does anyone have any questions or wants to
comment on something?
If not, then let's go have lunch.
Thank you all.
Hello everyone. It's nice to see you all joining our
freshwater session. It's good to see some familiar faces, but also some new
ones.
My name is Astrid Schmidt-Gloeble and I am co-organizing this session
together with Koen Martens from ARBINS and brain
of FADA, Freshwater
Animal Diversity Assessment,
and then Vanessa Bremerich from IGB.
She is head of developing the
FIB data portal, and then online, Helen.
Can we see actually if she's online?
Helen Dallas from Freshwater Research Center in South
Africa. She is the inventor of the FB system.
And last but not least, Olaf from Catalogue of Life.
So the reason why we gather here is that you probably have
known 1,000 times the paradox of freshwater, tiny in
coverage, but big in terms of biodiversity.
And
I think that freshwaters are also different in terms of their
characteristic compared to terrestrial and marine environments.
Meaning if you look at lakes or ponds, you have
isolated or closed systems. If you look at rivers, you have
systems that are interconnected, so what is happening in the catchment is
influencing what is going on down there.
And that being said, I think that the
data that origin from this freshwater also are different, and
they deserve special attention. And this is basically
why we are here,
to bring us on the same level, so we are all working, or most
of us are working with freshwater.
We want to bring us all on the same level in terms of which data
structures exist, which taxonomy exists.
Yeah.
And also I want to add that I want to use the time maybe
after the break to discuss about the sustainability
and interoperability of all the systems that we are
all caring for.
Okay. With that, I hand over to the session moderator,
Koen.
Yeah.
But only very temporarily.
Yeah. Very temporarily.
Because it is my pleasure to introduce the talk of Astrid
Gloeble with the help of Geraldine Mertens, Not Just Another Database:
Building the Future of Freshwater Taxonomy with FADA Teams.
Ast, your time starts now.
Okay. I want to start my talk with the question, what is this
species? So some of you might recognize it's a caddisfly or
Trichoptera in Latin, but what is the species name?
So if you look at it, it was described as Goera basalis
by Colenati in 1848,
and then it was actually put into the genus
Lasiotifula. This was around 20 years later, and it's not
so sure whether it was done by
McLachlan or Hagen, but anyway, it went into
Lasiotifula. And then in the year 2002,
Weaver
revised the whole Lepidostoma tree, and he put all
the Lasiotifula species into Lepidostoma.
So this species is now called Lepidostoma basale,
and it has, of course, some synonyms.
So if you now really want to check
is this name really true, if you are a Trichoptera expert, the first thing you
would do is look into the Trichoptera
World Checklist, and as you can see here, it's an extant species, and
there it's called Lepidostoma
basale.
Okay, this is the world checklist.
But most of us don't look into the world checklist, they look into GBIF.
And here we can see that Lepidostoma basale is a synonym of
Lasiotifula basalis. So
something wrong in GBIF?
Because it says Lasiotifula basalis is actually the accepted name.
Same is true, of course, for Catalogue of Life because they are super
interconnected.
And if you look in the third database, Freshwater Ecology, it's again,
Lepidostoma basale. So I leave you with the question, what
is this species?
So
summarizing this, freshwater biodiversity has
not a
database shortage, but rather a taxonomy problem.
And this is actually where FADA comes in, Freshwater Animal Diversity
Assessment, and where I hand over to Geraldine, who will tell you
everything about past and future of FADA.
Hi, everyone. Also a pleasure to be here.
So to tell you about FADA, we need to go back in time a little
bit, actually quite a lot, around 20 years ago.
Several very brilliant person had this crazy
idea to start the Freshwater Animal Diversity Assessment,
namely Koen Martens, Estelle Balion, Christian Leveque at that
time, and Henri Segers.
So more than 20 years ago, they wanted to establish this taxa list on
freshwater species. And so they partnered with several
experts from all over the world in Belgium, and they had this very
big meeting where they
decided on what they were going to include into FADA, namely
species and genera,
as well as some
zoogeographical distribution,
endemicity, and they all decided on a
uniformized approach on how to gather
all the data So each expert was responsible for
their own animal list, going from very small
crustacean to
very big mammals.
However, once the project stopped being funded,
all these species lists that had been established kind of
died off
because of some
technology issues, that it was not possible to continue maintaining the
list. And it was also very limited to exchange
machine-to-machine integration.
One very
nice thing that came out of FADA is this special
edition in Hydrobiologia that was published out of this
impressive work that they did.
Each chapter
from the biodiversity assessment that was established
was published in a special edition.
And so each chapter concerned one group of organism,
and they all followed the same format, so that
results could be drawn from the different chapter, the different groups, and
also compared and analyzed.
But what about now? So
the
challenge that we faced at that moment was not to
create another species databases,
but more to transform FADA into a living taxonomic
infrastructure so that it will live on in the future.
So that's why the new project started, on which I'm the manager.
So it's InfraFADA project, and the idea was really to
rebuild the whole system. So as you may imagine, 20
years later, lot of expert had stopped
working. Some taxonomists had even passed away or
just retired, unfortunately. So we had to start with
rebuilding the whole consortium of expert because they
are the one providing all the information to us.
So here it's really an overview of all the work
packages from the project. And as you can see, everything starts
with the expert providing the information, and then
the list
had to be imported into a system that Astrid and
her colleague have been very
hardly working onto,
which
we've called FADA-TiMS, and she will explain more about it soon.
So it's really the tool behind all the lists.
Then, as you can also see from the scheme, exchange is a
very important aspect from our project.
Namely, you can see that the FADA service are meant to be
used from relevant networks such as Catalogue of
Life and GBIF.
One objective is also to valorize all this data, as you can imagine, because
all of these experts are providing
these taxa list to us, spending and investing a lot of their time
and effort, and so we want to valorize everything they've done for
us. So we have special plan, particularly regarding
publication, which I will tell you about soon.
So at the moment, we have about more than 100
expert from all over the world working together
to establish this updated
list.
And since it's a global project, you can imagine that it's a huge
collaboration from people from all over the globes.
There is 61 animal groups in total, and
you can see that there is this macrophyte, little guy that is hanging
on there. And actually, you might think it's weird to have included
macrophyte when we are dealing with animals, but
we thought it was super important at the very first FADA edition
to include the habitat of all of these species, which is why
we've decided to include the macrophyte as well, one chapter on macrophytes.
So for the moment, we have
43 Excel,
which are the template that we provided to our experts so that they could send
us all their taxa list. So, 43 in total,
on which we received already 24, and 19
are currently still being updated for us.
Then you see there WoRMS and TaxonWorks.
So I don't know if you're all aware of these databases, but
many of our experts, once our first project
finished, moved on to those databases.
And so since we did not want it to ask our expert to work in
parallel
database and enter their data twice, we've managed
to work and exchange data together with these two major
database. So as you can see, there are 15 lists that are expected from
WoRMS and three from TaxonWorks.
So as I told you, we really want to valorize all the data
and all the work from our experts, so we have several
plan outreach.
We want to have an assessment of the present day
freshwater animal diversity, and we would like really to compare
the result we had in the first FADA edition to the one we have now.
This will help us analyze major threat, future trend, and
do some prediction in the future, which will be super useful.
So yeah, the idea would be to update and create a new version
also of this nice issue of Hydrobiologia that we had,
but also to publish in other journals.
I'll leave it back to Astrid again. Thank you.
Thanks, Geraldine. So now back to the
database. The database we are having in
FADA is called FADA-TiMS, and the challenge was that we need
to go from static checklist that we had 20 years ago to living
taxonomy. And this is how we researched it.
So taxonomic experts, they have a sys- Is
this working?
System that is called FADA-TiMS, where they can enter all
their taxonomic information and where they also
can create the taxonomic information, and then the things is
getting published. I will talk about this in a minute.
And once it
is published, it feeds also in external infrastructures.
So
what is now possible with FADA-TiMS, so FADA-TiMS is
operational and working. We have different user permissions
depending on whether you are an expert, expert leader, or just a group
member or if you're just the public.
And what is also important here is the bulk upload, because as
Geraldina said, some of the
experts gave us Excel lists and they were bulk or they will be bulk
uploaded into FADA-TiMS.
And I will give you now a few impressions.
This is actually this starting page
of FADA-TiMS. If you scroll down, you will
reach this
section where it says Available Organism Groups, and then you can
click on any of these icons and you will be taken to the organism
group.
And this is actually how it then looks like.
On the left-hand side, you have all the different organism groups that
are already in FADA-TiMS. And here you have the
big overview side. And on the overview, you can not only see
the species name and the author, the family, whether it's
accepted or not, and if it's a synonym, for example, you will be
directed to the accepted species with
right one mouse click. And then we have the,
where is it? The biogeographic information, and then also
the tag, whether it's aquatic species or water-dependent species and
whether it's freshwater or brackish and so on.
For the public, if you are not sure what you are looking for, you have the
search field over here where you just can type in a name and you
will be directed into the organism group where the species belongs.
And we have also the filter option over here where
you can actually,
for example, just filter for one specific biogeographic
region.
If you then click on this little triangle over here, you will see the detail page,
and it goes down here, of course,
with all the hierarchical information, and down here,
taxonomic information, taxonomic references, environmental
information, environmental references, and also the linking to
other
infrastructures. Like you can see already here,
the green
button brings you directly to GBIF and the occurrence
records, and the red button brings you to the Red List if there
is an assessment.
So for the expert, the detailed view looks a little
bit different. So they have all these editable fields over
here where they can actually change what they want to change.
And
on top here, we keep track who added the species and when it was
last modified and by when. So you always know who worked in
your file.
Okay, this is what experts create.
So the names, the synonyms, the classification, the authorships, the FADA
environmental regions, environmental information, and the FADA
distribution.
And then we also offer exports. Exports in terms
of PDF files, PDF files ordered by family,
CSV files, and also versioned checklists that
get the DOI from Checklist Bank. And, yeah,
you can click on-- So once the authors tell us they
are finalized, we can click on a button and say establish a
versioned checklist. And, yeah, you can see
this then down here
right below the headline that there is a versioned checklist available.
And if you click at the tiny button over there,
you will directly be directed to this checklist.
And this is basically how I see the freshwater
biodiversity data ecosystem. In the middle, we have
FADA-TiMS,
and then we have TaxonWorks and WoRMS, where we harvest species
into FADA-TiMS, and the little green arrow shows you that we link back to the
systems as well.
And then we have Catalogue of Life, where we deliver the checklist,
and we get back the DOI for our versioned checklists.
And then we have GBIF. So GBIF harvests the
species from Catalogue of Life, and we link, of course, back
to GBIF, as you have seen. This is the only minor thing.
What we are still missing is this tag for freshwater species in
GBIF, but we have discussed this already on Tuesday, so this should be solved.
Yeah. And then this is what we are going to do in the future.
We will link to other databases like Freshwater Ecology or
the Red List Database in terms of that the Red List Database also
takes the
real taxonomy, so the good taxonomy as a backbone.
And then all this
information also serves as taxonomic
backbone of the Freshwater Information Platform data portal that
Vanessa will talk about and the FP system that Helen will
actually talk about.
And what we then additionally have is the GBIF freshwater
data publishing guide.
This was published a few years ago, which should help
scientists to actually
prepare their data in a way they can be uploaded to
GBIF, and this can be done with the Freshwater Information Platform IPT
So
there is not a need to store everything
in FADA Tims, but it is
very important to make FADA Tims interoperable so that
really the reliable taxonomy can be linked
up with every other infrastructure.
Shortly coming back to the workflow from expert curation to
citable data. This is how ChatGPT imagines that it works.
We have an API,
and we can also export ColDB data packages
that are then delivered to Checklist Bank, where we get the DOI.
And then this is actually the only thing that is
the incentive for our scientists, that they get a
DOI for their checklist, which makes the checklist really
citable and can be seen easier.
Yeah.
So
we've heard this also several times during this conference.
The challenge is sustainability in terms of people,
who curates and who keeps the experts engaged,
who replaces retiring experts or experts who
died,
and then also in terms of infrastructure, who maintains the database,
who maintains the mapping between the systems,
and in terms of interoperability, who published the
version checklist, for example, and who keeps the data
exchange aligned with evolving standards?
So I think these are
main things that I would also like to discuss later in the
afternoon.
We have
a bit of a short-term solution that is called FADA More.
It's a follow-up project of InfraFADA, and it will help us
to maintain the whole system during the next three
years.
But we will not only maintain the data, we will
also enrich the data. So we will add molecular data and
cryptic diversity. We will add parasites and
host relationships, and then we will also add more ecological
information and
also the connections to ecological databases like
freshwater ecology.info.
And then we have the FB system, the Freshwater Biodiversity Information
System,
where Helen will talk about because this really is something
that is super useful.
You are having different signs.
Okay, I have still two minutes. Thank you.
So this BIM system works with a multi-tenant
community, meaning that
more or different infrastructures share the development,
share the maintenance, and share the technical support.
And this is also something that can help us to sustain and maintain
our infrastructure in future.
So to summarize this slide, projects end, taxonomy
must not. Communities and shared
infrastructures can persist, but we need to talk about how.
And this brings me to my final slide.
It's not just another database. It's
not just a place to store species names.
It's a mechanism for keeping freshwater taxonomy expert-curated,
makes the knowledge interoperable and usable, and connects
freshwater taxonomy to the wider
biodiversity data ecosystem.
So the future of freshwater
biodiversity data depends not on more databases, but on better
interconnectedness and interoperability.
And
with that, I want to thank you for your attention, and I think the time is up, and
can we answer one question?
There's no time for que-- but first let's thank the two ladies.
So there's no time for questions, but after the final talk, we have about a slot of
10 minutes or so to ask questions about the whole series.
So thank you very much,
Astrid and Geraldine.
And then it's my pleasure to announce the next speaker,
who is known to
all of you, I'm sure, Olaf Beunke from Catalogue of Life.
His title,
not
surprisingly, starts with Catalogue of Life
and Freshwater Species Data.
And Olaf will
science this talk together with his collaborators, Diana Hernandez
and Camila Plata.
So
all yours.
Thank you. Can you hear me?
Okay. Then we already start
until--
Yeah. Is it working? Thanks.
Thanks so much,
and great to see you in this session.
Oh, I don't see my slides myself here.
So how does that work?
Okay.
And
I fare in the blind. Yeah, if you can show them up there, it's more easy.
PowerPoint?
No, it's just PDF.
Oh, then it doesn't.
Then it doesn't show. Okay. So you can see what I'm
going to present. I can't see it. So that makes
it real easy. I can
stand in front of my presentation in that case.
Okay. I guess you know what we do as Catalogue of Life.
Before we go into freshwater specific
data, I just wanted to give you a little bit of
insights into Catalogue of Life.
This is actually the 25th year that the Catalogue
of Life
is being made publicly available.
I want to acknowledge my colleague, Yuri Raskov,
over there, who's been
there with Catalogue of Life for most of that
part. But actually, activities already started
before that in 1996, so that's already 30 years.
So we make a global species list, and we
have many reasons why we do that, but one most
important
usage is to reconcile open biodiversity
data.
Ah. Technology works with us. So this is
courtesy by
Ed DeWalt and Jeff Ower.
It needs to be updated, but this is showing you
all the co-authors from the year 2022,
and their host institutes around the world.
So you can see we have global coverage
of authors, but of data creators, but
there are also a large part of empty spaces
there. So we still have a job to make sure that the
entire world is connected
to us.
Now, here, the blue line just gives you across
those 25 years, how say, the growth in the
accepted species. We are, for that
release,
slightly above 2.2 million accepted species.
And the red line is synonyms. So you can
see we are steadily improving.
Now,
this year, we are publishing two versions.
We are publishing this base release that is compiled of
global
species lists, but we also are
extending that information. And, for example, we're adding
publications from Plazi to it,
Unite Species Hypothesis, Barcode of Life,
for example, and the rest just shows
you a couple of our biggest contributors.
Of course, I'm just showing here the biggest one, but also our
smallest contributors we really like and
acknowledge their work.
Now, how can you access us? We basically have
a
data infrastructure that is Checklist Bank.
In fact, all our tooling are there and,
how you say, we run different front ends from the
API. So all our functionality, all data is
in the API for starters.
You can access catalogueoflife.org, the latest
release that is there, or you can go to Checklist Bank,
where you can find multiple sources.
So basically, that infrastructure has three
functions. I'm not going to show them all in this talk because we don't
have time for that.
I could, but probably somebody will get angry.
So one is that we are having this open data
repository for any type of list,
taxonomic, nomenclature, but also policy
relevant list, for example. But also all our tooling,
how we are assembling our data products are in
Checklist Bank.
And then there are a bunch of tools available for
users to say, "Hey, what is the difference
actually between these different lists?"
So I'm just going into the first one because
you can see there are 65,000 data sources in
Checklist Bank at the moment. Every month, that's growing with a
few hundred thousand,
and that is mostly publications that come
in through us through Plazi, EWT, and Pensoft.
But
sort of rough analysis shows that we have about
1,000 national related species list already
there.
About 400 of them are, for example, invasive
species lists. And then we got about 200
global species lists. So I'm just showing you this because this is
the availability of the data that we have
right now in front of us.
Now, let's zoom into the freshwater checklist, and
immediately, I have to admit, we run into
troubles, because how do you actually export that
or find in our own data product
what is freshwater and what is not?
And
we're not good at it, I have to admit.
But what we also observe is that there are data sources
out there that we could integrate, but that aren't published
yet. And so here's an example of
freshwaterecology.info at the European level.
It's not in our infrastructure,
but if we start to match with the accepted names,
then basically,
most groups really do well. So we have coverage,
but not, for example, in the Phyto benthos.
So you can see that publishing a list like that
would help us,
how you say, integrate the data better.
Here's another example, and
this is not fully comprehensive, our search, but I'm
just showing you that we were exploring, getting
excited, and then Diana found this list.
This one does match 100% with
the Catalogue of Life,
but it's still relevant to get such a data list in because
maybe it contains other types of information,
references,
how you say, whatever,
better authorships for higher ranks that we could
integrate.
And then, of course, there's our trusted partner, WoRMS,
World Register of Marine Species.
They,
how you say, have a real active network that
is creating all the time. And the nice thing that they are
doing is that they have,
how you say, these species profiles where they
are stating that something is marine,
freshwater, brackish, or terrestrial.
However, we are not showing that on our front ends,
and that is because we don't even have it in our back end.
At least we have it, but we cannot model it in our front end.
Sorry, I should have said that.
If you then look at the matching,
then actually it goes pretty well with the Catalogue of Life
except for algae.
And that's a problem that we unfortunately know.
We are still trying to get,
how you say, the global list of algae, AlgaeBase,
on an open data license. There's history there.
We hope that we can collaborate better in the future.
Now, if we go to FADA itself, we
do contain still four lists of, how you say, the
previous assessment from 2013.
These
have not been updated
in our systems, which is really something, a target that
we would like to
get. And this is, of course, fully integrated
into
our system. Now, the new FADA will have these
species profiles,
and that's going to be really interesting
for us, and I come back to that. Now,
a further assessment into Checklist Bank
tells us that there are about 1,700
datasets that have somewhere freshwater in their
title. And when we then go investigate, most of them
are actually publications and coming from Plazi.
Yes, sir.
So our conclusion of this little search is there are a
couple of things that we can do better
together, and, how you say,
then we enter a way forward. There were other
titles here, a way forward into the muddy
waters.
Let's create transparent water, but that's all too funny,
so we're not doing that. It's serious business, this.
So this is more or less the proposition.
We've been conversing, what can we
actually do better and what is our current
situation?
Our current situation is we already get some data in,
for example, from WoRMS, and they are already giving us
a clear indication whether something is freshwater,
yes or not.
Now, the intent is that we are connecting to FADA teams.
That has already an export into the Catalogue of Life data
package, so we can communicate to one another.
And pretty soon,
I'm sure that data sources will be updated in the
Catalogue of Life. I'm looking forward to that.
But FADA is also itself talking about, how you say,
the freshwater designations, and just like
me, I'm also water dependent, by the way.
We would like to get those designations into Catalogue of
Life as well, and we can't at the moment.
So we expect that
more or less in a year's time. Can I say that? Promise that?
Yes, I can. So next year, we're probably
going to present to you that we have integrated
this
information and it's updated.
But we cannot make promises without promising ourselves
something.
So what we will be doing is looking into
whether we can also include this designation,
brackish, freshwater, water dependent, aquatic,
into our systems and update that
also in the API.
From there,
since we are the taxonomic reference for GBIF,
it will also be possible to, how you say,
to get a better handle of what are the
freshwater species and occurrences
actually out there. And as I understood that
this is a discussion of 15 years,
getting
out of existing data
An understanding what is actually the freshwater
biodiversity, and can we do better analysis on it?
So this is our pledge in this collaboration that we would
solve that problem.
And so next year,
if we haven't done it, then
let's do it. That's the better thing. Yes. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Thank you very much, Olaf. So here we have time for one quick question
and a quick answer.
Nobody? We'll postpone it until after the-
Well, maybe I have one more additional thing.
Basically,
there's nothing stopping us from publishing
freshwater
species lists. So if you have anything available,
please knock on our door, and let's get it up
into Checklist Bank so that we can
evaluate it.
Thank you for this answer without the question.
Yeah.
I'm good at that.
It's now my pleasure to announce the next speaker,
who is Alejandra Correa Botella from Colombia, and
she will talk about a species-level taxonomic catalog
of Neotropical freshwater insects, building a consensus
reference for occurrence data integration and conservation
planning. Alejandra.
Thank you.
Okay. Thank you all for being here.
So before I get into the data, let me
give you a shape of this talk. I will walk through five different steps.
Okay. Yes. Here.
First, I will talk about what exists, the checklist itself.
Second, is it reliable? The verification and
against global data infrastructure that I have done.
Then the structural gaps, what that verification has revealed.
Fourth, I will ground into a real case of application in
Colombia, a river in Colombia, the River Samaná Norte.
And then the fifth step would be how to put all of this
into practice doing a spatial prioritization and the real dam
development pressure that we have in my country.
So the Neotropics stretch down from going
from Mexico, going down through South America,
and our rivers and streams hold an unparalleled
taxonomic reach, especially for freshwater fauna.
Yet that richness is where the knowledge is the least.
So here what we see in general,
globally, freshwater populations have declined around
83% since 1970, according to a report
from the Living Planet. But this proportion gets higher in Latin
America and the Caribbean,
where it reaches 95%. On the left, we see data
deficient hotspots. The darker the blue, the more
species we know almost nothing about.
And this is particularly where Central America and Southern
America sits, where the richness knowledge is the least.
My country, Colombia, my home country, sits at the right
corner of this paradox. We are known to be the
most diverse country on Earth.
For every 10 species, we do know that one of those is
described to be occurring in Colombia.
Yet we don't have
a stable list of a species name for freshwater insects.
Here we see a different scenario. This is the dam expansion.
So globally, there are plenty of dams, and in the
Neotropics, there are plenty to be constructed in the future.
We see how the pressure is concentrated right along here, the
Andean slopes.
So we are modifying natural flows before we even have the
data to assess
what we are being lost. And this is not a coincidence.
Biodiversity data gaps and development pressures all converge
here, and that convergence is the core problem that I
address in my PhD project. Without
taxonomy or without names, without a checklist, none of
it can be properly evaluated, especially in the
scenario that we do have in the Neotropics countries.
So what I will show you today in this talk,
every number that I will show you today
tries to answer the question, how much of the
diversity can we actually name, can we actually find, and can we
actually use? That is what matters.
So here I present a checklist that I have been
doing during the last six months, covering
seven order of freshwater insects for the Neotropics.
It's better to say that it covers from southern Mexico going down
until Brazil. I don't include information from Argentina, Uruguay,
Chile, and Paraguay because according to Moron biogeographic
regions, this corresponds to a very different region for the rest of the
countries. And as expected, Coleoptera and
Diptera
have the highest number of richness, and this reflects
both through biological diversity, but also reflects
where our regional taxonomic fort is being put in the Neotropics.
It's also worth noting that orders such as Odonata,
Trichoptera, and Hemiptera and Ephemeroptera are the
four most actively studied orders in the Neotropical
regions, and this is according to a
paper published based on the abstract sent to
our regional symposium of aquatic insects in Brazil.
This isn't an arbitrary scope.
This reflects where
the regional community effort is being put.
Now, I want to be very explicit about this.
This is a taxon core list. That means I show
here species names, synonyms, taxonomic
classification. What I'm showing you here is the naming
backbone that needs to be done before any data
occurrence could be downloaded, and therefore resolved
and used as evidence
for downstream analysis. To keep that backbone at
true species level information, I
only include officially described species, as well as
where a genus has no reliable genus, or many genera
have no reliable species level information, I keep it like that.
But having a checklist isn't the same as having a complete one
checklist, and the gap isn't the same everywhere.
So why focus on Colombia? First, because it's the country where I come
from.
Second,
because Colombia, as seen on this map,
is the country with the highest number of documented species
of those seven orders of freshwater insects.
I have so far around 1,250 species,
and this is not because Colombia is
biologically exceptionally in isolation, even though we
think that it is, but it's because Colombia sits
or is located right here at the center or in the middle
of heterogeneous biogeographic subregions that we have
in the Neotropics. But documented just means a name
that is attributed to that country.
No, it doesn't mean that the occurrence data that we could
therefore download is verifiable.
Let's take this example.
Oh, sorry.
This is Anachroneura nolicoda. This is a stonefly
that is known to occur in Mexico, Central America, Peru,
and Brazil. And these are the occurrence records
that
this species has now in GBIF.
On paper, its distribution should possibly include
Colombia as well. But taxonomic resolution bias,
this is what I think now. Taxonomic resolution bias, that means
how records get matched to correct names, leaves this species
effectively invisible for Colombian data.
This is the same species but different dataset.
Here, I showed the Plecoptera species file.
Suddenly, the same species,
based on this dataset, is distributed or has occurrence
records almost in all the countries for the Neotropics.
But look what is still missing. Colombia.
Now, we don't have occurrence data for this species so far.
And it's curious because this is the country which sits at the
geographical center of the species' range size, as you can
see here
in this map.
So that means, or we cannot say that it's because the species is not
in Colombia or could not be in Colombia.
We can say that it's because no one has looked for it, because no one
has named it for Colombia, therefore look for it, therefore identify it, and
therefore upload the record in GBIF or other
platform.
Now let me show you this in the base case scenario that we currently have
in my country, Hemiptera.
I can say that Hemiptera is one of the most actively studied
orders in Colombia. The top contributor authors and
describers of new species from my checklist are
Colombian active researchers. And I see this as a
genuine strength because this science and
taxonomy is not dependent anymore on single or
collective international efforts anymore.
And yet, take Owatometra uesa. This species
was described in 1942. However, the first Colombian record that we
have was published in 2018.
And even now, the species has zero GBIF
occurrence records.
Then matching these names against GBIF or
other global data infrastructure reveals
that there is a disagree in the way how the data is being done.
To be clear, I'm not saying this is a failure of GBIF or any global data
infrastructure because they work with the data that
have been already published, digitized, and mobilized.
But what I do say is that we have a data supply gap,
not a platform problem. On the left here, what I
show is some of the analysis that I have done
and verification flags across three orders, Coleoptera, Trichoptera, and
Hemiptera. Coleoptera shows the highest volume, is
corresponding to mostly recent nomenclature changes, subgenera raised
to full
genera. And also, Trichoptera flags are
different in form because they relate more with typographic, algorhythmical
errors. Hemiptera shows a bit of everything, including
one genus reassignment.
Now let's quantify the same idea, but comparing with worldwide
estimated diversity. So this is the proportion that my
checklist
offers in comparison to what has been described for
the world in Trichoptera and what has been described or is being
estimated for this order in the world.
Now, the same pattern, Odonata, a completely different order.
Damselflies and dragonflies. Same layout as before,
described, estimated, and so on. But now I want you
to point the attention to this. This is TaxonMia.
This is a Colombian effort, a novel, a huge, immense
effort that my colleagues did in my country
four years ago.
And my checklist right now triples the number of
Odonata species for Colombia, which is great,
I think.
So now, I
said before that, and I really think that this makes no sense if
we don't put it into practice.
And especially because in the Neotropic, everything is needed.
And here, what you see is this beautiful river.
I took this picture a week ago.
And this is the river Samaná,
Samaná Norte. It's the only river of its size
in the mountainous Andean region in Colombia, where I'm from,
that still flows freely, meaning no dams.
However, two dams are planned to be constructed in the coming years.
But dams, as usual,
aren't the only problem that we have or the only pressure the river
has. The river drains directly into the Magdalena River.
Magdalena River is the biggest or the most important macrobasin
that we have in Colombia. All our economy depends on that
basin. And now the Magdalena basin holds
an established population of invasive species.
So this is considered the biggest problem that we have in this river yet.
So I show all of this because this is exactly the kind of basin
you would want a strong biodiversity data for,
because it is under real pressure to change.
Something that has resonated with me during this week,
resulting from all the talks, is that data are meant to represent the truth.
Now, the data need to be interpretable.
And when data becomes that, people can really use it as
evidence. I did the job to search for the occurrences
in this, the seven order freshwater insect occurrences
in this basin, and the data is limited.
Let's say that we have around 600 occurrence records
along the whole basin, and they resolve only to genus
level, not to species level.
So
I think this is what
is being collected. It's not interpretable for making
decisions in real conservation processes.
And that has a domino effect. No species level,
no occurrence data.
Then again, no species names means no occurrence data.
No occurrence data means no data for doing SDMs,
species distribution modeling. That is the main purpose of my talk, of my
PhD project. Thank you.
No SDMs means no habitat suitability information.
There is no way to address the Leibigian and Wallacean shortfall if we do not
even have the species names. And that means no
possibility to know the biogeographic patterns along the whole
Magdalena River Basin. Means no evidence to argue
with data that this river should be protected, and in the
case of River Samaná, to keep it free from dams.
So, as I said, Samaná is also part of my whole study area for my
PhD project. So a fair question that maybe you might
have after all my talk is, why build this
checklist for the whole Neotropics if I'm just working in Colombia?
Or my area of study is Colombia. Because Colombia
alone lacks what a country-only reference would need.
We don't have species-level names.
We don't have verified occurrences.
I'm talking about the seven orders of freshwater insects.
And taxonomy and insects do not know
about geopolitical borders. So you saw this example
with Anachrony and Olicaudia. Only once you check the
literature coming from neighboring countries such as
Ecuador, Peru, Venezuela, and Brazil, you will know that the
species would probably exist in Colombia.
So there was no time to wait for Colombia, and it's
why my checklist takes the neotropical
scope,
and this is, I think,
what Colombia actually requires now. Thank you.
Thank you very much, Alejandra. You kept exactly on time.
So once again, in fact, no time for questions, but
the next talk is virtual. Maybe while this is being set up,
if there is somebody who has a question for Alejandra or for any of the previous
speakers?
No. Okay.
The next talk is going to be virtual
and will be given by Helen Dallas. I hope she's online.
Good afternoon.
Okay.
My name is Helen Dallas. I'm from the Freshwater Research Centre based in Cape
Town, South Africa. The title of my talk is Biodiversity
Data at Your Fingertips. I'll be sharing with you details of the
freshwater biodiversity information systems that we have developed for South
Africa and scaled up for Africa. And I'm presenting on
behalf of my co-authors, Jeremy Shelton,
Nazli Little from the Freshwater Research Centre, as well as
my colleagues, Dimos Trikomkos and Tim Sutton from
CartoSA.
All of this work has been funded by the JRS Biodiversity Foundation.
Freshwater biodiversity data are essential for monitoring ecosystem
change, for informing conservation, and for supporting
evidence-based management of freshwater ecosystems.
However, such data are often fragmented, both across
institutions and regions,
often inaccessible, and thus valuable data are very difficult to discover
or poorly integrated across scales and taxonomic groups.
Data are therefore often underused in decision-making,
and yet the threats to freshwater ecosystems continue to grow.
The Freshwater Biodiversity Information System, FBIS,
and FBIS Africa platforms, developed for South Africa
and for Africa respectively, respond
directly to this challenge by connecting data,
people, and decisions.
The process to develop FBIS for South Africa started back in
2017. A user-centered approach was
followed to allow us to design backwards based on the
needs of the end users.
The design and functionality of FBIS have thus been shaped by
key user groups, including, but not limited to
water resource managers, conservation managers and
planners, researchers and scientists,
environmental consultants, and policymakers.
The result is a powerful visual data-rich
system designed to host, share, and
explore freshwater biodiversity data in South
Africa.
The platform currently holds more than 14 million occurrence
records of freshwater taxa on the platform.
FBIS has eight biodiversity modules, including
fish, annelids, invertebrates,
wetland and riparian plants, algae,
wetland birds, and water-dependent mammals and
reptiles. We have a growing freshwater community
with 1,648 registered users
on the platform, and these users are currently
actively uploading and downloading data
from the platform.
Importantly, in South Africa, we are using freshwater data from
FBIS to support science conservation
and management of freshwater ecosystems in the country.
So what data tools have we developed in FBIS
to turn biodiversity records into usable information?
Firstly, there is a taxonomic management system
that uses the taxonomic backbone of the global
biodiversity information facility to provide the
taxonomic information for each taxon on the
platform. Going forward, in collaboration with FADA,
we will be integrating these platforms so that they all speak to each other.
There are also links
to the IUCN for global conservation status for
those species that have been red-listed.
Occurrence data is the primary currency of the platform, and a
range of queries and filters have been developed to allow the
extraction of subsets of data based on a user
query or filter application.
For example, a range of spatial filters and temporal
filters are available, and these can be applied
independently or in combination to provide very
powerful filtering opportunities for extracting data.
There are a number of visual spatial layers that have been
served on the various platforms, and these are specifically for
visualizing the data, and these include, for example,
layers related to management, catchments,
ecoregions, vegetation, climate,
protected areas, and conservation layers.
This is just an example of some of the layers on the platforms.
We've also developed a range of standardized dashboards
which translate the occurrence records into
easy-to-use information. This information includes
maps, overview information, graphs,
metadata, and other visual tools for displaying
data. Importantly, every single occurrence record
on the FBIS and FBIS Africa platforms have
associated with it metadata to allow for
citation and attribution.
All graphs and data may be downloaded for including in reports and
for further analysis.
In designing the FBIS, the intention was to design it in a
way that the platform could serve not
only the needs of the FBIS South Africa community, but
could serve as an underlying engine for other information
systems.
And this was possible by separating the underlying engine from
the data, and this has enabled FBIS South Africa
to be modified and deployed for other platforms, including
non-freshwater platforms, as well as being scaled up for
Africa.
Therefore, FBIS
Africa is a move from national to continental scale,
and it is rapidly expanding in both data coverage and user
uptake.
The ambition
for FBIS Africa is a stronger community of freshwater biodiversity
data users and contributors across Africa
for the betterment of Africa's freshwater ecosystems and people.
Both FBIS and the FBIS Africa platforms
interoperate with global biodiversity infrastructures,
including GBIF and the IUCN Red List of Threatened
Species, and in this way, they contribute to a more connected
and accessible freshwater data ecosystem.
By combining regional expertise, open
infrastructure,
interoperable data workflows, and powerful biodiversity
analysis tools, FBIS and FBIS-Africa demonstrate
how community-driven information systems can support fair
biodiversity data mobilization and translate
biodiversity knowledge into
actionable conservation and management
outcomes.
One information ecosystem, multiple scales.
From the level of site, to catchment, to national,
to continental, to global.
Each level adds value while remaining connected
to the others.
And thus regional expertise can therefore contribute to
continental and global biodiversity knowledge.
A multi-tenant model has been used for improving
sustainability of all platforms, with each
tenant onboarded experiencing independent
governance and customized branding of their platforms.
Those of you who have been involved in development of information systems in the
past know the challenge associated with
sustainability, both in terms of funding but also in terms
of data.
There are benefits to be had
from this multi-tenant model, and these include
beneficial cost savings,
improved technical infrastructure,
platform improvements shared across all tenants,
and increased resilience across all platforms.
Reflecting back on the FBIS and FBIS-Africa journeys,
I'd like to share with you five design principles that we feel
demonstrate the success of the FBIS
model.
Firstly,
stakeholder co-design promotes uptake and value.
Interoperability with systems such as GBIF and IUCN
multiplies the impacts of the platform.
Open access
enables collaboration and innovation,
and sustained support and partnerships were an
essential ingredient to the success of both FBIS and
FBIS-Africa.
The incorporation of multi-tenancy increases resilience
and fosters sustainability of all the platforms.
So why does this matter for freshwater biodiversity?
Freshwater ecosystems support biodiversity, people, and
economies. So it's not just about freshwater biodiversity.
There's a very strong link to people and economies.
Data-informed decisions are critical in the face of rapid
change,
and open accessible data empower diverse
users across Africa and beyond.
Stronger data ecosystems enable a more resilient and
sustainable future for all.
In conclusion,
open, interoperable, and user-driven biodiversity
information systems can transform freshwater data
into action.
Thank you for your attention.
Thank you very much, Helen, in case you hear me.
She does.
So,
which brings us seamless to the last talk of the first session in
our freshwater
session, and that is Vanessa Bremmerich,
and she will introduce the FIBioData
portal towards an integrated freshwater biodiversity
data ecosystem.
If I manage.
Okay. Hello, everyone. Let me just briefly introduce the
team that has been working on this biodiversity data portal.
So there's Helen, who just gave the excellent talk on
the FBIS before.
Tim and Dimas, who are the
core developers from this company, Kartosa.
From the Leibniz Institute of Freshwater Ecology and Inland
Fisheries in Berlin, where I am based, it's myself and
Sonja, and also Astrid has been working a lot on
this.
So let me give you just a very quick run-through
of the background. Of course, we heard before that FADA
started way before everything else.
But for me, the story started with the BioFresh project,
which ran between 2009 and 2014. And there
we were looking at the status, trends, pressures, and conservation
priorities of freshwater biodiversity.
After the end of the project, a group of four of
the partner institutes and university
founded the Freshwater Information Platform to maintain all the excellent
data products that came out of this project.
And
this includes the ones who are here, plus also University
Duisburg-Essen.
And it also contained the very first Freshwater Biodiversity Data
Portal, which was an excellent valuable resource at the
time because you could go there and just filter and search
for freshwater species and download and use it for your research.
But I will quote Astrid here from your talk.
It was a valuable resource, but it needed a reboot.
So it was actually quite hard to maintain, to keep up to date.
Luckily, we got the Infra FADA project that you heard
about. So without the renewal of this taxonomic backbone,
making a new data portal wouldn't have made sense at all.
So this is absolutely central to what we are trying to do here.
Luckily or maybe not so luckily, at around the
same time at IGB, we were part or we
got funded a special investigation program
that was looking at the causes and recovery after this
Oder environmental catastrophe. You might have heard of it.
There was a huge fish kill.
So instead of creating some new resource
to put all the data that have come out of this project, we took some
funds to renew the already existing
FIB biodiversity data portal, and we were very
lucky to be able to partner with the Freshwater Research
Center here and also Kat Rosa who had been doing absolutely
great work.
So what is this data portal? It is the
renewed Freshwater Biodiversity Data Portal in the Freshwater Information
Platform. It is built on the Biodiversity Information
Management System, BIMS, that Helen just
introduced.
I'm actually quite glad to see that it has been talked about quite a lot on
this conference. You may have seen it also on Monday where
Judith presented the Sand Parks portal.
So it also works very well for non-freshwater
applications.
So I think in this data portal, the community that we mostly
represent is, of course, the partners from the Freshwater Information Platform
and FADA. But also we are part, or
let's say we are involved in data mobilization efforts in
Freshwater BON,
which is the Freshwater Biodiversity Observation Network in
GeoBON.
And
so for instance here, it would be one of the applications to
help with developing the freshwater essential biodiversity
variables.
So the portal is going to be able to show data availability because we
will have all the freshwater occurrences from GBIF there.
It will also link to the IOC and Red List status for all the
taxa that are available. And through this, I
think we will also be able to show data gaps
per FADA organism group based on this taxonomic
backbone.
Then what is FIBio not? We
haven't discussed this yet, so this is my personal opinion in a way.
It is not yet or not at all the OBIS for
freshwaters. You might have heard about OBIS.
It's the Ocean Biodiversity Information System for
freshwaters.
It's an excellent resource and community, and I think in
freshwaters
we are kind of lacking this commitment and this
community that is truly global and funded.
So maybe we can
carry that over into the discussion round.
So what we are doing is mostly because we, as
research institutions, think that this is super important.
We are trying to create a valuable data resource for our
researchers.
Yeah, and we definitely want to keep doing that.
So what it is also not, it's not very focused on
regional or national resources or also not for
national or regional assessments.
Of course, you can upload very small scale data or just single sampling
sites, but those won't be linked to that very specific
information that you might have for your country or your national
park or whatever. So if you are interested in that aspect,
please get in touch directly with Helen.
I think the model she presented, this BIMS multi-tenant
model, is actually very excellent
to set up such a specialized portal.
Also what it is not, it's not fully available in a
production environment, so we are still finalizing the few
last steps. So if you stumble upon our developed version,
please keep in mind
that what you find there is not
the last version.
Okay.
Maybe the most important aspect or motivation of this data
portal is that we wanted to make it very easy to
follow the guidelines
laid out in this GBIF Freshwater Data Publishing Guide.
It was authored last year, Astrid already mentioned it, by Astrid and
Jen.
And it contains valuable descriptions
of best practices for freshwater data publishing.
Also information on the necessary metadata fields
to describe these sample locations and the sampling methods
so that
meta-analysis across data sets becomes possible.
It also has some
ideas on freshwater specific amendment fields to the Darwin Core and
some recommendations for new fields.
So whoops.
One of the recommendations we already integrated into the data portal
are the freshwater organism groups.
So we call them meta groups in the data portal.
As you saw, FADA contains more than 60 groups,
but researchers often search or filter these broader,
more common groups,
and they can find both the FADA groups and the meta groups in the
portal. So for instance,
you could be interested just looking at macrophytes or
macroinvertebrates, amphibians, fish, or birds, and then you can
also filter only these broader
groups.
Another aspect here, as you can see, freshwater
fungi, benthic algae, and phytoplankton is
currently not part of FADA.
So
we will come up with different ways to add checklists for these
groups. Fortunately,
we are working with very
excellent experts on these organisms in our institutions,
in our networks. So I hope that we will be able to provide
some information
on what the freshwater taxa are in these groups, but it will
definitely not be on the same level as the curated standard lists
like they are in FADA.
Okay. Another important aspect is the additional
information that we want to add to the sampling sites.
So for instance, we want to collect
information on the habitat, on the ecosystem type, but also
on sampling methods and organism lifecycle stages and sample
timing, because this is really
crucial information to work with the data later on.
So,
in the system, when we enter new data, we always start with the sampling site,
then we add this aforementioned additional information.
We can also look for what kind of information is already in the
system available from FADA, GBIF, or IUCN Red
List.
Then we go and add our list of species from biotic
samples or eDNA sampling.
And at the same time or at the same site, it would be
also super interesting to see what else is available, or
we
go there and we take some additional information.
So we have some abiotic measurements, for instance, from sensors like
temperature, water level, oxygen levels, something else.
Or we do have water quality parameters like salinity and
nitrate loads. So we also want to add this into the same
system so that cross-analysis becomes more easy, so we can
compare the biotic and abiotic data levels.
We also started adding information derived from remote sensing, like
chlorophyll a time series, water color data, water surface
extent would also be possible, or land use in the catchment.
And lastly, the system annotates the data or the sampling site
locations with information from geographic reference layers
and
catchment scale data.
So let's have a closer look at this point.
We want to enrich the data with freshwater-specific automated
workflows for both annotation and quality
control. So when we add a site to the BIMs
or the FIB,
we automatically query the already configured reference
layers in the system. So basically, for this point,
we can then add
as an annotation all the unique IDs of these
reference layers. So it could be, for instance, ecosystem or habitat types,
lake IDs, riparian zones, wetlands, RAMSA sites, and so
on.
So this already happens. Then there's another aspect, which is the
catchment scale data. I think this is,
as you mentioned, something that is really unique
to freshwaters that we also need to take this connectivity into account.
And here we will look to connect to external tools
and processes,
and look at the connectivity along the river network in the lake catchments.
And for these catchments, we can also get environmental data on the
hydrology, land use, soil, and so on.
So,
in parallel to the development of this data portal, there were several
projects
that were funded from the German National Data Infrastructures,
NFDI, for biodiversity and for Earth.
For instance, the Hydrographer R package, the GeoFresh platform
that have all these capabilities that I just
described. There's also an EOSC project called AquaInfra that
works on creating these reproducible
workflows. There's a package here, for instance, that can
flag outliers.
Just a quick run through how this looks like.
So when we have this sampling site, what we can do is snap it to
the river network. So get the ID of the closest segment,
then also delineate the upstream catchment and get all
this information.
So,
one other thing that we really want to do is feedback into the
communities. So what we really think is crucial is some
kind of way of automated data quality control or quality
flagging.
So one idea would be to use the environmental
information or species traits to flag outliers.
Another one would be
that we
use these rule-based informations.
John Waller gave an excellent talk on this on Tuesday, I think it
was.
And then we can have a feedback loop with the expert and say, "Okay, look, we found
maybe your species
does occur somewhere else," or, "Maybe this occurrence is
not really correct." So I tried out this tool that John
Waller from GBIF developed. So for instance, in FADA, we do
have the information that a certain species ...
is a Neotropical one like this example.
So here in this nice little tool, we can upload the
FADA biogeographical realm and say everything that is not
in this
very coarse thing will be flagged as suspicious.
Something to think about. And then last,
we do have a bit of a roadmap. Some of this came directly
from talks that we had with this great community
here at TADWIG.
So we do want to check how freshwater habitats and
freshwater dependence
is described in EnvO and maybe add to this.
I already described the quality control loops.
And one other thing, please check also the talk we have
from Daniel in the second part of the session, where we want to also
integrate a globally standardized river basin name
database in our
portal. So thank you very much. Also, on behalf
of the Freshwater Information Platform team
and Freshwater Born and our funders.
Thank you very much.
So as promised, we now have time for some questions,
discussion. I would like to make two announcements.
The speakers of this session and the next one should stay a little bit because we
need a picture for the funders. And please come all
back because after the break, there is more goodies for all of
us.
Okay, so you have heard now a series of talks
all circling around freshwater
biodiversity. You heard about the past and the future
FADA.
You heard everything you ever wanted to hear about the Catalogue of Life and more.
You heard about how student projects can actually integrate and use
the information and data sets. You have
heard what they have done in South Africa and in the whole of Africa.
Pretty impressive. And Vanessa has shown you the future
of how freshwater data is going to be integrated.
There is no excuse not to be interested in this.
Have more questions or have suggestions or have
a topic for discussion for later on.
They're just nodding.
Okay. Well, we have six minutes, so before we have to go for coffee.
I know this is the afternoon session. We had a fantastic lunch.
Everybody's nodding a bit in a different way.
So how would you, if you would be involved in this
information platform, what would you change? What would you do different?
What would you add
from your own point of view? All of you here have your own different
perspectives, projects. Please.
Please introduce yourself also.
I have to introduce myself because-
There's a microphone coming. There's a microphone coming.
Thank you. You hear me, everyone?
Yeah. Oh, yes.
My name is Anne Lykke Solheim, and I work at the Norwegian Institute for
Water Research here in Oslo.
And I'm a limnologist by training and have worked with
phytoplankton ecology mainly for my
whole career, also relating a lot to European work
and European projects,
working for the European Environment Agency for many years
and also for the Joint Research Center in
northern Italy.
Mm-hmm.
So I have various backgrounds. And I
will give a talk later on, the last talk, actually, in the session.
But my question now is to
all of you, especially those who have presented so far.
To me, it seems like a myriad,
too many
biodiversity information platforms.
I
think Catalogue of Life is what I've heard of before, and
also GBIF, and I've worked with Astrid in several
EU projects. I also worked at RGB, actually, for
some time.
And I'm wondering, how can all these
platforms be integrated so that we don't
need to learn all these acronyms? I
cannot even remember all the acronyms at this point.
Maybe because I'm not a taxonomist by training, but rather an
ecologist. So I'm struggling a bit with
all these platforms.
I also have some questions about abundance, because it
seems that most of these platforms, it hasn't been
specified really, but my impression is that it's based on
presence, absence,
and not on abundance. And I think that may be a gap,
because that has also a lot of importance for
environmental management, which organisms are
dominating, who
of them are rare,
and we have the red list, of course.
So I'm just throwing out
some fire here.
So is there any solution to this jungle?
Thank you very much. And you can give it immediately to Olaf.
Lykke.
Lykke. Thank you very much.
It happens to be that I'm a jungle expert.
On trees, that is. But
no,
I like it a lot because our broader community
has
a disease, and this is called the acronym soup
And that is really difficult to understand from the
outside.
So that
is our problem that we will solve for you.
I think one of the things that we are doing together is to exactly do
this, to connect our systems better so that as a user,
you can go seamlessly from A to B.
Now,
the differences are still there because we have different purposes.
And if we would put all the purposes into one initiative,
that sounds really nice, but it's actually really complex.
So we rather have each one of our niches, but
make sure that we are speaking the same languages
totally. So that is machine to machine, human to machine,
human to human. So,
yeah. And about abundance, perhaps,
if you
go to sites like GBIF, it's
not only presence, absence.
You can actually find real sample-based data,
and abundances as well.
Thank you very much.
Yeah. I just want to add to this. Excellent point.
Abundance is super important. I think
we can ask Helen. One of the reasons she
developed this was to have high-quality data from freshwaters.
And of course, you can enter abundance there, and you
should also push it to GBIF.
Yeah. And this is also my answer to the second question.
Of course, GBIF is the unifying everything in
everything, and this is exactly what we are trying to do.
So in the end, if we all agree on the
standards and push our data there, we will have high-quality
data in GBIF. And the other small things, you don't
need to remember the names. They are just vehicles, okay?
Fine for us.
But we need to do the homework and actually create this high-quality
data and push it. And one last thing, we were discussing to have
a GBIF-hosted portal, which is an excellent tool to show
freshwater biodiversity. And once we have the FADA list, I think we
may even be there to do that.
But that then only includes all the data that people actually published,
so publish.
Thanks, Vanessa.
Helen, would you like to reply?
I think there is a question still.
Ah, there is a question from
Yuri.
Just answers.
An answer, even better.
I am the person who has answers more than questions.
So
in present time, you do not need to sip this soup of
acronyms. That is the stupidest way to
build projects
dispersed through acronyms. Ask Google
Gemini
particular questions and add to your prompt,
"Please give me answers based on credible sources."
You immediately
will have
abstract and link to appropriate resource,
whether to the Catalog of Life, to GBIF, to FADA, to WoRMS, and
other things. So it's my opinion and my experience how
modern search engines help us to navigate
trustable resources.
About FADA, what I would do
in addition, just pay attention that
if you are
building checklist for
freshwater species in a group which already included
in ISIS or in WoRMS, because WoRMS it's not only
about marine species. They accepted the reason
that if marine species is the biggest part of your taxon,
please also pay attention and include terrestrial and freshwater
species. So they already have this.
And if you are working in such group, which is not obligatory
freshwater,
try to do this inside such
aggregators
and accept their classifications.
Because I do not want to see different conflicting
classifications for marine species, for terrestrial species, and
for freshwater. So use the same classification.
Talk to your colleagues from another ecological domain.
Thank you, Yuri.
I would like to give you straight away.
I just wanted to say that WoRMS, maybe it sort of disappeared in the
message, but WoRMS was there to pick up the checklist when FADA sort of
went in hibernation. Yeah. So we are very thankful to them.
We have had many
talks about how the new FADA and WoRMS will interact and so on, and
they made it quite clear that they are not really interested in
harvesting all the insect data from FADA. Yeah.
And that is 60% of the FADA diversity.
So there will be some differences, but the collaboration is definitely there,
and that's what we need. Like what Astrid said in the beginning, we don't need more
databases. We need more interoperability and to
maintain the databases we have.
Please.
Hello. Yes. Thank you. My name is Bernard, and I'm also part of the
Norwegian
Institute of Water Research. And so it was really interesting to learn
about this FADA, and it's still very new to me, but I wanted to touch
on the
quality and what you accept in, because in Norway we have
a lot of almost startups that do the
environmental consultancy firms.
And so they're not connected to the herbarium.
Sometimes a botanist
is better trained outside of the academia as well.
So I'm not saying that it's a bad thing, but
It's somewhat unregulated, and I wanted to hear what your thoughts
about what are you open to taking into FADA,
such as water plant surveys from
a
large variety of sources?
Mm-hmm.
Anybody wants to react to that?
So Bernhard is also going to give a talk, so come back to the second
session.
Oh, okay.
It's a very hard thing to answer. Of course, we want
data, but we don't want to have misinformation.
So I very much agree with you. I think we are building on the
community that we have. There's a certain trust
in the scientific monitoring, also the EU monitoring, maybe.
So, we want to focus on that data. And the only
thing I can maybe give as a short answer is if we take
these other data sets, there should be
biodiversity data quality control mechanisms in
place. We already had a session on that, and it was excellent.
We will look at that. The other thing is community, always
community. So if someone can flag that this
specific data provider is suspicious or whatever,
it would be way easier for us to get that feedback. I'm not an expert.
I cannot decide that. So having more community
involvement would help.
Yeah, maybe just to add on this, in terms of taxonomy and
species identification, as you have seen, we get
a lot of stuff on GBIF that is not correct, actually.
And the only idea that I was discussing recently with
Vanessa is that we might add a tagging to the species,
how reliable it is identifiable by an expert,
by a normal person, or by a layperson, so to say,
or by a consultancy. So maybe having a kind of
traffic light system, and then if you see there is
a species that is flagged in red, so meaning it can only be
identified as adult by an expert, and you have it in your data set,
then it's up on you that you exclude it for your
analysis.
As moderator,
I have to show you this. Thank you everybody for being there.
And please come back after the break.
And can the presenters of this session all stay here for a
picture, please? Thank you very much.
Careful.
... meeting
held by Vanessa Bremmerij and Sami Domisch.
And he will talk about a collaborative perspective on a globally
standardized river basin name database.
Daniel, all yours.
Yeah. Okay, thanks.
Just quick audio test. Aha, okay.
I don't see what I'm
showing here. Okay, yeah. I was warned about this, but in life it's
always slightly different. So
who can manage the slides then? Should I have to say, "Next slide,
please," or how does that work?
Because, well, here I don't see that thing, so I don't know how I can actually
advance it. Can anyone help me out? I'm playing around.
Press Enter. Enter? I'm entering some unknown-- No, now
I'm seeing the news here. Someone please assist me.
So I'm starting with an introduction, which basically
looks at what is a drainage basin. I guess most of you
know. But since we're doing taxonomy in
biology, the names and the things are not always the same.
And
we have the same problem for the drainage basins, actually
I can just-
Unfortunately, I can't because do you have a PowerPoint?
No, I don't have PowerPoint. I could download the PowerPoint if that's necessary,
but I was actually trying to use the PDF in order to
avoid trouble. Now I'm in trouble. Maybe here is the PowerPoint.
What's your name?
Daniel.
And family name?
Mietchen.
It should be actually in the name. It was the
last downloaded file on this machine.
And it is on the internet, but I can't show what
this screen share. Anyway, so drainage basins.
We have the
issue that water comes from above, it falls
down in a certain
spot, and then it moves by gravity and through other processes,
and eventually it lands in the ocean.
There is a lot of things in between that involves rivers.
And then
when we want to analyze those rivers, we have multiple options to do this.
There is the geosciences way of doing it, which is basically putting everything on
a grid.
And then
the grid has different sizes that are basically determined by the measurement
method,
not necessarily by biology, and that is important.
And then
in other ways, we could
try to build something that is not grid-based, but more based on the
structure of the river or some other characteristics.
Still things happening here? Okay.
So yeah, I don't have all the slides in my head, but much of it.
Oh, yeah, we can do with the outline.
Actually, you can all download this, in principle.
It's on Zenodo,
which is what we did to get the file here.
Now, what am I supposed to do now? Oh, yes. So yeah.
I wanted to have a definition. There is one definition up here,
which basically tells you what a drainage basin is.
And then we have an example of the major
drainage basins on the planet.
And
then, of course, you can imagine that this can be scaled
down, and there are existing systems that can
describe those
river basins. So the most popular of those is the
Pfafstetter coding system, which basically looks
at the
four main tributaries to a river and then
divides the area around the river based on
relative
position to those four main ones.
And this system is actually quite widely used in a number of popular
databases, geodatabases. It does not know anything
about biology.
And also it doesn't handle the naming issue, actually.
It doesn't handle any subsurface features like karst
rivers. It doesn't do anything related to changes
in water levels if a river runs dry or if there is a flood
or things like this. And yeah, it
doesn't handle complex branching patterns well.
It assumes that there is perfect branching, basically.
So let's take one step back. Yeah, I already briefly outlined this
thing here. In the geosciences, essentially everything happens on a grid.
In biology, rarely anything happens on the grid.
But if we want to
bring the geo and the bio data together, we have to think
about mechanisms by which we can translate this.
And this talk here is not to give
answers. It is essentially asking questions.
To what extent can TDWG or TDWG associated structures
assist with bridging this gap so that we can
leverage the strong ecosystem of tooling
that exists in geosciences in order to help address
biological, ecological issues. So for instance, if I
have found
a
species of fish somewhere, how can I easily and
in a standardized fashion express that this belongs to that river basin and
not to that river basin? And
yeah, so that's the mindset that we should have here.
And now I actually lost track of time, so please someone warn me when I'm
getting out.
And so I wanted to approach this from a local perspective.
So we had the global perspective. We've seen the major
river basins. Now we want to start from the other end.
We are in Oslo, and we were at the Munch Museum yesterday, and actually, I was
glad to find out that he actually painted about some of the local
rivers.
And so Akerselva, roughly that should
be
how it is pronounced. And there are other rivers here in Oslo, and
there's lots of water in Norway.
And yeah, lots of those things have names.
And then also the area that is drained by the Akerselva
also has names, and that's the river basin that we are going to use as our
example. So if you go into some databases, there's the AquaInfo databases
that you may have heard about and Vanessa is involved with.
And so on the left-hand side here, you can basically see all the
Akerselva river and its tributaries,
basically expressed as segments in a grid-based
world.
And then you can basically
draw some lines around this, which are the drainage
boundaries or the basin delineations,
and that defines the area that is the basin.
Right? And in principle, you can do this for every
single river, but the naming is not clear.
So there we are at the more or less the taxonomy kind of thing, but we
don't have the nomenclature yet. And so the question
is how can we name this in a useful fashion that works both globally and across
multiple languages? Then how can you express that
in Darwin Core or other similar systems such that it is
useful in ecological contexts and can be-
... recorded as being related to
the river basin. Now,
another aspect of this talk here is the collaborative aspect.
Because this is a global issue and multilingual and
cross-disciplinary, the question is, okay, which databases are
able to handle these kinds of things? And Wikidata is a primary candidate.
There have been similar talks about other issues
that involve multidisciplinary and multilingual and global
collaboration. And so I'm basically looking at
the Akerselva again from the perspective of Wikidata.
So what does Wikidata tell us about the Akerselva?
Well, it's an instance of a river. No surprise here.
It also picks out the
source of that particular river and also the mouth, where does it empty
into?
And importantly, highlighted here in blue, the drainage basin that
belongs to it, which has the name Nordmarksvassdraget,
something like this. And
that's the kind of thing that we want to have, and we want to have this for every
single river on the planet, no matter what its native language
is and how permanent it is and whether it
still exists or things like this, or whether people build a dam
around it.
And we want to also
map this to other identifier systems.
So for instance,
the river itself here has an identifier.
Can I move the mouse here? No.
So you see the drainage basin itself has an identifier in the Regine
database, a Norwegian database for river basins.
And then
the river, Akerselva, has an identifier in the ELVIS database,
which is just for rivers and not for river basins.
And at the bottom line, I linked three Wikidata queries, which
basically tell us Wikidata knows about 431
items with statements involving drainage basin, and also the
same number with statements involving this Regine database.
Basically, all the drainage basins that Wikidata knows are
essentially from Norway,
and that's just how it is.
And I didn't do anything about this.
And there are 1,066 items with statements involving
this ELVIS ID, which is for rivers in Norway.
So at least we have a good starting point with Norway and things, but then this
Norwegian database doesn't tell us anything about rivers that don't touch
Norway, basically. But we want to have a similar kind of
setup.
Now,
we're
zooming out a little bit. We're still touching Norway, but already Norway
have multiple languages.
And Norway also has neighboring countries that happen to have
furthermore languages. And so the same river that touches Norway,
but also Finland and Russia, has multiple languages.
Already the river. And then suppose we want to define that river
basin, which one of those languages should we use as our basis?
Probably not a single one of those, or maybe should we?
This is the kind of question that we want to answer.
And
then we can go further. There are edge cases.
So for instance, there are rivers that exist that are
seasonally dry,
or there are droughts
that also affect rivers to the extent that some rivers actually split
during a drought, or
certain structures that are normally underwater in the river, they come out.
Hunger stones like this one are an example.
Then what about subsurface karst rivers?
Seasonal flooding, which might actually bring together river systems that are
normally ecologically separated.
Then permanent or transient or seasonal flow reversal.
There are some systems where the flow is in one direction during certain
periods of time and then another direction in other periods of time.
That certainly has dramatic
effects on the ecology. Then what about the connectivity of groundwater?
What about weather phenomena like atmospheric rivers?
What about paleohydrology?
Or dams, human-built, beaver-built, or riverbed mining
or similar things. Historic river courses.
Maybe we want to use some historic data to infer climate change or other things,
and we have to deal with historic names and historic courses of the rivers.
Historic samples. When they say, "Oh, I took the sample near the river of
so-and-so," then we have to take into account that the river back then
was there, where it is not today. And what about languages that don't
have a written tradition, just an oral tradition? How do we treat them?
Yeah, lots of edge cases, but I think we should start with the main ones.
And now,
the question is, how do we map this to TADWiG?
And here I have to say, I've never been directly involved in running any
TADWiG activities. I've participated here and there.
And so what I did was basically just naively looking at the
TADWiG community page, and I see
MG, IG, and TG. I looked all of these up.
So MG is for maintenance, IG for interest, and TG for
task groups. And then I looked
which one of those might actually have an interest.
I marked them in green. If any of you have knowledge
about any of those entities and you could answer the question whether that
is relevant, whether that's active and interested, well, that's the kind of
conversation we want to have. And also, if there is anything outside
TADWiG, like this Fachdaten system that I mentioned
before, and you're aware that there are activities that would address this
naming issue, then that's the kind of conversation we would also like to have.
And then
in the maps that I briefly showed,
there is OpenStreetMap. In OpenStreetMap, you also have multiple layers.
It can express lots of things, and it is collaborative just the same as
Wikidata. It is also tightly integrated with Wikidata.
It is multilingual and global and so on.
So to what extent can we collaborate with the OpenStreetMap community on those
things? And with that
I want to move to the next steps. So one of the next steps is actually tonight,
again, at the Akerselva River, there will be this Elvelangs i
Fakkeles
event
that the organizer already mentioned.
And
so tonight you can experience that.
And while you walk along the river, you can think about how we should rename this
drainage basin,
and sing along and maybe come up with a song that solves this issue.
The second thing, there will be an unconference tomorrow
where I'm proposing to spend some time thinking about this issue,
preferably with multiple perspectives and different experiences.
And some of the things we could be thinking about then is
use cases.
And you can bring your own use case, but some use case could be, how
do I record
that I found a certain species in a certain aquatic environment
if that aquatic environment is changing over time, right?
Then freshwater invasions, because they tend not to follow the
grid, but to follow the actual
water, basically.
And then
we could think about multilingual data modeling.
We could start with something rather simple like Akerselva, or we
could look at something rather complicated like the Mekong.
Or we could look at hunger stones and
what species live on hunger stones when they are underwater or when they're
exposed, things like this. With that, I'm thanking you, and I'm
hoping that there will be discussion about this.
Thank you very much
for one of the most challenging and surprising talks that I've ever seen in
freshwater biology. Very interesting.
And congratulations how you handled the challenges in the beginning of your
talk.
So sorry.
It doesn't work. You were wonderful. Doesn't it work?
No, it doesn't. Now it does. Yeah, now it does?
Okay. Don't touch it. Okay.
Any questions for Daniel?
Yes, please.
Thanks for raising all these interesting questions.
I have a question to the
microphone.
In the meantime, while you're thinking about and I have the microphone, if anyone's
aware of people who should know about this and are not in the room, please think
about that and let us know or let them know and things like this.
Thank you, Austi.
My question is whether you are aware of the
European
Water Information System?
Roughly, yes, but it's not global enough to-
No, it's not global
...fulfil our purpose.
But for Europe, there has been a lot of work done on this, and there
is a formally accepted division of river basins
in Europe where all the countries have to outline
geographically the-
Do you know how to... Keep talking.
Keep talking.
What's going on?
No, it is on. But because-
You could do it like this because-
Okay.
... I have to give this up away anyway.
Now it works again.
I think it works again. Thank you.
So I suggest that... I don't know what's happening with this one.
I think our technician is busy with-
I suggest that you consult the WISE database, which is on
EEA's, the European Environment Agency's
webpage,
where you can see the list of river basin
districts, and then within those, also single river
basins. And all the countries have also delivered
shapefiles-
Yeah
... to show the actual extension of all the river basins in
their own country. And for transboundary river basins,
the neighboring countries have to collaborate to agree
on this. So I think we have come quite far in
Europe, but I don't know how it is in other continents.
Yeah.
Well, basically you summarized it.
Yeah, there's a lot of things that we can use, and there are also individual
countries and some groups of countries that have made good progress, but we don't
have anything global.
Yeah, so that's the current state.
And maybe there could be a TADWiG
structure that could build on the European experience, look around, what does
Vietnam do and so on. And
then at some point, we have a system that actually works.
Thank you, Daniel. Anybody else
would like to make a statement?
Thank you very much for a very interesting talk. Thank you.
Then for the next talk, is going to be given by Bernard
Glauskedalen.
And here is my other challenge. Somebody disappeared from the--
No, she's on there. It's saved. So I needed to say
that the second author
also should be mentioned and was not on the slide, but it's on the slide now, so I
don't have to worry about this. So
Bernard,
you're going to talk about From Lost in Transition to Fit for Purpose Data:
Why Ecologists and Conservation Practice Still Need Grouping and
CF?
Even the title changed. So again, From Lost in
Translation to Fit for Purpose Data: Why Ecologists and Conservation
Practice Still Need Grouping and Uncertainties.
All yours.
Yes.
Thank you for that. So Natalie and me, we work at
the Norwegian Institute of Water Research.
I do plant surveys,
and Natalie works with our databases.
So we are colleagues but from different sections.
And
our start is
some examples of some discussions that would be ...
are occurring within our section that we wanted to
showcase
for the audience.
Yes. Let's start. Would you take the next slide?
We should switch places.
I need the computer.
Okay. Yeah. So that picture is my background.
Oh, yeah.
That's her background.
Okay. Let's switch.
It's very important.
Oh, hi, Natalie. Good to see you. I hoped to run into an IT
developer today. Could you help me a moment?
Of course, Bernard.
You see, there was this water plant, Sparganium angustifolium, that I wanted
to registrate in the database. Can you do that?
Of course.
There you go.
There.
No, this isn't right. The record should show
that the plant was sterile. You see, this species can
only be 100% separated from the other species in this
genus when you have the flower, and I didn't have that.
So you should put a cf. before the species name to indicate this
uncertainty.
Okay.
Computer says no. Sorry, I can't do it.
But this is a very common approach. We always put cf.
to show that it's not a certain identification.
You must be able to do this.
See, I can't. The system won't allow.
I can maybe registrate just at genus level,
or maybe you
have to be sure of what you're doing. Are you sure about the species?
I'm sure of what I'm doing. And we would lose a lot of precision on
the data if we put it to genus level.
It is correct that we can't be using it for such a species
distribution pattern all over Norway for this species, but we can still
use this record to, say, trend populations inside of lakes,
and
we can use this to indicate the ecological condition of the lake based
on the species assemblage compared to tolerant and sensitive with
eutrophication, which is where the funding comes for my work.
You know what? It's better to lose the cf.
if you can't include it, because that's where the money comes from.
Yeah, lose the cf.
Okay. Sparganium angustifolium it is.
Thank you. Now, I also have this other water plant that I want you to record.
So this is an Utricularia vulgaris plus put it in.
Okay.
Done.
Person change.
Hi, I'm Natalie from NIVA.
I work with the red list for water plants in Norway.
And I see your records of water plants, and there's a lot of them, but I
just can't use your record of Utricularia vulgaris.
Why not?
Well, the record doesn't state if it has flowers or not.
You really can't separate Utricularia vulgaris compared to Utricularia
australis without the flowers.
Bernard.
Okay.
This is the data that he gave me. I just input the data.
Sorry, it's really not my problem.
You data people.
Okay. I'll try to help. We can bump it to genus
or maybe delete these records.
Yes. Bump it to genus. Yes, this is the correct way.
Okay.
Back to Bernard.
Natalie, I just saw that my records had gone up to genus.
What happened with my Utricularia vulgaris?
Yeah. We had a data quality check, and then the experts
left a note for you. "The record does not state if flowers were
present. This species cannot be separated from Utricularia
australis by flowers."
By flowers. But we never find flowers on these plants.
And
we would lose so much ecological data then because there are a lot of
other species in the same genus that we are able to separate out, so
it's a super common approach to group these species.
This really shouldn't have been removed.
Okay, but how can I fix this? Can we classify it in
some way that acknowledges that we are unsure about the identification but
keeps the species?
Yes.
You put in Utricularia vulgaris agg.
That's an aggregate to indicate that this is a grouping above the species
level. Yes, put in the agg.
Agg. Mm-hmm. Our database does not support
aggregate.
There is a text field here. Can I just add the information that it was
sterile instead?
Yes. Just do that, and add in the...
Thank you.
Now, since we have these hyper-correct people, I have
another registration I want you to put in for me, a white water lily.
All right.
Super common. And to be absolutely correct, you can put it in
as Nymphaea alba col. As is a common
approach, that we include the hybrid species, Nymphaea
candida,
in our records of white water lily. So please put this in col.
Put it in col.
I cannot do that with our database.
No, but this is
very odd.
Last resort.
Well, last resort then. Put it in as Nymphaea alba
sensu lato, in the broad sense, which is to indicate all these
species, like the broad species concept compared to sensu stricto. Yes.
I can't do that.
You can't do that. Yes. Well, then you have it your way and just put
in whatever you want. I'm done with this
So that was our sketch to indicate our problems.
And within this, we wanted to show that identification is
super messy.
So we might want to ask ourselves how correct do we
want to be
in the records that we put out?
And the incentive really
isn't there by the paying customer to make things verifiable and
to be able to look back on it.
And at least for my work,
making it really hard for me to being able to use other
botanists' records for
considering what species was there and so on, because I don't know what they
identified, what they included in their names.
And just as an example here, you see this is the herbarium in Oslo, and
this is a very common example of a water plant where you have three different
names put by three different people on the same poster, and we have
up to six of these.
And for several of the groups,
the first name that was given can be as low as 6%,
but 94% of the records can be identified as a separate
species when an expert is going and looking at the same revision.
Yes. I promise our databases in NIVA aren't that bad.
We just wanted to make a little bit funny for you.
We do have ways of recording uncertainty and
grouping taxonomy, but the problem comes when we try to standardize our data
exchange and publish to a Norwegian institution.
For example, sometimes we lose part of the data, and
sometimes data gets transformed, and it's not exactly what was observed in the
field. So one thing that I learned from my colleagues,
ecologists, is that being able to use CF in order
at such identifications is quite important.
Then I had a look at our data. I selected a couple
datasets from our very large dataset.
These ones
span from the '60s until last year.
And I thought I was going to find a few more observations that
contain CF
in our databases. But for
water plants, I found 0.1% of the
observations in the dataset I was looking, and for benthic algae, it
was 1.1%. Then I was thinking, "Ugh,
okay, maybe this has something to do on
the requirements that we have for reporting," right?
And it's not exactly how we record it on the field.
So I had a look at what we have. Oh, yeah.
Are these
observations rare, or is something funny happening there?
Yes. And then what I observed is that we had
information. It's just that when we were reporting it, we were
losing some of it. So sometimes we would just say that where we would
report an uncertain identification as certain, other times, we would
just report the genus. And we had some also different ways of
working when we had aggregates, often using pseudo data for
reporting it to Familia.
So I have a question for you.
Maybe you can help us because we are building this new database at NIVA.
And my question is this one: how should biodiversity systems
represent uncertainty and taxonomical grouping without
losing ecological meaning
in a consistent way? Because what happen is we have this representation, but it's
different sometimes from domain to domain.
We would like to have this standardized, and each domain has their preference,
and they push towards their preference.
It would be nice to have some
good guidelines with this. And then, yeah, this is important for us because if
we cannot express this uncertainty in a
consistent way, we're going to have loss of ecological
information or false certainty, which we do not want.
And thank you.
Talking about surprises.
Congratulations, and thank you very much.
So
there is a question for all of you.
Is there anybody who feels
up to
giving an opinion? It is certainly a
very valid question.
Olaf?
Olaf.
It's a very good question, I would say.
And I only can express my opinion here.
I think these things need to remain with the data. They need to...
Hello?
She's working on it.
So
my opinion is that these things need to remain with the data,
otherwise we run into trouble, and our databases
or what ends up in GBIF will never be correct.
But
I cannot imagine that you can have it harmonized
throughout different organism groups.
So the plant people, they have much more of these
aggregates and
stuff, and
invertebrate persons, we just have the CF.
So I think
our
infrastructures need to be flexible here.
I think you cannot harmonize it across different organism groups.
Mm-hmm.
Dimitri.
It works? Yes, it works.
Congratulations with your presentation.
I think that we all should take the same approach in the next Taxawic.
Would be fun.
Maybe not all. Maybe not all.
Maybe not all.
I had two things in mind, all the extra things that would
make it much more difficult if you work with the taxonomic backbones,
using in the way you want. And then another thing, and
maybe you saw the talk of Peter De Smet, who talked and
briefly had the idea, and I talked with him before on, we have these
coordinate uncertainty meters.
And he was thinking about maybe we should have
something similar
on the determination of the species.
I don't think it would solve everything.
Maybe it's a start. So I suggest talk to Peter De Smet.
What was the word you said? They had this-
So,
identification uncertainty.
Yeah.
Mm.
And think about what we do with AI recognition.
They are never 100% sure.
Mm.
But it is an important value, and it's a value that you can
give to the user of the data. Okay? It's not the same if you talk
about a human making a determination, but it might give
you already some indication. It will not solve the problem, and maybe
it's
interesting stuff to talk about or to think about.
Let me do the running this time.
Thank you.
They don't pay me enough for this.
Here you are. Yeah.
Thanks very much, and thanks for a great talk.
So we've got a system with our biodiversity
information management system where we actually have an additional column that
we add in identification certainty.
So
if it was experts identified or high, medium, low, or
unknown. So then at least if you see something that's odd and you look
there and you see, oh, the identification accuracy is
unknown or low, then you probably wouldn't or
shouldn't use it. Thanks.
Thank you.
So that means
false certainty or loss of ecological information. What would you choose?
Uncertainty.
So just-
So just follow the question then.
You said you don't enter the data, yeah?
No. So we still add it.
Yeah.
So then it's up to you to choose. So you get the full data set back-
Mm-hmm
... and you can go down and you can find all the records that are either
unknown or have a low
certainty, and then you can choose yourself to actually exclude them.
So we also have additional field in our data set where we have a thing called
an include or an exclude. So if I've worked through the data and I've
generated a checklist and I realize that that is
truly a misidentification, even though
if the certainty might be low or unknown, I can then add
exclude with my reason. So I can say, "This species was
actually completely misidentified," or whatever the case is, so that in
future when I pull that same checklist, I don't include it
again. And the reason why we did this is that
some of our colleagues did a whole invasive alien analysis over the
last 10 years, and they kept coming into the same problems with and then
saying, "Yes, but the last time we did this, we threw the species out and
we can't remember now why we did it."
Mm-hmm.
So now we've adapted it like that so that we can hopefully
have some continuation going forward.
Excellent. Thank you very much. So I suggest we keep this in mind for later
and
continue. May I give you this?
And continue this discussion.
And so last but very much not least,
the next talk is by
Anne Luke Solheim.
Perfect.
Thank you.
And the title is, "How Does Human Impact Change Species
Diversity and Composition in 50 Types of Inland Water Habitats?"
Sorry, I won't have a microphone.
50 types,
wow.
Okay.
I'm
probably going to have a very boring
presentation compared to what you just saw.
It's not at the same level of entertainment at all,
and a completely different topic, moreover,
which may not be
so interesting for all of you who are working mainly with taxonomy here,
but I will give it a try even so.
So the main question I am trying to address in my
presentation is, how does human impact change
species diversity and composition
in 50 types of inland water habitats?
And this work was done for the European Environment
Agency
within
the European Topic Center for Biodiversity and
Ecosystems,
and in collaboration with some of my colleagues that you
see the names on the first line.
And also Ute Jandt from the Martin Luther University
in Germany.
And I will tell a bit more about
this
shortly. And then how do I move this stuff? Enter?
Ah.
So the background for my talk and the context
is based on UNIS. How many of you have heard about
UNIS?
Ah,
not bad. So UNIS is the European Nature
Information System for habitat classification, which is
managed by the EEA,
and the aim is to facilitate harmonized descriptions and collection of
data across Europe through the use of criteria
for habitat identification. So this is trying to link the biology to
the habitats.
And for the freshwater part of UNIS, it was a very
weird system
up until recently,
which was some very
wide
habitat types and some extremely narrow ones.
So it was screaming for a revision.
So we were commissioned to do this work over some years
to try to link the UNIS,
the Water Framework Directive, and the Habitats Directive.
So the content of my presentation is to present an extract
of the report which gives all the details.
If you're interested, you can go into that link that is seen on
the slide here
if you want to know more of the details.
So the main focus in this presentation is
how do the biological community that are found in
natural, unimpacted waters differ from those
where human impact has really made a difference?
So first slide about the different habitat types that have
been now suggested to
substitute the old one.
And on
the top of both these two parts of the slide
for standing waters, which are lakes, ponds, and pools, and running
waters, which are rivers and streams on the right side,
we have identified more than 20
habitat types, and they are mostly based
on the broad types identified for the Water Framework
Directive.
And we have added also some rare types to
capture more of the specific habitats that are listed in the
Habitats Directive.
And those are shaded out in the bottom of each of these
panels because I don't have time to talk about them.
And those have been mostly the focus of the co-author
Ute Jandt.
So I'm sorry, Ute, if you are listening, that I won't have
time to talk so much about this.
So if you look at the type descriptors in the bullet
points on both the panels, you see that the type
descriptors that are important for the biology are more or less the
same for lakes as for rivers, which was a little bit
surprising to me.
So,
its altitude,
its calcium content, and its humic content
and size
in both cases.
The data source and the biological communities that we have included
is shown on this slide. First, the data source was
actually not from GBIF or from Catalogue of Life or
from any other of these major
databases, but it was from EU research
projects.
Two of them actually. REBECCA was the first one, and then WISER
took over.
And this was a period from 2004 to 2011
where these two projects were done.
And in those projects, the different
partners compiled species-level or at least
taxon-specific information
for
most of the groups of organisms in freshwater.
And also had additional physicochemical data, which is important in
order to try to understand what level of impact
is these communities actually having in each
case. So it's more than
thousands of lakes and rivers that are included in this
database.
The groups of organisms is shown here.
I don't need to repeat them for you. You can read for yourself.
I also want to say that the taxonomic harmonization was actually done
mainly by expert meetings and workshops,
where the experts in each of these groups were sitting together around a
table and discussing how should we harmonize the taxonomy.
And they came up with lists that were agreed among them.
These were also used in the intercalibration work for ecological
status in the Water Framework Directive.
So it had major impacts for the whole implementation process
of the Water Framework Directive, this work that was done on the
very basic level.
We however, made sure that these expert
lists were supported by international tools
such as AlgaeBase and also Astrid's
fantastic freshwaterecology.info.
That was especially valuable for benthic invertebrates, of course, but also
for several other groups.
So
the methods we use to assess taxonomic composition is
very simplified here in this slide to three steps.
First, we divided the data into natural water bodies versus
impacted ones,
and then we assessed the similarity of taxonomic composition
using NMDS and clustering. And you see just an example plot on
the upper right for aquatic vegetation in
the lakes,
comparing different habitats for which we had sufficient data sets.
And then we identified the characteristic common and dominant
taxa
for each of the habitat types
and made tables like you see on the lower right,
specifying the habitat on the left side and then the
family names and the taxon name to the lowest possible
level.
And then we had
the two columns for reference rivers or natural rivers, and
then the two columns for impacted rivers next to it.
What you can probably see, even from
behind here in the back, you can probably see that there are
many more taxa occurring in the reference rivers than in the
impacted ones.
Which was a surprise to me,
but it's probably due to...
I will tell you why this is happening later in my next slides.
But this was a general pattern. We found many more characteristic
species in the natural waters than in the impacted waters.
So I will summarize the results now for lakes.
First in what are the natural communities, how can we characterize
those.
And we see that
for the habitat descriptors, we have almost the same as I
mentioned earlier. It's alkalinity, humic substances,
altitude, and depth, which are really important for
structuring the species composition of the different
groups of biology here.
Species richness increased with size and decreased with
altitude, and that was what we found for all the three groups.
And the lowest row in the table here shows the
characteristic common and dominant taxa in these natural
lakes,
which are just like textbook knowledge more or less.
And I was surprised that this came out of this data analysis we did.
More mixotrophic chrysophytes in siliceous lakes
at higher altitudes and in humic lakes.
More autotrophic diatoms, chlorophytes, and large
dinoflagellates in calcareous lakes, in clear lakes, and in
lowland lakes. That was for phytoplankton.
And for aquatic vegetation, we found more isoetids in siliceous
lakes, more charophytes and elodeids in
calcareous lakes, and more nymphaeids in humic lakes.
And for fish, we found more cyprinids in calcareous lowland lakes
and more salmonids in siliceous lakes and at higher
altitudes.
So what's the human impact doing to this species
composition? First of all, I have to excuse myself for not having
a row with species richness here. That was because that
result was really messy. We didn't get
any clear
result for the difference between natural lakes and
impacted lakes concerning species richness.
That may also have to do with the uncertainty of the taxonomic
determinations that was in the database that we used.
So I only have information about the effect on taxonomic
composition for these different groups
of biology.
First of all, the general
pattern was that the similarity increased between the
types.
They became less specific for all the three groups of
organisms.
We also, for phytoplankton, found more dominant taxa, fewer
characteristic and common taxa, and especially less chrysophytes.
While the other groups that are listed in bold font at the bottom of
the row for phytoplankton, they increased quite
clearly in most of the habitats.
For aquatic vegetation, the only systematic response
we found across the habitats was that the isoetids
became less abundant, or they occurred in
fewer water bodies, let's say.
And for fish, we found
actually no characteristic species in impacted lakes of any type,
and more cyprinids and fewer salmonids.
Now for rivers, the main results for
natural rivers
is that the type descriptors that are important for the
biology are the same for all the four groups, with
the exception of fish.
So we have altitude and alkalinity being important for phytobenthos,
aquatic vegetation, and benthic invertebrates.
And fish also responded to catchment
size and also to region, which is not so strange.
That's due to fish migration, biogeographic patterns.
And also flow, river flow is important.
Here we see for natural waters that the species
richness increases with catchment size and with alkalinity
for phytobenthos and also for benthic invertebrates.
While we got increases with catchment size and decreases with
altitude for aquatic vegetation and for fish.
And the communities are characterized by
phytobenthos, more diatoms, chlorophytes, and
cyanobacteria.
Sorry.
It's falling down.
Let me help you.
Yeah, please. Thanks. I'm soon finished.
This.
Okay. Thank you. Oh, maybe you haven't heard what I've said so far.
Oh, yeah. No.
Okay. That's good.
So the natural communities were characterized for
phytobenthos by more diatoms in calcareous rivers,
also more chlorophytes and cyanobacteria.
While in siliceous rivers, we found more red algae.
Two minutes? Yes. And
for aquatic vegetation, we found that lowland rivers have many
characteristic and common elodeids, lemnaids, and nymphaiads,
while mid-altitude rivers have more bryophytes and charophytes.
And for benthic invertebrates, we found a lot more
calcium-requiring organisms in calcareous rivers, of course,
than we find in siliceous rivers, such as snails,
amphipods, and mussels. And we also found more stoneflies in
highland than in lowland rivers. And finally, for fish,
calcareous lowland rivers have more cyprinids than siliceous rivers.
And the cyprinid species increases with catchment size and decreases a
lot with increasing
altitude. I'm sorry for reading out what's on the slides, but
it's just so difficult to remember all these details.
It's a 200-page report.
I'm trying to summarize it in 15 minutes.
The impacts of human pressures on the
taxonomic composition in rivers, and for rivers, they have
much more multiple pressures than for lakes, which are mainly
impacted by eutrophication. In rivers, you also have the harder
morphological changes with embankments and barriers
and flow changes all the time. So for
all the groups, we found increased similarity between most types,
and we found for vegetation, large decreases in the number of
characteristic and common taxa, also the same for benthic
invertebrates. And also for fish, we found an
increase in the number of dominant species of fish.
So
this cartoon is just the only entertainment I have
in this presentation. Sorry for that.
But it says that the biology is really upset about the human
pressures, and the scientists and the law is trying to
support the biology. But the sector
authorities do not always agree. So there is this
fight, and that's why we probably do not see much improvement in
the water framework directive ecological status since the
start of the directive back in 2000,
actually, where it started,
and the first river basin management plans were delivered in
2009. And since then, it has been on a
standstill with about 60% in less than good status and
40% in good or better status. And this is shown on the map,
talking to you with the river basins.
These are the formally agreed
river basin districts of Europe, and within each of these, you
can also find smaller river basins that have
shapefiles
in the WISE database.
So you see where the situation is worst, where the red colors are,
and best where the blue colors are.
So Norway isn't so bad,
fortunately.
So in conclusions, each of the revised habitat types is
truly different from the other habitats for at least one of the
biological communities.
And now I move to the blue part. Healthy waters have
distinct biological communities shaped by geology, altitude, and
size.
And the yellow part, human impact make many
habitats lose their natural distinctness.
Different freshwater habitat types become biologically more similar,
converging towards degraded states with fewer
characteristic species.
Thank you so much for your attention.
Thank you very much. Is there a question for
Anna?
I guess time is out already or in two minutes.
We are nearing the end of our session, but if there is...
So no question for Anna?
Do you remember, Anna,
how you decided on what is the difference between pristine or
reference and impacted?
Yes.
How do you define that from the beginning?
Yes, that was partly already embedded in the database when we
started the work-
Mm-hmm
... for this revision.
Mm-hmm.
And that was
based on the water framework directive classification system of
high, good, moderate, poor, and bad ecological status.
So we grouped the high and good ones
and the moderate, poor, and bad ones into these two different
groups.
Yeah.
And for the rivers, we had to get some help to
identify the
reference rivers
by using GIS tools in one of the
partners in the topic center.
Mm-hmm.
So they were helping us to actually
spatially
assess where are the reference rivers in Europe.
Because in some cases we didn't know the status in that river part
of the database.
Okay.
So we had to get some additional help through this work, and then we
used the officially reported Water Framework Directive status
classification for those water bodies.
Okay.
So.
Excellent.
Yeah.
Thank you very much.
You're welcome.
So now, yeah.
Just a quick question. Is there a way, or did you think about a way to
translate between the old-
I don't hear you well. Can you come a bit closer? I'm getting old.
I will just speak up.
Did you think about a way, or is it even possible to translate
between the old classification and the new classification?
Yes. There has been a huge
crosswalk table made in Excel,
which EEA will publish when it's
definite.
It's been
looking across to the old system, but also looking across
to the habitat types in the Habitats Directive, the Water Framework
Directive broad types, and also the
IUCN classification and even the
MAES classification, if you're familiar with that,
mapping of an assessment of ecosystems and their services.
So it's a very wide Excel table
showing these cross links, but I couldn't put that into report.
But there are much more details in the report if you're interested, so please
feel free to download
that.
Thank you. I will definitely do that.
Okay. Thank you very much.
You're welcome.
Thank you.
So we are coming to the end, as I said, but is there anybody who would like to make
one more comment
about what has been said today? Because we promised you that you could react later
on.
Anybody?
If not, I would like to ask either Vanessa or Astrid, or both, to
make a concluding statement because you have pulled this
whole session together with a little bit of help from
Olav and me. But
any of you two would like to make a concluding session?
Statement.
Does it work? Yeah. I just want to thank everyone who was here
today and
who listened online to us.
I think
we are a minority here as freshwater people.
I think it's super important that we talk about these issues and do get
everything interoperable. So really, thank you for being
here and for presenting. And
yeah, we probably will join this,
how's it called, Elvewalk.
So if anyone is interested in going with us, and maybe
before some dinner, just meet us downstairs.
Vanessa, you want to add something?
Olav, did you want to say something? No?
No.
Thank you.
Okay. Then thank you very much, all of you.